Europe: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The Cretan civilization ended within the first fifty years of this time period but the exact nature and cause of the destruction is not known. Syridon Marinatos, late Inspector General of Antiguities of Greece, believed that Crete was destroyed by a tremendous volcanic action in Thera, the island known anciently as Kalliste and later also as Sartorini. This last eruption of the Thera volcano was followed by massive tidal waves as the island center collapsed, and these waves surged outward perhaps 650 feet high at probably two hundred miles an hour, dealing the settlements of Crete a pulverizing blow. The ash was carried as far as 1600 miles, killing vegetation and choking harbors. The force of this volcanic explosion has been equated with that of 500 to 1,000 atomic bombs. The ash fallout plunged the Aegean Sea area into night for weeks. Total deposits of the ash on the remnant of Thera are still two hundred feet deep and the same ash has been found recently to be a layer seven feet thick some 9,850 feet deep on the floor of the Mediterranean Sea, 87 miles from the volcano. Scandinavian scholars date this tremendous upheaval of the Mediterranean world as late as 1,200 B.C. and feel that the Sea People who roamed the Mediterranean, raiding the coasts of Asia Minor and Egypt were displaced peoples from island and other coastal civilizations destroyed in this great cataclysm. The period is likened by Heyerdahl (Ref. 1) to what he has described as a similar great unknown tumult of just before 3,000 B.C. There is no doubt but that the blast completely changed the Mediterranean, whether it completely destroyed Crete or weakened it for subsequent invasion by Mycenaeans, or whatnot. The Thera explosion was four times greater than the A.D.1,883 Java eruption that took 36,000 lives and spread a cloud of ash around the earth' (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

Arguments still go on about the actual dating of the great Thera incident, some recent revisions of radio-carbon datings indicating that it occurred about 1,600 B.C. and thus could not have had direct bearing on the Cretan demise. Regardless, there is no doubt that even before its final end, Crete had been subjected to devastating attacks in its island territories by the Phoenicians, new masters of the Mediterranean, and to attacks at home by the Mycenaean, "barbarian" Greeks. The latter, perhaps simply following their own warlike instincts for plunder, definitely came ashore on Crete, at least later, and left their marks, destroying whatever remained of all the palaces except Knossos, which they used for their own capital. The Mycenaean rulers wrote their language in Linear B which has now been at least partially deciphered and appears to be a form of ancient Greek. By 1,375 B.C. even Knossos was burned to the ground and whether this was done by rebelling, remnant Minoans or squabbling Mycenaeans chief s, no one knows. A disastrous expedition to Sicily had been undertaken at about that time, and its failure may have led to the fall of the Knossos lords. Still another view, however, is that Knossos remained functional until 1, 150 B.C. when it fell to invading Dorian Greeks. (Ref. 5) The last vestiges of the Cretan or Minoan civilization in their colonies along the coast of Asia Minor were also destroyed at a still later period by Ionian Greeks who then made their own settlements there. Remnants or refugees from the Cretan society are said to have fled to the Palestine coast, where they became known as Philistines1.

The Thera volcano was not the only cataclysmic occurrence of this period. There were earthquakes all over the Mediterranean and even northern Europe while volcanoes erupted in Italy and the Sinai and seismic tidal waves "caused the sea to recede from the land and even sucked out the rivers"2. After 1,100 B.C. the Dorian Greeks, who had charged down the Greek peninsula, crossed over to Crete to repopulate it and become the ancestors of its present population. (Ref. 7) Rhodes was also colonized by Dorians from Argos in the 11th century B.C. (Ref. 8)

GREECE

Mycenaean power was dominant in the Mediterranean at least after 1,400 B.C.3 and their pottery was popular from Italy to the Turkish coast. They used many slaves, especially women who were used in the textile and bronze industries, as well as in private households. Some were captured in war, many were bought. Houses had flushing lavatories and bath rooms supplied with terra cotta pipes and sloping gutters. (Ref. 10) In the 14th century B.C. a giant mound covering a stone tomb was constructed at Mycenae which was 48 feet in diameter, 43 feet high to the tip of the dome and had a doorway topped with a lintel made of a 100 ton stone.

At about the 13th century B.C. at the height of their power and when the Mycenaeans controlled the Aegean world, they suddenly began to fortify all their cities and strengthen their defences, indicating a premonition of disaster. Other Greek speaking tribes had begun to drift down into the Greek peninsula by about 1,500 B.C. but it was not until about 1,300 that they were sufficiently strong to begin to usurp the Mycenaean power, so that by the end of that century the Mycenaean cities and fortresses were in ruins, the art degenerated and the written language (Linear B) had been forgotten. (Ref. 12, 13) 1,250 B.C. is usually given as the traditional date of the Trojan War, with complete collapse of Mycenaea by 1,200, but Cotterell (Ref. 14) gives the latter date as 1,150 B.C.

There were three main tribes of the new, invading Greeks, each with its own variation of the Greek language - lonic, Aeolic and Doric. The Dorians, descending from the upper Balkans about 1,200 B.C. are generally credited with the actual destruction of the Mycenaean Kingdom. They took the best lands with the less favored regions left to the other tribes. Attica became Ionian, along with a group of cities across the Aegean in the central section of the Asia Minor coast, and from these people came the master institution of Greek civilization, that is, the polis. Physically the polis consisted of a town or city with an area of farm and pasture land surrounding it. Politically it was a community governed by magistrates and laws. All of the invading warriors had ancestral ties with central Asia nomads and still lived a similar life, eating sheep, goat and wild hog. Still another tribe, the Thessalians, entered Greece in the province which now carries their name, sometime before 1,000 B.C. (Ref. 15, 16, 17)

UPPER BALKANS

Thrace, in the area of present Bulgaria and a corner of present Greece along with European Turkey, began a lively period with identifiable rulers and Indo-European gods, at about 1,500 B.C. This country had two coasts - one on the Aegean and the other on a corner of the Black Sea - and thus was at the cross-road of West and East. The Thracians were formidable horsemen with a taste for battle, banditry and elegant gold objects. Their goldsmiths were producing masterpieces in the 13th and 12th centuries B.C. One of the largest gold finds of Europe's Bronze Age comes from Vulchitrun, Bulgaria and dates to this period, with many resemblances to the art of Mycenaea. They did not have a written language and knowledge of them has come chiefly through their Greek neighbors and recent Bulgarian excavations. This was the homeland of the Phrygeans, who began at this time to spread to Asia Minor. (Ref. 18)

ITALY

As noted in the last chapter, before 1,200 B.C. Italy was inhabited by a thinly scattered, backward population of dark whites of the Iberian or Mediterranean race. Then migrating Aryan Italics moved down, certainly by the end of this period, at 1,000 B.C., settled most of northern and eastern Italy, intermarried with the natives and established the Italian groups of Aryan languages. This included the Latin tribe south and east of the Tiber, and the Umbrians and the Sabines. These latter, living near Villanova, may have been the first Europeans to learn the use of iron. Extreme northern Italy, as well as the Mediterranean coasts of France and part of Spain, was originally peopled by a non-European speaking group called Ligurians. They were apparently pushed north by the Italics, where they came in contact with early Celts so that about 1,200 B.C. this Ligurian culture was absorbed into the Celto-ltalic (Apennine D) and the people gave up their own language to take on the Celtic-P tongue. Subsequently they were referred to by some European historians as Celto-Ligurians. They soon adopted the cremation rituals of the Urnfield Culture. The Italics at the toe of Italy pushed the Sicles toward Sicily, which was inhabited at the time by the Sican tribe, of unknown origin and language. In Etruria, of central Italy between the Tiber and the Arno, there was a Bronze Age Culture called Apennine and there was an abundance of copper and some tin for the making of bronze. Copper from the island of Elba was used throughout the 2nd millennium B.C. South Italy began to receive contacts from Mycenaean Greece as early as 1,300 B.C., particularly on the island of Pithecusae on the west, and Vivara and Lipara, and by the 13th century B.C. Mycenaean imports were already common. (Ref. 19, 20)

For hundreds of years the peaceful farmers of Corsica had buried their dead in great stone chambers with nearby single, standing menhirs which were roughly-shaped, unadorned, raised stones, and some seven feet high. After 1,500 B.C. there was a dramatic change and these menhirs became distinct sculptures with carved heads, tunics, daggers and swords. Whether they represented war trophies or memorials to a courageous enemy is still debatable. At about this same time, or at least between the 14th and the 12th centuries B.C., a tribe of the Sea People, the Shardana, came by way of Libya across the Mediterranean and overran the southern part of Corsica, pushing the remnants of the original Corsicans north, and by 1,000 B.C. the latter had disappeared. The conquering Shardana burned their dead and did not put up monuments. (Ref. 21)

CENTRAL EUROPE

In this time-frame an Indo-European speaking, tall, blonde people emerged as a confederation of tribes from a prehistoric complex and began to inhabit the bulk of Europe, spreading out from a "nest" around the rich ore fields of Bohemia and the central German mountains. Called Unetice, the distinguishing feature of this Bohemian-central German culture up until about 1,500 B.C. was the burial mound, but by 1,300 they had given this up in favor of cremation with the ashes of the dead placed in urns in cemeteries, and thus becoming known as the Urnfield Culture. This became the custom of later peoples, including the Italics, Venetians and Illyrians., and it may also have been the cradle of the three linguistic variations of "Old Indo-European" and possibly also that of the Phrygians and Armenians who settled in Anatolia about 1,200 B.C. All of these people were farmers, not much inclined to village life, raising animals, hunting, sacrificing to sun-gods, using the battle axe and both two and four wheeled chariots. People later to be identified as true Celts had probably not become differentiated at this time, although there is much confusion in the literature on this point, and many would call the early waves of Indo-Europeans of the Urnfield Culture by this name. (Ref. 22)

It is probable that after 1,220 B.C. the Scandinavian branches of the old Indo-European peoples which had migrated south after the catastrophes which seem to have occurred there in the 15th century (See SCANDINAVIA, this chapter), reached central Europe and spread with the local people in various directions - some to the Apennine peninsula to be- come the Ambrones, later Umbrians - some drove the Veneti to northern Italy and the forefathers of the Illyrians to Yugoslavia, and the Phrygians and Armenians to Anatolia – and finally some went to Greece. In the far north of the continent proper, the Thuringians Germanized north Germany and the Goths, Burgundians, Alemans and Marcomans prepared to move west as the Lausitz Slavs moved in behind them. (Ref. 23, 24)

WESTERN EUROPE

It was in the 12th century B.C. that Phoenicians from Sidon first settled on the coast of Spain, building a light house at La Coruna to be used as a guide for their ships going to England for tin. Soon after, other Phoenicians from Tyre established trading posts along the Guadalquiver River and finally founded Cadiz about 1,100 B.C. (Ref. 25) At this period Spain had a basic population of dark whites who may have been the ancestors of present day Basques, and there were Ligurians on the west coast. The latter had invaded from France and were actually a mixture of early or pre-Celts with Celtic speaking Ligurians who were numerous in France. McEvedy (Ref . 136) insists that about 1,200 B.C. a branch of these same people crossed over into England, conquering and intermarrying with the natives, who were already a mixed group of dark-haired and dark skinned people, possibly Iberian in origin, and light-haired Scandinavians. All of these people spread throughout England and Wales. The area of Wessex was particularly prosperous, with trading contacts with most of Europe and the Mediterranean. Working on the assumption that some of these early invaders of the British Isles were actually Celts, we can differentiate two stocks:

The Goidels (Gaels) still surviving in northern Ireland and nigh Scotland, representing a survival of the earliest Beaker-folk with a Q-Celtic tongue
the Cymri and Brythons (Britons) still represented in Wales as the P-Celtic, Urnfield people. The latter were close kin to the Gaulic Belgi

(Ref. 26, 27)

SCANDINAVIA

As the early Celtic people spread across northern Europe, they did not enter Scandinavia, and actually even made a type of barrier cutting off some trade between Scandinavia and the Mediterranean areas. In spite of this some iron, which was the secret weapon of the Celts, seeped into Scandinavia, so that they also had what might be called a "Celtic Iron Age", even though their basic economy still depended mainly on imported bronze to the extent that their unique metal work developed a special Northern Bronze Age. People buried their dead in log coffins in barrows and the clothing and hair were preserved intact. Rock scribings of wild animals and legendary scenes hewn into rock continued to be produced throughout large areas of Scandinavia, including Finland, and even parts of northern Russia. The richest finds of these scribings straddles the Swedish-Norwegian border. (Ref. 28, 29)

The climate in Scandinavia was for awhile warmer and drier than today and then it became cold again. Glaciers expanded, the sea level sank and vines stopped growing. In the more southern areas the Teutonic or Germanic tribes were in growth and some had already migrated to Britain and back and forth to the main continent. Danish amber was in demand on the continent and by 1,000 B.C. the Danes decked themselves with ornate weapons and ornaments and used bronze lurs as musical instruments. Navigation science must have been fairly well established, as there was much sailing of narrow, keel boats about England, Jutland and Brittany and perhaps even to Gibralter and the Canary Islands, where boat drawings similar to the Scandinavian ones have been found. (Ref. 30)

EASTERN EUROPE

The previously described Urnfield Culture, involving the burial of the ashes of the dead in urns, appeared in Poland about 1,300 B.C. and was also called the Lausitz Culture. These early people of Poland were the Lusatians, a western branch of Slavs. The eastern Slavs by the Pripet marshes of the middle Dnieper River did not use this burial method. North of both of these Slavic groups the Balts and/or Letts lived on the south shore of the Baltic. As indicated previously they may be neither purely Slavonic nor Teutonic nor Celtic. Their classical Baltic Bronze Age Culture, located between the Oder and Dvina, included local metal objects, pottery and burial rites in barrows surrounded by stone rings. To the northeast of the Balts all land area was sparsely inhabited by Finns and/or Lapps. The bulk of the southern branch of the Baltic Finns was the Estonians. Others of this group were the Livs (now about 1,000 remain on the tip of Courland) and the Votes. There are perhaps a few of the latter still around Narva, but they originally occupied all of Ingria. All of these Finns, like the Balts, came originally from the great arc of the Volga in the first half of the 2nd millennium B.C. and probably met with the Aesti, described by Tacitus. As they reached their Baltic homes, they intermarried with Balts and Lapps in an amount unknown. Southern Russia, from the Carpathians to the Caspian Sea was inhabited at that period by the Aryan Cimmerians, probably closely related to the Thracians. The Cimmerian name is preserved in the Crimean peninsula of the Black Sea. (Ref. 31, 32, 33)

1 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

2 [129] MARINATOS, SPYRIDON, "Thera, Key to the Riddle of Minos", National Geographic 141: No. 5, page 702, May, 1972.

3 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

4 [109] JUDGE, JOSEPH, "Minoans and Mycenaens: Greece's Brilliant Bronze Age", National Geographic 153: 142, Feb. 1978.

5 [188] SAVILLE, CURTIS & KATHLEEN, "They row, row, row their boat across the Atlantic Ocean", Smithsonian, Oct. 1981, pp. 192-215.

6 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

8 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

9 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

12 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

13 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

14 [41] COTTERELL, ARTHUR, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

15 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

16 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

17 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

18 171. PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

19 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

20 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

21 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

22 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

23 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

24 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

25 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

26 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

27 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

28 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

29 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

30 [117] LA FAY, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

31 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

32 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

33 [144] MICHAUD, ROLANDAND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

1.  Mc Evedy (Ref. 6) says that some refugee Achaeans may have been with the Cretans as they "transformed" into Philistines, as there are close parallels between Philistine and Mycenaean pottery.

2.  Herm (Ref. 9), page 87

3.  Grant (Ref. 11) writes that the Mycenaean civilization started at 1,700 B.C.

Europe: 1000 to 700 B.C.

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The great island empires of previous centuries no longer existed, and all of these areas were integral parts of either Greece or Asian states. For example, the southern half of Cyprus was now under Phoenician influence, while the northern half, along with

Rhodes and Crete were under Greek control. At various periods around 800 B.C. Assyrians, Egyptians and Persians conquered Cyprus, but let native kings rule. Dorian Greeks continued to control Crete, however. (Ref. 1)

GREECE

As the classical Greeks multiplied and migrated down the peninsula they did not develop a civilization of their own but, as barbarians, they wrecked one (Cretan and Mycenaean) and then built a new one out of the old. The Mycenaean cities and culture were so destroyed that even the art of writing was lost until about 800 B.C. when the Greeks adapted the Phoenician alphabet to their language. (Ref. 2) "Alpha", "beta", "gamma" are not Greek words, but come from Semitic terms for ox, house and camel.

The development of iron working techniques also contributed to cultural change and a well proportioned "geometric" pottery appeared about 900 B.C. This later turned up in Etruria in Italy, perhaps as copies. Early Greece was not fertile enough to support a fast- growing population and the need for more land, coupled with political oppression by the ruling classes led to two hundred years of extensive colonial expansion involving all the shores of the Mediterranean as well as the Aegean islands, Sicily, and Thrace. The colonies soon became independent of the mother cities, which continued to fight among themselves. Thucydides dates the earliest sea battle of history to about 712 B.C. between Corinthians and Corcyraeans. Corinth was formed from the union of a group of villages early in the 8th century B.C. and soon was wealthy because it was on the key land route between all the Hellenes (so-named from the mythical King Hellen, progenitor of all Greek peoples).

The Greeks added vowels to the Phoenician alphabet, and soon their language and their love of beauty fused into the Greek genius which transformed the world of that time.

NOTE: Insert Map Reference 97: Greek and Pheonician Colonies

The first Olympiad was held in 776 B.C. (Ref. 3, 4, 5, 6)

The fertile, wooded island of Euboea, just off the Greek coast became a great maritime power about the 9th century B.C. establishing a trading post at Al Mina on the coast of Syria which subsequently became a great source of gold and silver. Similarly, in the 8th century B.C. they established a trading post on the island of Pithecusae off the west coast of Italy for development of trade with the Etruscan city-states. (R-75)

UPPER BALKANS

The upper Balkan area seethed with Dacians, Thracians and Greeks and at this time a horde of ferocious, bearded, barbarian giants, the Scythians, appeared around the Black Sea, displacing the Cimmerians from around the north shore and the Crimea.

At the same time, the Greeks were bringing civilization back into the area of Thrace with various colonies along the Aegean coast. Iron working was well established along the Thracian and Illyrian areas. Colin Renfrew (Ref. 7) believes that the Thracian gold- smiths, working in Bulgaria, were the descendants of the Copper Age mound-makers described in earlier chapters.

ITALY

The Terramare peoples had already spread through eastern Italy and part of Sicily by the era under discussion and probably became the Samnite, Sabine and Latin tribes, as mentioned in the last chapter. In Etruria, between the Arno and the Tiber, in the 1 0th and 9th centuries, B.C. there were groups of Iron Age villages and by the next century special bronzes began to be imported from Sardinia. Between 750 and 700 B.C. various hill top villages in this Etruscan area began to be consolidated into city-states, with true urbanization. The first was Tarquinii, some miles north of the Tiber mouth on the west coast; then Caere to the south, reaching the Tiber; then Vulci to the north of Tarquinii; and finally Clusium and Veii, as inland city-states. All were fundamentally Etruscan people, speaking a non-lndo-European language which was known later to educated Romans, but which remains essentially untranslated today. The first three city-states mentioned above became independently strong sea powers, with large trade potentials based on enormous copper, iron and tin mines in the mountains of their respective regions. They traded these much wanted metals for gold, first through the Phoenicians from Sidon and Tyre, then after 800 B.C. with Carthaginians who established commercial outposts in Italy, Sardinia and Sicily,(as well as in France and Spain). In the 8th century it was the Greeks from the island of Euboea who established their large trading centers on the island of Pithecusae and on the mainland nearby at Cumae, to get the metals from the various Etruscan city-states and the Etruscan held island of Elba. The Euboean connections with Syria and Asia Minor also allowed the distribution of Oriental objects in Etruria. Another product from the region of Campigliese was alum, used particularly as a binder in the dyeing of fabrics and shoe-leather, both of which were Etruscan specialties.

About 1,000 B.C. Villanovan migrants from the Danube, using iron, crossed the Tiber and settled in Latium, exterminating or marrying the existing population. There was undoubtedly a great deal of shifting of populations and many of the Villanovans may have become assimilated into the Etruscan city-states and certainly many Greeks became permanent residents there, bringing much of their culture with them. The Etruscans of Tarquinii spread southward across the Tiber to Capua as early as 800 B.C. probably to facilitate trade with Cumae. It is a mistake to consider the Etruscans as a single, homogenous group, as they lived in their separate city-states, sometimes trading with each other, sometimes fighting and usually failing in every attempt at any coordinated efforts. Grant (Ref. 8) says that they were much like the modern Japanese in that they were great imitators and they copied all Greek works of art, adding some of their own improvements and unique variations.

There were settlements of some type at Rome probably through the 10th and 9th centuries B.C., but the traditional date for the official settlement of Rome is always given as 753 B.C. Just across the Tiber the Etruscan city-state of Veii was formed by a coalition of villages between 750 and 700 B.C.. Ancient writers said that it had a population of 100,000 but this was undoubtedly an exaggeration, although it probably was as large as Athens. Veii had no metals, but became rich from agriculture and the salt beds at the mouth of the Tiber. Rock-cut arched drainage channels and tunnels, sometimes two miles long, were made to facilitate drainage and their roads were excellent.

Based on Herodotus' reports from Lydian sources, the traditional concept was that the Etruscans came from Lydia in Asia Minor, but almost all modern authorities feel that this is completely in error. (Ref . 75). McEvedy (Ref. 9) believes the Etruscans were natives of the old Iberian group and that their higher culture developed from early contact with Greeks who were interested in the Elban and Etrurian iron and copper deposits. This view is strengthened by the Cambridge University Encyclopedia of Archeology (Ref. 10) which says that the 10,000 known Etruscan inscriptions belong to an old Mediterranean substratum still largely undeciphered. Michael Grant (Ref . 75) gave further documentation of this view in 1980. It is of interest that non-Indo-European languages were also spoken by the Ligurians and Raetians of northern Italy, the Corsicans, Sardinians and the Sicans of western Sicily. Tharros was a Phoenician port on the west side of Sardinia which received gold from Spain and then traded it extensively with the Etruscan cities for their own metal and agricultural products. It was the wealthiest of all the Sardinian cities, with multiple workshops for production of gold, silver, precious gem jewelry and ornaments. (Ref. 11) Bronze objects from these Sardinian workshops were arriving at Etruscan harbors throughout the 9th and 8th centuries B.C. In other parts of Italy, proper, there were the Iron Age groups of Picentes, Veneti and Iapyges. Some Etruscan city-states, particularly Volaterrae and Clusium, also extended their trade and influence north into the Transalpine regions. By 750 B.C., under this impulse, Felsina1 had become an economic power, as an amalgamation of villages with easy access to Etruria.

CENTRAL EUROPE

About 1,000 B.C. various branches of the Urnfield Culture, a group of related tribes with common culture and burial practices, dominated the Rhine/Danube axis, and began to expand into valleys of the main river thoroughfares. Four main branches gave rise to important groups of historic peoples: Celts in the west along the upper Main, Moselle and the Rhone, Slavs in the north from the Elbe to east of the Oder, Italic-speakers in the region of Hungary and Illyrians in the southeast about the river Tisza and Muresul. (Ref. 12) Some would say that the Celts did not really emerge as a distinct people of common language, religion and culture until about the 8th century B.C., and as manifested in the Hallstadt Culture (800-500 B.C.)2, located near the richest salt deposits in Europe and definitely influenced by the Etruscans from the south. In 1846 some 1,100 graves were opened in the Nieder as well as the Hallstadt regions of Austria, showing the extensive iron utilization and decoration of this Celtic Age. The Celts were energetic and inventive, using iron for tools and weapons. "They introduced soap to the Greeks and Romans, invented chain armor, were first to shoe horses and give shape to hand saws, chisels, files and other tools we use today. They developed seamless iron rims for their wheels, set our standard 4 feet 8 1/2 inch railroad gauge with the span of their chariots, pioneered the iron plowshare, the rotary flour mill, a wheeled harvester two millennia before Cyrus McCormick3.

Farther north there was ever increasing pressure from the Germanic tribes with some Teutons already moving up the Elbe and Rhine. The oldest Germanic wind instruments date back to 800 B.C. In a triangular area in northern Europe bounded by the rivers Aller and Saal in the west, a line running east from the river Somme to the Taunus mountains to the head of the Saal, and by the North Sea coast on the northwest, there were no Celts, and before the Germanic tribes began their migrations from the east and north, the people in this area spoke an older language than either Celtic or German. Some place-names in this region still bear the stamp of this unknown tongue, another example of ancient Europeans who did not speak an Indo-European tongue. (Ref. 15, 16)

WESTERN EUROPE

In the early part of this period, the people of western Europe were in a middle Bronze Age, speaking languages at present unknown. In Spain the Phoenicians had reached the lower reaches of the Guadalquivir River in Andalusia and they traded for metals mined by the natives, who seem to have been mainly Basques. The largest Phoenician city was Tarshish (Greek - Tartessos) and the script they used is called Tartessian, an only slightly modified Phoenician. The ships of Tarshish were the largest sea-going vessels known to the ancient world.

The first Indo-European speaking tribes who emigrated into France between 900 and 700 B.C. ran into the Ligurians who were short, muscular farmers, dangerous in battle. They had already had contact with Greek traders and Greek civilization. (Ref. 17) By the end of the 8th century B.C. Indo-European peoples were pouring into all areas of western Europe and even before that there was extensive trading occurring from the continent to Britain, as evidenced by the imported tools, weapons and trinkets. It will be recalled that the possibility of still earlier migrations of Celtic-speaking people to the British Isles was mentioned in the last chapter. It is possible that the Picts of Scotland were descended from the prehistoric Abernethy Culture, people who may have migrated from Germany to Scotland about 1,000 B.C. Our very limited knowledge of their language suggests a mixture of Celtic and some older speech. They were excellent metalsmiths and had a symbolic art which survives on some stones. (Ref. 18, 19, 20).

SCANDINAVIA

Denmark continued in an extended Bronze Age with a non-egalitarian society based on a mixed farming and herding economy. But the Danes were also highly skilled metallurgists and carpenters and had contacts with central Europe. The political leader was also the religious leader and there was an elite class who controlled trade and religion. While in the early Bronze Age, preceding the period under discussion, the dead were buried in wooden coffins, in later times (1,100-500 B.C.) cremation was common and the ashes were of ten placed in a pottery urn. Archaeologists have uncovered about 350 hoards of bronze and occasional gold objects which may have represented religious offerings of some kind. The objects included tools, swords, neckrings, armbands, brooches, belt ornaments, buckets, cups, bridle bits and shields, all of excellent workmanship, perhaps constructed by very specialized craftsmen. Eighty-one of the hoards, dated from the 9th to the 8th centuries, B.C., all contain women's ornaments in what appear to be special sets. The presence of animal bones and harvesting sickles in some hoards suggest that part of the purpose of the hoards was to insure fertility of the crops and herds. (Ref. 21) The Danes also developed their own Iron Age, using bog-iron. The people of Jutland of this period were the Vandals about whom we shall hear much more in later chapters.

Southern Sweden also continued its Bronze Age culture at this time and there was a general spread of Teutonic tribes throughout the area.

EASTERN EUROPE

Along the Baltic coast were German tribes and Balts. From the Elbe east to beyond the Oder were the proto-Slav, Urnfield Culture Lusatians, destined to become the Western group which had migrated from the east Carpathians to the Dnieper area became the Eastern Slavs. Some 140 miles northwest of Warsaw the Lusatian town of Biskupin has been excavated, showing an extra-ordinary stone enclosed area of five acres with one hundred identical houses arranged in thirteen rows, all made of oak and pine. a 130 yard-long wooden causeway linked the city, which was originally on an island in a lake, to the mainland. It is obvious that in addition to being skilled in the use of wood these people had a high social development, and some feel that their knowledge was carried over later to the Druids of the Celtic people.

By 800 B.C. the Eastern Slavs were completely conquered by the ferocious Scythians who took over the area about the Black Sea. The Slavs of this region were the ancestors of the Russian, Ukranian and White Russian peoples, and they had an innate aptitude for work in metal. The Scythians were primarily of Indo-European stock but may have had some added Mongol elements. In addition to dominating the local Slavs, the Scythians displaced the Cimmerians who had previously occupied the north shore of the Black Sea about the Scythians because much that has been described about them has come from Herodotus' The Persian Wars (Ref. 22) and one must always take this tales "with a grain of salt". In Book IV he described a visit to Scythia and wrote of their legends and customs. These included various barbarous activities including their propensity for beheading an enemy, then skinning him and making coats, caps and cushions from the skin. The skulls may have been used for drinking cups, after gilding of the interiors. The blood of the first victim was always drunk and scalps were taken to be later used as napkins. Herodutus told of hard, cruel men with leathery skin, filthy hair, wild cavernous eyes and many wives, all loving strong wine and smoking hashish while living chiefly in the saddle. (Ref. 23, 24, 25) They must not have been completely savage, however, as archeologists have shown that they produced highly developed arts and crafts with gold necklaces, miniature, cast animal figures and delicate glass ware. (Ref. 26) ***(*Page 1185)1

1 (Ref. 27)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [216] THUCYDIDES, The Peloponnesian War. (Translated by John H. Finley, Jr.). (Random House, Inc., New York 1951).

5 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

6 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

7 [179] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Bulgaria's Golden Treasures", National Geographic 158: 112, July, 1980.

8 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

9 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

14 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

17 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

18 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

19 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

20 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

21 [257] LEVY, JANET E., The Bronze Age Hoards of Denmark", Archeology 35: No. 1, pp. 37-45, Jan/Feb. 1982.

22 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

23 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

24 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

25 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

26 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

27 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

1.  "Felsina" was an Etruscan name, later called "Bononia" by Romans, after the conquering Boii Gaulic tribe.It is now "Bologna".

2.  Herm (Ref. 13) dates the Hallstadt Culture from 700 to 450 B.C.

3.  From Merle Severy (Ref. 14), page 588.

Europe: 700 to 601 B.C.

EUROPE

Beginning about 700 B.C. and lasting for the next 1,000 years most of Europe seems to have been somewhat colder and moister than it is now. (Ref. 1)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Crete remained under Dorian Greek control, while the Aegean islands overall belonged to a mixture of Ionian and Dorian tribes. Rhodes remained independent and even had a colony on Gela, in Sicily. (Ref. 2)

GREECE

The Greek civilization continued to develop in Greece proper as well as on the coasts of southern Italy and Asia Minor. There was a series of city-states, most of which were aristocratic republics by the end of this century. Cavalry played a decisive role in inter-state warfare and only the wealthy could be cavalrymen, with the result that noble landowners developed an increased influence. Sparta was supreme in the Peloponnese, while Athens was the major power in Attica. The hillsides of Attica had already been denuded of lumber for houses, ships and charcoal for metal working by 650 B.C. and the consequent erosion of the marginal land removed the soil to the point where little would grow and the peasants began to go into debt. All of Greece had poor land for livestock and thus with scarcity of animal fats, the Greeks cultivated olives for their oil, and depended on food imports for the remainder of their food necessities. The urgent need for grain stimulated much of their later enterprises.

Metal coins were introduced stamped with the likeness of an ear of wheat. Although gold, ivory and marble were used on sculpture and public buildings, the common people lived in houses of sun-dried brick, built on rubble in narrow streets strewn each day with litter thrown from the houses. Wives were held to housekeeping and childbearing while husbands, if they could afford it, openly took concubines and associated with the hetairae, women of education, wit and beauty, groomed for this profession, not unlike the Geisha of more modern Japan. There were about ten slaves for every free citizen and it was felt that about one hundred slaves were necessary to keep one philosopher in comfort. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

UPPER BALKANS

The Greeks had cities on the Black Sea coast of present day Bulgaria and Romania while Thrace began its period of highest culture. The Macedonians were Greeks, speaking a dialect remotely connected to those in Greece, proper, but developed separately. A series of local chieftains ruled until the middle of this century when the country was partially united by King Perdiccas I. (Ref. 6 )

ITALY

On the Italian peninsula there were multiple tribes, including the Latins and the Sabines, but dominating most of the north and central parts were the Etruscan city- states. Rome, itself, was ruled after 616 B.C. by Tarquinius Priscus, son of a Corinthian Greek man and an Etruscan woman. The Etruscans absorbed writing and other elements of the Hellenic civilization, assimilated and changed them and passed them on to other Italic peoples. The Latin alphabet was derived from the Etruscans, but the latter were never able to inflict their language on the Romans and in essence Rome remained a city of a dual culture. The Etruscans, themselves, had attained a certain degree of unity of culture and language. They attempted to form an Etruscan League, but the ties with adjacent tribes were more religious and cultural than truly political and concerted action was difficult to obtain. The Etruscans were superior engineers, and the Roman Theophrastus, writing later in the third century B.C. stated that they cultivated medicine and were rich in their pharmacopoeia. There is some evidence that they excavated tunnels and leveled hills to drain swamps as malaria control projects. They definitely practiced some surgery and dentistry, using gold wires in the latter field. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12)

The Etruscans seemed to particularly like the painted pots and vases brought from Corinth in Greece and were soon imitating them on a massive scale. Near the end of this century, due to the acquisition of more metal resources, perhaps at the expense of Tarquinii, the city-state of Caere became enormously wealthy, covered about 375 acres and had a population of about 25,000. Saleable copper and iron allowed them to acquire massive quantities of gold from the Greek markets of Pithecusae and Cumae. There is a strong possibility that the Etruscan alphabet, an adaptation of Greek letters in use in the Greek markets, was introduced to Etruria by way of Caere.

At about this same time the city-state of Vetulonia apparently became another prominent Etruscan community, lying just northwest of Vulci and characterized archeologically by great mound tombs, some of which reached a height of nearly fifty feet. Large stone sculptures have been found in these tombs, consisting of both male and female figurines and apparently adaptations from Syrian originals. Bronze horse-buckles indicate much horse traffic. Jewel works with a special granulation process of applying tiny grains of gold were typical. Village amalgamation into a single city perhaps occurred just at the end of the century. (Ref. 13)

There were Greek cities in Sicily and on the southern tip of Italy. In particular, there was Sybaris, a city of renowned wealth, situated in the toe of the Italian boot. Its inhabitants delighted in luxury and pleasures, features which gave rise to the term "sybarite", still in our vocabulary. It has only recently been located, now buried twenty feet deep in water soaked soil. The Carthaginians had a trading post at Motya in western Sicily, just after 700 B.C.

CENTRAL EUROPE

This was an age of Celtic domination, but with gradually increasing pressure from Germanic groups descending from the north. It was the late Iron Age in Austria and people wore bracelets, anklets and decorations over their chests. Intricate designs in iron with piece interlocking with closed eyes, perfect animal figurines, etc. can be found in the collections from multiple excavations of this era. Celtic ornamentation was greatly influenced by Scythian modes and the latter also contributed a new concept of cavalry, including snaffles, two-part bits and movable side reins. (Ref. 14)

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

The Iberians in most of this area were overrun by the Urnfield Celts except in the south, where the Tarshish Culture persisted and resisted the Celtic Hallstatt and later La Tene Iron Age Cultures. Contact with Phoenicians and realization of the local mineral wealth, resulted in the development of the only really native unit in this Kingdom of Tartessos. Greeks also came to this area about 630 B.C., introducing olives1 and grapes. Investigations in Portugal and Spain in 1975 and 1976 revealed stone writing in the Celtic Ogam, but using Libyan and Phoenician languages, indicating a fusion of Gaels and native Iberians with Semitic and Libyan sailors. Fell (Ref. 15) believes that it was from this area that mariners sailed on across the Atlantic to America at this time, and regardless of one's acceptance or non-acceptance of Fell's theories, there is definite archaeological evidence that the sailors of Tarshish sailed up the Atlantic at least as far as Brittany, to obtain Cornwall tin. Only limited excavation of the Tartessian urban developments have been made to date. (Ref. 16, 17)

FRANCE, NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM, AND BRITISH ISLES

This part of western Europe was now almost entirely Celtic. The Celtic languages had two large divisions which the Welsh Sir John Rhys (1877) called the Q-Celtic and P-Celtic, with the former using Q,K or Ch of ten where the latter used P or B. The ancient representatives of the Q-Celtic speakers were the Goidels (Gaels) and probably the Celts of Spain and Portugal, with the modern descendants being the speakers of Irish and Scots Gaelic and Manx. The ancient P-Celtic speakers were the Brythonic peoples of Britain, the Gauls of central and eastern Europe and the Picts of Scotland. Their descendants are the current Bretons of Brittainy, the Cornish and the Welsh. Of interest is the fact that while the P-Celts wrote using Greek or Latin letters, the Q-Celts originally wrote in a now defunct script called "Ogam", which had an alphabet of fifteen letters, all consonants and developed from a finger sign language. Later some tribes added more consonants and vowel signs. (Ref. 19, 20)

SCANDINAVIA

While Norway, Sweden and Finland remained in a Bronze Age culture, Denmark had both bronze and iron. This was a time of Germanic tribe growth, particularly in the latter country. Ty, in northern Jutland, was the alleged homeland of the Teuton tribe, while the Cimbrians are said to have originated in Himmerland. There is still no complete agreement on the relationship of the early Germanic and Celtic tribes. In ancient times they were often confused, and apparently there was not a great deal of difference physiologically. Language was supposedly the chief difference, but even with that problems arose with such tribes as the Teutones and Ambrones whose languages may have been mixtures with both Celtic and Germanic elements. (Ref. 21)

EASTERN EUROPE

Southern Russia was dominated at this 7th century B.C. by the Scythians who finally absorbed some culture from the rising Persian civilization on one flank and the Greek cities of the western and northern shores of the Black Sea, on the other flank. Some elaborate gold sculptures of that time have been found in Scythian burial mounds. Northern Russia and the Baltic area remained as described in the last chapter. (Ref. 22)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

5 [77] "GREEK MEDICINE", (Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Newsmagazine, Vol. 3, No. 9, Sept. 1959).

6 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

7 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

8 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [185] ROMAN MEDICINE, in Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, 3: No. 8, Aug. 1959.

12 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

13 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

14 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

15 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

16 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

17 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

18 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

20 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

21 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

22 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

1.  Trager (Ref. 18) credits the Phoenicians with bringing the olives to Spain

Europe: 600 to 501 B.C.

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

In this and the adjacent centuries there was extensive admixture not only of cultures and materials but of peoples, themselves, throughout all areas of southern Europe and even northern Africa and the eastern Mediterranean. There were migrations of peoples from Greece to the Aegean islands and Asia Minor and to Italy and southern France, while Phoenicians and Carthaginians moved to Italy, Sicily and Sardinia and the various tribes in both peninsulas intermingled, fought, traded, usurped territory and consolidated villages. Peoples of varying races and languages seemed to live side by side at times, only to fight at other times. Just as diverse languages seem to be no impediment to students, business men, teachers and travelers in Europe today, so it seems to have been true throughout the centuries. Thus eastern and Greek influences became prominent in Italy and the western Mediterranean.  (Ref.1)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

There was no great political change in this century from the last except that Persia took over Rhodes and its colonies. (Ref. 2)

GREECE

The node of Greek trading was at the Peloponnesian isthmus and Greece's first major city, Corinth, had developed there. About 600 B.C. a paved way allowed ships to be hauled across the isthmus. What Corinth owed to this key position geographically, Athens owed to the discovery of silver at nearby Laurion. It was with this that Athens subsequently financed its navy using a slave work-force running to five figures. (Ref. 3) The Ionians attained great naval strength, but Samos, under Polycrates, became a great seapower also, using long-boats with as many as fifty oars. Greece continued to be polyglot with even the Ionians having four different dialects. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

As the city-states increased in population subsistence became a problem in view of the poor soil, and various cities solved the potential crisis in various ways. While Corinth and Chalcis established overseas colonies, Sparta attacked and conquered nearby Greek neighbors and thus developed a military state. Athens, on the other hand, developed a specialized agricultural export trade and started manufacturing based on the export of wine and oil from their grapes and olives, in exchange for grain. Miletus and Eretria participated also in this trade. In Attica the tyrant1 Peisistratus started a policy of granting state loans to farmers who planted their land with grapes or olives. Solon forbade the export of any agricultural product except olive oil and this was the final touch as far as Greek soil was concerned, because the deep tap root of the olive tree soaked up the moisture far down in the limestone and did nothing to feed top soil. Even though Athens grew rich on the silver and olive oil, basic food supplies still had to be imported, necessitating continued trade. The unique artistic talents of the Athenians helped as they exported their famous "black-figure" vases with the black shapes standing out from an orange-red base2. Meat was a rarity except at times of religious sacrifice. There were no palms in Greece, but figs were used, particularly dried, in winter.

A change in warfare technique early in this century was an important factor in changing social relationships in Greece. The horsemen of the battlefield, heretofore chiefly aristocrats because of the cost involved, were now being replaced by heavily armed and armored clusters of infantrymen called "hoplites" which were massed together, shields overlapping, in a "phalanx". The farmers were able to take over this role and the tendency toward the development of an aristocratic primacy was checked. Even then some social struggles developed. Peisistratus (560-527 B.C.) backed the cause of the poorer class of hill men against the aristocracy in one such uprising. It is possible that the psychology of the phalanx helped to promote the democratic ideal of all being equal, but contrary to what one might believe from perusing the classical school textbooks, Greek democracy was far from being total. Great numbers of slaves, which we shall discuss more in detail later, lacked all political rights; women were also disfranchised; and resident aliens were admitted to citizenship only very rarely. Actually, throughout this 6th century Greece citizenry was pretty much a closed and hereditary group united by ties of kinship.

NOTE: Insert Maps taken from Reference 97 ANCIENT GREECE, CENTRAL GREECE

Aesop, of fable fame, lived in the first half of this century, born as a slave, physically malformed, rough, dogmatic but brilliant. He became the Greek ambassador to Lydia, but later, after challenging the integrity of the priests of Apollo, he was sentenced to die and was thrown from a cliff. Thales, after receiving part of his education in Egypt, founded the Ionian School of Natural Philosophy and set up the first system of abstract geometry and is said to have predicted the eclipse of the sun which occurred in 585 B.C. Coins of small denomination were introduced in Greece at this time. Toynbee (Ref. 10) says that 550 B.C. marks the end of the two hundred years of the acme of the Hellenic civilization, but in view of the developments in the latter part of this century and the next, many would disagree.

UPPER BALKANS

Early in the century the Scythians extended their power as far west as present day Hungary, but then they were decimated by a mysterious disease and they drew back to their homeland around the Black Sea. Herodotus mentions a disease of the Scythians which made them sterile, but it is not known if this was one and the same scourge which facilitated their defeat by Darius, when late in the century (513 B.C.) the Persians crossed the Hellespont, conquered the silver and gold rich land of Thrace, making a buffer zone against Greece. The remaining Scythians in the north fled, burning the land behind them. Thrace had been flourishing with an extensive trade and Greek styles and luxuries. Strangely enough, the Persian invasion only seems to have stimulated Thracian art. Macedonia continued its own more or less unmolested development. The Indo-European Illyrians had settled in present day Albania and their mines had attracted Greeks who settled near them on the Adriatic coast. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

ITALY

The region between Florence and Rome, now known as Tuscany, was populated by the prosperous Etruscans who capitalized on the rich copper and iron deposits of the area. They had twelve cities in Tuscany, additional settlements in the Po Valley and they controlled western Italy down to Cumae. In the north after 600 B.C. Bononia began to produce a great series of bronze buckets shaped like truncated cones and bearing figured reliefs. These have been found as far away as Austria and Slovenia and the Bononian ones may be copies of the latter. On the Adriatic Sea, in this century, several villages were brought together to form the port of Spina, not far from present day Venice. Spina was centered on a long, wide canal which connected the sea to a lagoon. The city covered over 700 acres, chiefly on peninsulae connected to the mainland only by narrow tongues of land. It was peopled by Etruscans and Greeks as well as the more native Venetii, and some of the latter apparently converted to the Etruscan language.

All of the western Etruscan city-states had their individual merchant navies which were active in the Tyrrhenian Sea, trading at the Greek and Cathaginian ports and their trader-pirates were active even in the Aegean, where they may have had a colony on the island of Lemnos. Many elements in their art and religion have been interpreted as Near East in origin, and as previously mentioned, traditionally it has been surmised that at least their rulers were immigrants from Asia Minor, Lydia in particular, but this has now been pretty well disproved. In 1964 there was excavated at Pergi, Italy, a letter written on sheets of gold leaf, in Etruscan, supposedly from Hiram, Lord of Tyre, to the king of Lavinia (near Rome) and Fell (Ref. 14) interprets the language as belonging to the Anatolian group and related to Hittite and Urartian. This does not, in itself, prove Near East ancestry for the Etruscan people. (Ref. 15, 16)

Originally the people of Rome were ruled by Etruscan kings, who, in turn, appointed or nominated the senate from the patrician families. Throughout most of this century Rome was actually an Etruscan city, even though the common language there was an Indo European one, destined to become Latin. The draining of the marsh for erection of the Roman Forum by construction of the impressive Cloaca Maxima was a typical Etruscan kind of operation. Etruscan metal-work, pottery and armour appeared in Rome, along with Etruscan immigrants. Terracotta friezes are identical in Rome and Veii and the great sculptor, Vulca of Veii, made the statue of Jupiter for a huge temple in Rome. The last of the Roman kings was an Etruscan and when he was overthrown the republic was established. After 510 B.C. the senators were appointed by two elected consuls. One of these, Valerius Poplicola, promoted the Lex Valeria, sometimes called the "Habeas Corpus" of Rome, allowing the plebians to appeal decisions of the magistrates to the general assembly, thus freeing them from the worst class vindictiveness. (Ref. 17, 18)

In the south, Pompeii was an important harbor for Nola and other Etruscan towns in Campania and fragments of their black pottery have been found there. Another Etruscan settlement was near Salerno. This Etruscan activity in Campania did not last long, however, as Etruscan Capua and Greek Cumae clashed violently about 525-524 B.C. when a force of Etruscans invaded the area in what has been called the "long march". Aristodemus, ruler of Cumae, repelled the invaders and later, with the help of adjacent Latin tribes, he further defeated the Etruscans near Aricia, between 506 and 504 B.C. (Ref. 19) In a Greek colony in southern Italy, Pythagoras established his brotherhood and incidentally developed his famous proof of C2= A2+ B2 in a triangle. The group placed such emphasis on the theory of numbers that ultimately it involved itself in a world of mystical, mathematical abstractions.

Sardinia and the western half of Sicily were conquered and occupied by Carthage in this century and of course there were multiple Greek colonies all along southern Italian coastal areas as well as on the southern and eastern coasts of Sicily. Somewhat replacing the Eubaean influence in the Mediterranean, another Greek city-state, Phocaea, now sent its fleet west to establish trading colonies at Massalia and Alalia (now Aleria) on eastern Corsica. These Greeks were interested mainly in trade for metals, and Etruria was the final resource. The capture of the Phocaean and other Ionian homelands by the Persians actually sent floods of Greek refugees to the west and thus Etruscan art of this period displays many Ionian characteristics. The southern parts of France, Italy, Greece and Turkey are today all very similar genetically in their populations, indicating the probable influence of this early Greek colonization.

From about 540 B.C. onwards, the Caeritans, guided by lonian artists who had flooded the area, developed an impressive new school of ceramics which, among other things, produced handsome water jars with rich polychrome paintings of Greek mythological scenes. The new wave of Phocaean settlers who arrived at Alalia in mid-century extensively plundered the surrounding territories with a consequent reaction by Carthaginian and Caeritan navies. As noted earlier in this chapter when discussing Carthage, these allies were actually defeated by the Phocaeans, but the latter also lost 40 ships and soon took their families from Alalia to Rhegum, in southwest Italy. The unfortunate Phocaean sailors of the 40 captured ships were slaughtered on the adjacent shore by the Caeritans. (Ref. 20, 21)

NOTE: Insert Map taken from reference 97, GREEK AND CARTHAGINIAN COLONIZATION OF SICILY AND SOUTHERN ITALY

Vetulonia, to the north, seems to have reached the climax of its political power during this century as a walled city with a two mile perimeter. It had commercial relations across the Arno and Apennines and received amber from the Baltic. One of the Vetulonia dominated cities was Populonia on a peninsula projecting into the sea not far from Elba. It participated with the island in iron and copper works and eventually became the real smelting center, as the supply of wood fuel on Elba dwindled.

Still north of Vetulonia and bordering on the sea was Volaterrae, noted for its fabrication of bronzes and sculptures of volcanic stone. The central city was surrounded by a wall four and one-half miles long, and its area of influence extended over to present day Florence, where mound tombs have been excavated. Volaterrae's inland neighbor was Clusium, an area originally occupied by Italic speaking Umbrians, but which eventually became Etruscanized while yet remaining biracial. King Lars Porsenna of Clusium was considered the most powerful Etruscan of all time, and his tomb has been described as a magnificent edifice, 300 feet square. The primary products of this inland community were agricultural, even though vast irrigation and drainage projects were necessary to limit flood waters. (Ref. 22)

CENTRAL EUROPE

In this century there was a continuing proliferation of the Hallstatt Celtic people throughout central Europe with a thin fringe of Teutons in the north. The Scythian nomads invaded, particularly in the great Hungarian plain, and greatly influenced Celtic art and society in general. From them may have come the war-horse with the bronze bits and harnesses and the head-hunting custom, all of which were later considered a part of the Celtic tradition. Bronze Age Indo-Europeans, Scythians and Greek concepts apparently all coalesced into the new Celtic pattern, with a center at Heuneburg, on the German Danube. (Ref. 23, 24)

WESTERN EUROPE

By 500 B.C. the influx of Celts into southwestern Spain (Andalusia) was so great that the local spoken language changed from Phoenician to Celtic, but even so the Tartessian culture persisted with Carthaginians taking over the old Phoenician settlements. The Phocaean colony of Massilia was founded on the Mediterranean coast of France in 600 B.C. and it allowed commercial relations between the Celts and the Mediterranean cultures. Vinyards may have been planted on French soil about this time, after the Greeks started importing their own wine into the Marseilles area. All the Atlantic coast and Britain continued under Celtic domination. (Ref. 25, 26, 27)

SCANDINAVIA

Although in this century iron was used exclusively for farming and war, the Scandinavian tribes continued to make bronze implements, bibelots and costume jewelry of great excellence and intricacy. The populations were increasing rapidly and people were already beginning to migrate to the European continent, proper. The Finnish people continued to live in widely spread villages throughout the northern regions from northern Scandinavia to and perhaps beyond the Ural Mountains. (Ref. 28)

EASTERN EUROPE

Finns and Lapps lived throughout the northern areas of Russia while Balts inhabited the southern coast of the Baltic Sea and on east to the Don River. South of the Balts were the early Slavs, and now through this area the Scandinavians pushed up the Vistula River as far as the Carpathians. In southern Russia the Scythians were decimated by a mysterious disease, although Darius' invasion may have had something to do with it also. In the spring of 514 B.C. Darius of Persia crossed the Bosporus with a vast army and moved through Thrace into Scythia, but his 700,000 men were very nearly consumed by the Scythians' military wizardry as they retreated using a "scorched earth" policy, so that Darius finally had to withdraw the remnants of his starving army. (Ref. 29)

1 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

4 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

5 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

6 [216] THUCYDIDES, The Peloponnesian War. (Translated by John H. Finley, Jr.). (Random House, Inc., New York 1951).

7 [58] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Tunisia: Sea, Sand, Success", National Geographic 157: 184, Feb. 1980.

8 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

9 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

10 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

11 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

12 [171] PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

13 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

14 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

15 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

16 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

17 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

18 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

19 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

20 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

21 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

22 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

23 [116] LAMB HAROLD, Genghis Khan. (Robert M. McBride & Co., New York 1927).

24 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

25 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

26 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

27 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

28 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

29 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

1.  "A tyrant was a man who gained power through coup d'etat and ruled extra-legally." (Ref. 8) page 202

2.  In 1970 a list showed that 1,560 of these vases had been found in Etruria, Italy, and many more have been found since then. (Ref. 9)

Europe: 500 to 401 B.C.

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

With the ultimate Greek victory over the Persians, many Mediterranean islands, including Rhodes and the Cyclades, now became dependents of Athens. Even the Etruscan held island of Lemnos fell to Athenian control in that period. At the end of the century, however, Rhodes pulled away, forming its own confederacy of three city-states. (Ref. 1)

GREECE (THE 2ND CENTER OF CIVILIZATION)

In the first half of the century the city-states of Greece were occupied with continuous warfare with Persia with the first Persian attack coming in 490 B.C. by sea. In 480 B.C. there was the great battle of Thermophylae and a concurrent sea battle at Salamis in which Xerxes was defeated. Between 478 and 477 Athens organized the Delian League as a defense against future imperialism, with members being the Aegean coast and island allies, with headquarters at Delos, but with Athens as the leader. These Athenian imperialistic policies were engineered by Cimon, aristocratic successor of Themistocles. The Perisan wars ended about 449 B.C. as the Persian Empire deteriorated and most of the Greek cities, even those on the coast of Asia Minor and the Black Sea, became free.

The key to Athens’ extraordinary accomplishments in the first half of this century lay in her fleet, which maintained control of the Aegean and allowed goods from the eastern Mediterranean to enter through the port of Piraeus. The fleet thus not only carried the war across the Aegean to help liberate the Greek cities there, but also allowed foreign contact, thus bringing new ideas and concepts, all of which set the stage for cultural creativity. In this context we must not forget that behind all the shipping and trade was the necessity for Greece to import food. The life-line demanded grain, even though this 5th century B.C. did see the use of the domestic hen in almost every Athenian household and Greece now became the home of fine wines. Alfalfa was introduced by the Persians and subsequently the Greeks used this as horse fodder. (Ref. 2, 3)

Some modern writers have a tendency to idealize Greek life of this century and underplay some of the less tasteful aspects of that civilization. In all Greek states abortion or abandonment of children was permitted. Sparta arranged to prevent parents from knowing which were their own children and vice versa, while the state decided whether or not any child would be permitted to live. Homosexuality was widespread and publicly accepted. Athens had between 75,000 and 150,000 slaves representing some 25 to 35% of the population. (Ref. 4, 5) Finley (Ref. 6) says that this number is purely a guess, and that while the exact number of slaves is unknown, the important fact is that this was a slave society. Urbanism and the great increase in wealth initiated capitalism and with the extension of full rights to the lower classes, free hired labor could not meet the needs of the capitalists who, taking advantage of the almost continuous wars, turned to ever larger scale slave labor.

As in Phoenicia, some Greek ports constructed in that time of low sea levels in the Mediterranean are today below sea level. Medicine of that period in Greece was a mixture of religious mysticism with some rational thought and procedures. Ascelepios was worshipped as the God of Healing and temples were erected for him for that purpose over many centuries and were in present day terminology mixtures of religious shrines and health spas. Alcaeon, possibly of this century, wrote a book Concerning Nature, which may be the beginning of Greek medical literature, although only a few fragments survive. He established a connection between the sensory organs and the brain, described the optic nerves and concluded that the brain was the organ of the mind, therefore also responsible for thought and memory. A century later Aristotle thought erroneously that the heart was the center of sensation. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10)

NOTE: Insert Map: GREECE DURING THE PERSIAN WARS

The period 475 - 429 B.C. has been called the "Golden Age of Pericles", the greatest ruler of Athens. In view of the thousands of pages that have been written concerning ancient Greece, it is sometimes difficult to keep things in proper perspective. Attica was actually a small area, with Sunium, the most distant point from Athens, being only forty miles away (although admittedly this was a long walk, with only feet for transportation). It was, however, a period of literature, plastic arts and the development of the foundations of science. This was the time of Socrates, for whom philosophy was neither theology nor metaphysics but ethics and politics with logic an introduction and a means. (Ref. 11) It was the time of the historian Herodotus (born about 484 B.C.) and in lonia the time of the great physician Hippocrates who fostered the scientific approach to the treatment of disease as opposed to the priests' explanation that disease was the result of anger of the gods. He was born on the island of Cos in 460 B.C. and became known eventually as the "Father of Medicine". Protagoras (480 - 410 B.C.) was the chief proponent of the Sophists, who taught the virtue of proper use of words and a method of verbal reasoning according to rules of argument whereby a man might hope to unravel all the mysteries of the universe. Their doctrines, including one that stated that the law was a conspiracy of the weak against the strong, provided the oligarchy with justification for violence and chicanery used to overthrow the democracy eventually (414 - 411 B.C.) Other philosophies included that of the Cynics who cared only for virtue and relation of the soul to God with the world and its learnings amounting to nothing; and the Stoics and Epicureans, using logic and rhetoric toward a similar goal. Parmenides and Zeno, of the famous paradoxes, were Eleatics. (Ref. 12, 13)

This great age of Greece ended with the Peloponnesian War - a war of Sparta and her allies against Athens and hers, which raged for thirty years beginning in 431 B.C. and which wasted all the power of Greece. Forty years of aggressive Athenian imperialism and land grabbing activities had forced most mainland cities to look to Sparta for leadership. Athens had control of the seas but commanded few mainland areas outside of Attica, and it was obvious from the beginning that neither side could win. Then in 430 and 429 B.C. a pestilence, which may have been a malignant form of scarlet fever1, killed off 25% of the Athenian land army. Thucydides said the infection had begun in Ethiopia, run into Egypt and Libya and most of Persia, then through Piraeus to Athens, itself. The latter never fully recovered and lost the war to Sparta. A peace which was supposed to last fifty years was declared in 421 B.C. but Athens resumed expansionist ambitions, this time with cruelty and slaughter in conquered islands. In reaction, the Persians financed a new Spartan navy commanded by Lysander and he completely defeated the Athenian fleet at a great battle at Aegospotami off the Hellespont in 405 B.C. The end came for Athens when Lysander then cut off the grain supply line and laid siege to the city itself in 404 B.C.. The final slaughter of the inhabitants matched the previous plague of 430 - 429. Plato, a pupil of Socrates, grew up in the atmosphere of this exhausting war. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

NOTE: Insert 21: GREECE DURING THE PELOPONNESIAN WAR

UPPER BALKANS

There was culture in Thrace and in the Greek colonies along the coast of the Black Sea. Many cities had developed in Macedonia and by 450 B.C., under the reign of Alexander I, a veneer of Hellenic civilization had appeared on the ruling classes of this area. (Ref. 18)

ITALY

Italy at this time was a motley of independent tribes and towns. There was still a northern Etruscan presence near the Po River, with various cities there. Virgil, the Roman poet of part Etruscan origin, describes his home of Mantua as composed of three races which apparently included Etruscans, Venetians and Umbrians, the latter two being Indo-European Italic speakers.

In Etruria, itself, in addition to Tarquinii and Caere, which we discussed at some length in the last chapters, we should now discuss Vulci, the city-state just north of Tarquinii.

In this 5th century B.C. it showed a marked Athenian influence, with the Athenian "black-figure" pottery flooding the community. No less than 40% of all Attic pottery that has been excavated in Etruria is from Vulci. But this city's real claim to fame was its bronze-work, with multiple cast bronze statues which were in turn exported afar, including back to Greece. It is possible that Servius Tullius who ruled as King of Rome after Tarquinius Priscus, was a Vulcentine with the original name of Mastarna. (Ref. 19) Early in the century the Etruscans, at the height of their power and allied with the Carthaginians, were at war with the Sicilian Greeks of Syracuse and their King Hiero 1. (Please see also 1, B, this chapter), and in a great naval battle off Cumae about 474 B.C. the Etruscan navy was destroyed. They were then forced to withdraw from Campania and this secured the liberation of Rome from Etruscan control. Even then, Cumae and Capua alike were still subjected to several years (430 - 423 B.C.) of fighting some hard-nosed mountain, Italic-speaking tribes, the Samnites. It was the descendants of the latter who eventually forged a new Campanian nation. In addition to the resistance of the Campanian Greeks the city-state of Caere was further damaged by an attack by sixty Syracusan warships which plundered harbors on the mainland and overran Elba and Corsica. (Ref. 20)

Up to this point Rome had actually only controlled an area of about nineteen by nineteen miles, but they soon defeated the Sabines and expanded into their area. In spite of the smallness of Rome, this was the period of the Roman Republic. At the beginning (494 B.C.) there was the first "secession" in which the plebes withdrew from Rome to form their own city, forcing concessions from the patricians such as the right to have officers of their own, tribunes and aediles. In the Republic there were four classes of citizens; the Patricians, consisting of the superior clans which supplied Rome with generals, consuls and laws for five centuries (the Mantii, Valerii, Aemili, Cornelii, Fabii, Horatii, Claudii and Julii); the Equites, or business men; the Plebs, or commons; and finally the Slaves. The Roman Senate consisted of 300 members made up of clan heads from three basic tribes, although occasionally an Equite got into that body. As a result of a political battle for better laws for the Plebs, a commission was sent to Greece to study the legislations of Solon and other lawmakers and on their return, ten men (decemviri) formed a new code call "the Twelve Tables" which were approved by the Assembly and became the first written form of a legal structure of Rome (450 B.C.), serving as the basic law for the next 900 years. In 443 B.C. appeared the institution of censorship and in 432 the first law designed to check electoral corruption was passed. At the end of the century the long war of Rome against the Etruscan city, Veii in Tuscany was started. At the same time the Gauls descended again from the north and the Etruscans were squeezed in the middle. (Ref. 21)

Pei (Ref. 22) states that at 500 B.C. the Latin language was a rough, elemental tongue, lacking most of the refinement of syntax and vocabulary to come later.

The Greek Syracusans were busy through most of this century fighting and defending their possessions. In the battle of Himera on the north Sicilian shore in 480 B.C. they defeated the Carthaginians and then were able to dominate the western Mediterranean. We have noted above how they subsequently defeated the Etruscan navy. In 414 B.C. the Athenians besieged Syracuse, but they too were defeated, their fleet destroyed and the survivors were taken as quarry slaves.

The Greek Empedocles, living in Sicily, developed a theory of the movement of blood to and from the heart, and performed various medical "miracles". He is said to have raised a woman from the dead. Later, Galen was to call him the Father of Italian medicine. (Ref. 23)

CENTRAL EUROPE

By 500 B.C. the greater part of the northern European coast was Germanic. The first, or Germanic, sound shift in the Aryan tongue created a dividing line between the Germanic and other Indo-European languages. Farther south the Germanic groups were still checked by Celts. From 500 or 450 B.C. onward is the age of the La Tene Celtic Culture, named after excavation sites in the region of Lake Neuchatel in Switzerland.

Corresponding to the Golden Age of Greece, there was a wave of Celtic expansion, with battles against the cities of the classical world. They used two-wheeled chariots as cavalry in tactical units of three and tribal foot soldiers armed with spears, slings and tall wooden shields decorated with metal bosses, but there were no bows and arrows. The Switzerland Celts extracted tolls as they controlled the head of the Seine navigation on the tin route from Britain to the bronze workshops of Italy. At that time the Rhineland had already become important in iron ingot production. A reverse flow of Etruscan bronzes went back up the river route and those art objects found in Germany, as well as in Belgium and Luxemburg, had definite influence on Celtic art. (Ref. 24, 25, 26, 27)

Recent excavations at Hochdorf (near Stuttgart) in southwestern Germany indicate that the Celts of south Germany had a stratified society with an aristocratic class that lived in hilltop fortresses. The wealth of that class was based on trade links with Greek colonies in Italy and southern France and with the Etruscans. The large tombs of the aristocrats were sometimes one hundred meters in diameter and held Mediterranean drinking vessels, furniture and other household luxuries. The average life span at that time was about thirty years. The Hallstatt culture existed in two great regions, one in the west with clear Celtic features and an eastern one in Carinthia, the north Adriatic and Yugoslavia, which included the Illyrians and the Veneti.

WESTERN EUROPE

On the east coast of Spain and at Massilia on the Mediterranean coast of France there were Greek colonies, but otherwise all France and the Atlantic coast was Gaulic (Celtic). These people also overran the basic population of Ireland, bringing iron to that land as well as to Britain, where its use rapidly outstripped bronze after 450 B.C. The Celts who arrived in Britain in this era were Brythonians, or P-Celtic speakers, from the early La Tene Culture on the continent. (Ref. 28, 29)

On the North Sea between the Somme and Aller rivers, including present day Holland, northeastern France, northwestern Germany and most of Denmark is an area where place- names still show remnants of a language neither Celtic nor German. The Celts never got this far north and the Germans for a long time were west of the Aller. A prehistoric people were apparently squeezed between the Celts and the Germans in that location. (Ref. 30)

SCANDINAVIA

In this century there was a true Iron Age in Scandinavia and a period of continued proliferation of Germanic tribes, some of which were spilling over into Europe proper.

EASTERN EUROPE

The Finns and the Balts occupied the same respective territories as in the preceding century. In the Slav zone of Poland a new fashion of decorating urns with faces replaced the old Lausitz style. This change appears to have spread southeastward from the Baltic. Areas of quite advanced civilization existed in the Greek colonies on the Black Sea and at the Persian borders near the Caspian.

On the Russian steppe the Iranian tribes between the Don and the Aral Sea became known as the Sarmatians while those farther west were Scythians, now becoming farmers. Southern Russia was both cooler and more moist than earlier or than now and instead of the previously existing steppe country, by 500 B.C. wooded or partly wooded country extended from Romania east for one thousand miles to the Don River. This tended to restrict nomadic foraging and raiding. It was in this century that Herodotus, the Greek historian, visited Albia on the north shore of the Black Sea and wrote of the Scythians. (Ref. 31) He mentioned that some of the Scythians grew grain, not for their own use, but for sale chiefly to the Greeks. East of these farmers were the largest and bravest of the Scythian tribes, reaching as far east as the Don. They used large cow stomachs to hold thirty to forty gallons of water. It is said that the natives of the Caucasus Mountains were still practicing cannibalism at this time. (Ref. 32)(Ref. 33) (Ref. 34)(Ref. 35)(Ref. 36)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

7 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [281] GORE, RICK, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

9 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

10 [125]  LYONS, ALBERTS., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

11 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

12 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

13 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

14 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

15 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

16 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

17 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

18 [218] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

19 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

20 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

21 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

22 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

23 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

24 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

25 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

26 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

27 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

28 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

29 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

30 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

31 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

32 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

33 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

34 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

35 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

36 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

1.  An unsupported statement of Trager. (Ref. 17, page 17)

NOTE: Insert 21: GREECE DURING THE PELOPONNESIAN WAR

Europe: 400 to 301 B.C.

Europe

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

In the last third of this century, all these islands were conquered by the men of Alexander the Great, but his control was short-lived. By 323 B.C. Rhodes was independent again and Cyprus belonged to Egypt until Demetrius Poliocertes, aspirant to the throne of Macedon, took Cyprus again. Then in 307 he besieged Rhodes, using 30,000 men to build siege towers and engines, but all of this failed. (Ref. 1, 2)

GREECE

Throughout the peninsula there was endless conflict between the slaves and the ruined proletarian masses who demanded that the state support them. Up until about 378 B.C. the police force of Athens consisted of about 300 state-owned Scythian slaves. At the beginning of the century Sparta, having won the Peloponnesian War with the help of subsidies from Persia, dominated southern Greece; then, by forming an "Arcadian League", Thebes took over control from about 370 to 360 B.C.; then Athens, with growing special- ization of professional soldiers and generals, professional orators and financial experts be- came supreme for awhile. But in the last part of the century the unity which the Greeks could not find among themselves was forced on them by Philip of Macedon. The battle of Chaeronea (338 B.C.) was the end of Greek liberty and the beginning, in some sense, of Greek unity. (Ref. 3, 4)

In spite of the wars this was one of the great eras of culture. Plato lived until well into this century and the political problems always remained a central issue for him and he became a frustrated politician. The mainly hereditary tripartite class division of the "Republic" corresponded closely to the divisions of 6th century B.C. Greek society, with an aristocracy that guided the state, citizens who fought for the polis and slaves and foreigners who labored. Plato brought together diverse intellectual strands from different parts of the Greek world and he did so with a consummate artistry that few have even equaled, giving to subsequent Greek and European philosophy its central themes and problems, as well as much of its working vocabulary. It is not generally realized that Plato also wrote medical speculations, logical but without any direct experimentation and leading to many faulty conclusions about the human body, errors that persisted well into later centuries and were difficult to eradicate. (Ref. 5, 6)

Near the end of the century Aristotle, a pupil of Plato, returned from his travels with Alexander to found the Peripatetic School or Lyceum. Scientific material of all kinds had come to him through the Greek-Macedonian armies' conquests (Please see next section UPPER BALKANS) and his work became the basis of knowledge even 1,500 years later in the Middle Ages of Europe. Aristotle pioneered in biology, embryology and physiology and was a champion of inductive reasoning. Three great structural ideas appeared in this era which rule the mind of contemporary mankind today: ( l) Science, in the broad sense, including history and relation of man to the total environment; (2) the idea of one universal God of righteousness; and (3) the concept of world policy.

Theophrastus followed Aristotle as head of the Lyceum and established the basic concepts of botanical science, collecting data from as far as India. Democritus, early in the century, had described the universe as being composed of atoms (indivisible particles incapable of destruction) and a vacuum. This theory was rejected by Aristotle but was to be emphasized again in the 1st century B.C. by Lucretium.

Hippocrates also lived well into this century. He described a mumps epidemic and some three and four day fevers which may have been tertian and quartan malaria. Other diseases described suggest diphtheria and either tuberculosis or influenza. Nothing was mentioned that suggested small-pox, measles or plague at that time. Whether all the teachings that we have come to accept as Hippocratic writings are actually the work of one man, or many, is not known. There were simultaneously great medical centers on Cos and on the Asia Minor mainland at Cnidos and the final collections of "Hippocratic" writings at the great library at Alexandria in the last part of this century may have actually been contributions from many Greek physicians. Injuries to bone and joints made up a large part of medical practice and manipulations to reduce fractures and dislocations were sophisticated and sometimes associated with very complex bandaging and mechanical devices. The cautery was used and there was extensive use of minor surgical procedures for tumors, fistulas, ulcers and hemorrhoids. The juice of the opium poppy and of the mandragora1 was available for anesthesia and pain relief . Books numbering seventy-two and treatises at about fifty-nine have been credited to Hippocrates. Case histories of some diseases are superb, but the anatomy, physiology and therapy, of course, was of ten poor and the specific diagnosis of any disease was seldom given. The ethics, conduct and appearance of the physician was emphasized. (Ref. 7,8, 9)

Of incidental interest is the fact that it was not until this century that the new raised wheat bread from Egypt became popular in Greece. (Ref. 10) The last third of the century saw the affairs of Greece subjected to the domination of their Macedonian neighbors - originally enemies and then allies. This situation will be discussed at greater length in the next section.

UPPER BALKANS

The Macedonians, occupying most of the area we know as Yugoslavia and Bulgaria, were kin to the Greeks and their language was almost Greek, but they were more purely Nordic than any people to the south and their appearances and customs were similar to the wild Celts of the period. Philip II, who became Macedonian king in 359 B.C. by simply seizing the throne after he had been appointed regent for his nephew, was a leader-king of the ancient Nordic-Aryan type. Having previously been held hostage for a short time in Thebes, he had gained much knowledge of the Greeks and he immediately developed an army trained in the effective Theban phalanx formation and proceeded to enlarge his kingdom to the north by subduing the Thracians with their gold mines of Mount Pangaion and then east and south to the upper part of the Aegean Sea. In spite of drunkenness and other personal vices, he was probably the best educated man of his time and with his son's tutor, Aristotle; it was he who planned most of the greatness that his son Alexander achieved. After he gained an Aegean coastline and the Thracian gold he soon conquered the coastline of Thessaly. Although there was much bickering and changes of alliances in Greece the main obstacle to Philip's control of the entire peninsula was always Athens, where Demosthenes constantly used his oratorical abilities to denounce him. His troops finally defeated an Athenian coalition, however, in 338 B.C. at Chaeronea in Boeotia. Subsequently, at a congress of Greek states Philip was elected, or at least recognized, as Captain-General of all the Greeks for an all-out war against the old enemy, Persia. Thus Macedonia rose to political importance by assimilating aspects of Hellenism. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

Actually the great battle with Persia was not enjoined until after Philip's assassination and Alexander's coronation as king. Within a few years Alexander had conquered all western Asia and a part of India and Egypt, carving out an empire 3,000 miles wide and in most regions up to 1,000 miles from north to south, thus approaching the size of the United States. As accompanying maps will show, the boundaries were almost identical with the previously existing Persian Empire. All of this was conquered within about twelve years without motorized vehicles and only about 35,000 men including some 5,000 mercenaries. He initiated the use of a torsion catapult to shoot arrows and stones, beginning a whole new era in siege warfare. (Ref. 14, 15) At least thousands and perhaps hundreds of thousands of Greeks followed in Alexander's footsteps, emigrating to the East and giving a deep Hellenic imprint over and above the purely military conquest. Alexander died in 323 B.C. at the age of thirty-three years, a man of tremendous vanity, at times kind and considerate and at other times vicious, cruel and destructive. He died in Mesopotamia, possibly of malaria. (Ref. 16)

Alexander set up no competent administrations in the various conquered areas and after his death the empire rapidly collapsed, with division of the territory among the various Greek generals. Initially the divisions were as follows:

General Seleucus controlled the Asian part of the old Persian Empire and the south half of Asia Minor except the coast, clear across southwest Asia to the Indus
General Antigonus kept Macedonia itself, but by 301 B.C. he was killed in battle and his son Demetrius I was defeated as Lysimachus took the area of Thrace and Cassander took Macedonia and Greece
General Ptolemy took Egypt, along with most of the coast of the eastern Mediterranean, including Judea and the old Phoenicia and the coast of Asia Minor

NOTE: Insert Map 22. THE EMPIRE OF ALEXANDER THE GREAT

ITALY

In 400 B.C. the Gauls plundered Etruria in northern Italy, conquering Felsina, which subsequently became known as Bononia. Ten years later, under King Brennus, they sacked Rome itself and retreated only after the payment of 1,000 pounds of gold. Thus began the long Roman-Gallic wars which did not end until the time of Julius Caesar in the 1st century of the Christian era. In spite of the Gauls, Perusia, which had broken free from Clusium, was the most powerful Etruscan center in the upper Tiber Valley. The Clusines spread their alphabet up the Adriatic coast to Venetia and the northeast and it became the basis of the alphabets of Venetia, Illyria and Raetia as well as of the German and Scandinavian runes. Meanwhile the Romans also had to continue to fight the Etruscan city-state of Veii, destroying it about 396 B.C. and then take on the powerful and highly civilized Samnite tribes of southern Italy. The only Etrurian power left in the immediate vicinity of Rome was Tarquinii and a seven year war flared up with it in 358 B.C. In 343 B.C. the Greek cities in Campania (Naples area) joined the Samnites in their campaign against Rome, but in spite of all this warfare some advancement of civilization did occur in Rome. The Compromise of Camillus in 367 B.C. gave concessions to the Plebes and internal dissension stopped, leaving energies free for expansion. The Appian Way was started at this time. While the Etruscan towns had always remained small, chiefly in the 5,000 to 10,000 bracket, early in this century Rome probably passed the 10,000 mark and drew level with Tarentum, the largest Greek city in Italy. (Ref. 17, 18, 19)

Although after the destruction of Veii by the Romans the Etruscan preponderance in central Italy came to an end, some Etruscan cities still flourished. Vulci had failed to help Veii in its death struggle and continued to exist as a thriving city. After a forty year truce, fighting again flared up between Rome and Tarquinii with the former the final victor in 314 B.C. At long last Caere had finally broken with Rome and had joined Tarquinii in its last days. Its independence gone, Caere still was a great cosmopolitan city to which Roman sons were sent to learn the Etruscan language and literature. (Ref. 20)

In the last of the century the Gauls actually settled down in northern Italy (Cisalpine Gaul) laying the foundations for the cities of Turin, Bergamo and Milan. The Kyllyrioi disappeared from Sicily in the early century and slavery became the only form of involuntary labor and this remained so after the island was conquered by the Romans. (Ref. 21) (For more about Sicily, see NORTH CENTRAL AFRICA).

CENTRAL EUROPE

The population of this region was essentially Celtic, particularly in Austria and Germany, although some Germanic tribes were wandering down from Scandinavia about the Vistula River and these may have been pushed somewhat west at this time by Huns leaving the region of the Volga. McEvedy (Ref. 22) writes that there were still no Teutons south of the latitude of Berlin and that this was to remain so for two more centuries. East of the Germanic tribes were the Balts and the Slavs.

The Hallstatt Celtic culture in Austria was based on salt which was mined particularly at Salzburg and at Durrnberg near Hallein. In Bohemia tin became an important export. The newer La Tene Culture evolved full flower in the old Celtic homelands, marking the second phase of the P-Celtic speakers' expansion. They developed an original art, part of which involved covering tiny surfaces of pots, sword sheaths and ornaments with mazes of lines, tiny animal figures and faces, all cut in minute detail. They manufactured brass and covered copper objects with tin and silvered them over with mercury.

In their first contacts with the Mediterranean world the Celtic people struck terror throughout the existing civilizations. They were tall, blond, with hair standing up stiff from their foreheads from lime washings, and then hanging long behind like horses' manes. They wore long mustaches and dressed in brightly colored shirts and breeches with cloaks fastened at the shoulder with brooches. The cloaks were striped or checkered. Some wore bronze helmets and chain breast armor, although others went naked into battle where they charged with wild screaming and singing, some on foot and some in four-wheeled chariots drawn by two horses and carrying one driver and one javelin thrower. Cavalry operated in the same way, each mount with two riders. But the most terrifying of all was their custom of cutting off their enemies' heads and nailing them over the doors of their huts.

In general the Celts preferred to remain potentially mobile and kept their possessions all in a state of readiness for travel, but in some locations they did build rather impressive settlements. One such was near Manching, Bavaria, where the outer wall was four miles long, enclosing an area of some forty thousand acres. There is evidence of goldsmiths, bronze foundries, iron and glass works, potteries and trading houses. Not far away was a foundry where sixty-two smelt furnaces have been excavated. Every Celtic town had small foundries and most had salt sources nearby. (Ref. 23)

WESTERN EUROPE

The La Tene Celts were at their peak of power throughout France (Gaul), England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland. In Spain there were also Celts, but Carthage had established a protectorate over all the Iberian tribes up as far as the Pyrenees. An interesting side-light on the nature of the early Iberian language is offered by Barry Fell. (Ref. 24) We have generally been told that the early language of the Mediterranean world was unique and that perhaps remnants today are to be found in Basque and tongues of the Caucasus. Fell says that a recent study would indicate that the old Iberic language was Semitic and closely related to classical Arabic. A recently found stone inscription from eastern Spain at Pujol was in the ancient Iberian letters but was Greek in language. This probably dates to about 300 B.C. when Carthage still dominated Mediterranean shipping.

The entire British Isles, called "Pretanic Islands of Albion and Ierne" were circumnavigated by Pytheas of Marseilles, but his story was not believed at that time. His journey had been made possible by the opening of the Straits of Gibralter as the entire Carthaginian navy had been withdrawn to attack Sicily. As a result of the astronomical observations made by Pytheas on that trip to Britain, he began to get the first hint of the curvature of the earth, and he incidentally located the Cornish tin mines. London may have had its origin about 400 B.C. when a Celtic king, Belin, rebuilt an earth wall around a few dozen huts where the Walbrook joins the Thames and then cut an opening in the south wall for a landing spot. (Ref. 25) That Carthaginians were also in Britain in this century is at- tested by the finding of Carthaginian coins in two primary areas, dating to this period.

This is probably the time when the Picts either invaded Scotland or made themselves known as an aboriginal people. Their real origin is unknown, although the most recent thought is that they may have migrated from the north of the continent. In later times they spoke P-Celtic, but this may have been acquired from a wave of Celts and probably does not represent their native tongue. The Romans named them "Picts", meaning "painted ones". (Ref. 26, 27, 28)

SCANDINAVIA

A period of continued multiplication of the Germanic tribes.

EASTERN EUROPE

The basic populations of this region showed no basic change from the previous century. From the north down there were Finns, Balts, Slavs and finally the Scythians just north of the Black Sea. The uncertain history and legends of the Scythians were clarified, in part at least, by excavations of burial mounds in the 18th century C.E., with recovery of some twenty exquisitely carved gold objects found in a mine shaft and given to Czar Peter of Russia. The archeologists found subsequently that Herodotus ' descriptions of royal funerals was accurate, in that concubine, butler, cook, groom and stewards, all strangled, were buried with the royal personage. In addition gold cups, large collars made of twisted metal and other treasures, were included. It is apparent that gold was a sacred part of Scythian life, the metal coming from the Caucasus, Ural and distant Ural mountain ranges. We have then, an ancient barbarous, bloody people who at the same time were creative artists, working in gold. About 350 B.C. a still stronger, crueler, but related people, the Sauromatae, began crossing the Don, scattering the Scythians before them. Some of the latter went to Thrace (Romania) and some stayed in the Crimea, with a capital at Neapolis. If we are to believe Herodotus, writing a century earlier, the Sauromatae spoke a language similar to Scythian because some Amazon women had, in effect, seduced some Sythian boys and taken them back to their home across the Don. It was perhaps these women who allegedly rode and fought alongside their men, giving rise to the legend that Scythian women were warriors. Herodotus writes that no Sauromatae Amazon could marry until she had killed a man in battle. (Ref. 29, 30, 31)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

6 [125]  LYONS, ALBERTS., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI,R. JOSEPH,M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

7 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

8 [125]  LYONS, ALBERTS., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI,R. JOSEPH,M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

9 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

10 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

11 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

12 [72] GIBBONS, BOYD, "The Bulgarians", National Geographic 158: 91, July, 1980.

13 [179] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Bulgaria's Golden Treasures", National Geographic 158: 112, July, 1980.

14 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

15 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

16 [125]  LYONS, ALBERTS., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI,R. JOSEPH,M.D.,Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

17 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

20 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

21 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

22 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

23 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

24 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

25 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

26 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

27 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

28 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

29 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

30 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

31 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

1.  This is hyoscyamus (also scopolamine), an ingredient of "twilight sleep"

Europe: 300 to 201 B.C.

EUROPE

At 300 B.C. there were Celts in every part of Europe excepting Scandinavia, the southern portions of Italy and Greece and Russia. Most of the European river names such as the Rhine, Main (Moin), Neckar, Lahn, Ruhr, Isar, etc. are Celtic in origin. If the various Celtic tribes could have gotten along together and made a concerted effort they could have created one of the greatest empires in European history, but they didn't. (Ref. 1)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Crete had become a haven for Mediterranean pirates. The Cylades were under Greek control. South of Asia Minor Rhodes had become a powerful commercial state. The "Colossus of Rhodes" was completed in 280 B.C. by the sculptor, Chares, after twelve years of work with the spoils left by Demetrius' unsuccessful siege in the previous century. Rising 120 feet, this bronze statue of the sun god was so large that a ship could pass between its legs. (Ref. 2, 3)

GREECE

This was a time of considerable chaos and confusion in the Greek peninsula. The Galatian Celts in about 280 B.C. raided from high up in the Balkans down through Macedonia and into Greece proper and were defeated only with great difficulty. The Celtic army probably had no more than 30,000 men and was led by Brennus, of the same name as the chieftain who had sacked Rome over a century before. Greece was divided among the Aetolian League, which expanded in the north central and western area by force, the Achaean League, which expanded by contract and the independent states of Sparta and Athens. The former was defeated in 222 B.C. by a coalition of Achaeans with the Macedonian King Antigonus Doson.

Although there was a shift of Greek science and medicine to Alexandria, philosophy was still prevalent in the homeland. Epicurus founded Epicureanism, a belief that pleasure is the chief good, but that the greatest pleasure may be obtained through a life of temperance and simplicity. The great evil that afflicts man is fear of gods and fear of death. The ultimate aim of all Epicurean theories and teaching was to rid humanity of these two fears. (Ref. 4, 5)

UPPER BALKANS

When the Macedonian leader, Cassander, died in 297 B.C., Demetrius I (Poliocertes) returned again to try for the king-ship. He did take Athens in 295 B.C. but was eventually deserted by his own troops and became a prisoner of Seleucus for the rest of his life. (Ref. 6) Celtic peoples were collecting in the upper Balkan area, fighting among themselves and periodically raiding southward, shattering all balance of power in Alexander's old empire and the first divisions among his generals and their immediate successors.

The Macedonians, themselves, were completely overrun for a short while. At the end of the century as Hannibal gave Rome its most terrible war, Philip of Macedon sided with Hannibal and the skirmishes of Macedonian soldiers with Romans in this issue of the main war was called the First Macedonian War.

An Illyrian kingdom was set up at this period with a capital at Scodra (modern Scutari, Albania) but because of Illyrian piracy tendencies the Romans had cause to war also against them and ultimately defeat them. South and west of Macedonia, the small but strong kingdom of Epirus flourished and even attacked Italy across the Adriatic Sea at the instigation of the local Greek city-states.  (Ref.7)

ITALY

This was a century of great Roman activity. By 290 B.C. all territory of the Sabines had come under Roman rule, and after the battle of Lake Vadimo about 280 B.C. the Samnite resistance was crushed and Rome controlled all the harbors of Italy as well as having perhaps 40,000 slave-captives. In 281 B.C. a Roman general had also triumphed over Etruscan Volsinii and Vulci. Italy was densely populated by a hardy peasantry, which gave the Romans a dependable pool of military man-power. Their labor force, like the Greeks before them, was slaves. Rome, too, was a slave society. (Ref. 8)

NOTE: Insert 23: ITALY BEFORE THE FIRST PUNIC WAR 264 B.C.

In the meantime, Pyrrhus, king of Epirus in the Balkans, and a kinsman of Alexander the Great, responded to pleas of the Greek city-states of Syracuse (Sicily) and Tarentum on the heel of the boot and helped them fight the Romans for control of south Italy. Rome was even joined by Carthage in this particular fight, in the attempt to keep Pyrrhus out of Sicily. King Pyrrhus brought 25,OOO men and many elephants which terrified the Italians and he initially won some victories at Heraclea (280 B.C.) and Asculum (279 B.C.) but lost many men and much strength, so that by 275 Rome had won and had reached the toe and heel of the boot of Italy. Carthage still held the western end of Sicily. (Ref. 9, 10)

By 260 B.C. Rome controlled 10,000 square miles of Italy, and with her allies another 52,000 square miles. It had about 292,000 men and its allies about 750,000, with a total population of about 3,000,000. This powerful confederacy had now become a potential challenge to Carthage and war between the two great powers broke out in 264 B.C. This First Punic War began a century of warfare for the mastery of the Mediterranean. With Hamilcar (see footnote on page 243) leading the Carthaginians and Regulus becoming the Roman hero, this was essentially a series of gigantic sea battles with a few land skirmishes in Sicily and the southern tip of Italy. The Romans won the sea battles by the "corvus", a boarding crane that allowed their soldiers to board the Carthaginian ships. (See NORTH CENTRAL AFRICA, earlier in this chapter, page 233). Carthage sued for peace in 241 B.C., giving Sicily to Rome and removing restrictions on Roman trade in the Mediterranean. In the next four years, while Carthage was torn by a bloody internal revolution, Rome took Sardinia and Corsica in treaty violations. (Ref. 11, 12)

These treaty violations set the stage for the Second Punic War beginning in 219 B.C. and continuing until 201. The Carthaginian General Hannibal (See footnote on page 243) entered Spain, enlisted Gaul mercenaries1, got help from Macedonia and Sicily, crossed the Alps with men and elephants, conquered most of Italy except Rome itself, and in a final winter, bedded his army down in Capua, south of Rome. He was poorly supplied from Carthage through Tarentum, which had fallen in 209 B.C. and his troops now seemed to lose their vigor. (Ref. 13) In 202 B.C. Hannibal was called back to Carthage where he was finally defeated by the Roman General Scipio, who was helped by Numidian cavalry under King Massinissa. In the end, Rome controlled all of Italy and Spain, but it was a costly war which changed Roman life considerably. There was an increase in urbanity with damage to the concept of democracy and the beginning of imperialistic expansion. Other factors may have played additional roles in the ending of rural simplicity. Apparently a declining rainfall about 250 B.C. provoked a marked decrease in the flow of Italian rivers, with resulting formation of mosquito-breeding marshes and stagnant pools. The mosquitoes, in turn, brought malaria. Grain production dropped and the grapevine and the olive began to be the big crops, so that even when the rains returned late in the century, Rome was already dependent forever on imported grain. The tens of thousands of slaves obtained in warfare augmented the slave society. But the capstone and triumph of Roman democracy also occurred in this century with the Lex Hortensia, in 287 B.C., a law in which the Senate agreed that decisions of the tribal assembly should have the force of law, even when contrary to the resolutions of the Senate.

NOTE: Insert 25. THE PUNIC WARS 264-146 B.C.

In Sicily it was the time of Archimedes and his great scientific accomplishments. When King Hiero of Syracuse went over to Hannibal's side in the Second Punic War, the Romans sieged Syracuse and Archimedes' invention of the water screw held the Romans at bay for some time. In the final attack on the city in 212 B.C., however, the scientist was killed. He had already established the laws of levers, methods of measurement of a sphere and a cylinder, the value of Pi and various laws of hydrostatics. He had either studied in Alexandria or had been in close contact with scholars from there.

CENTRAL EUROPE

The Celtic settlement of Austria was well under way by 279 B.C. and the great salt mines of Salzburg and adjacent areas were in operation. A tribe called "Teutones" had settled close to the Main River and some have interpreted this to mean that Germanic tribes were already in this area, but these were actually simply another Celtic tribe, and the true Teutonic or Germanic tribes had not yet left the northern reaches of Germany.

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

In the first half of the century Spain was essentially under the control of Carthage and there were various wars of the local Iberian, Ligurian and Celtic tribes against these overlords. The First Punic War had stimulated the Carthaginians to increase their dominance of Iberia. In 238 B.C. after the first Punic war, Hamilcar Barcal crossed to Spain and recaptured those cities for Carthage whose allegiance had lapsed during the war years. Tradition has it that he founded Barcelona and Cartagena and that in accordance with his recommendations to his troops to intermarry with the natives, his own son, Hannibal, did so. He died during a charge against a Spanish tribe and Hasdrubal2, nephew of Hamilcar, continued a three year campaign and then signed a treaty at Cartagena with Roman envoys agreeing not to go north of the Ebro River. Rome feared Carthaginian alliance with the Celts in the Pyrenees. By 221 B.C., however, Hamilcar's son, Hannibal, incorporating many Iberians in his army had captured Roman-Greek Saguntum on the east coast and precipitated the Second Punic War. By 218 B.C. Hannibal had crossed the Pyrenees to advance through France to Italy.

The Roman General Scipio the elder went from his home in Rome to Spain to fight the rear guard of the Carthaginian army which was still under the command of Hasdrubal and by 205 B.C. Spain had become a Roman province although the complete conquest actually took another 200 years with heavy toll in men and money because of constant guerilla warfare. Scipio, however, took his army to Africa to attack Carthage directly. It was his son, Scipio Africanus, however, who fought the final battles in Africa. (Ref. 15, 16)

FRANCE AND NETHERLANDS & BELGIUM

As previously mentioned concerning the Celts in general, the Gauls bleached their hair and wore jewelry but they were also vicious fighters, charging into battle some- times wearing chain mail and sometimes naked or wearing only collars and bracelets and formidable mustaches. Some were very tall, fair-haired and blue-eyed and may have been a ruling class over other shorter and dark-haired people. As did their central European brothers, they cut off their enemies heads and hung them around their horses necks, often later lining the skulls of enemy generals with gold. When not fighting they feasted, drank and hunted. The Gallic women of ten fought beside their men (See Queen Boadicca in 1st century C.E. under BRITISH ISLES). On their southern flanks the Celtic tribes were showing a gradual rising of their cultural level as contact was made with the southern civilizations, particularly Rome. (Ref. 17)

BRITISH ISLES

The new waves of La Tene Celts were even more warlike than their predecessors and became a warrior aristocracy in Wales and Cornwall. The Welsh and Cornish languages are survivors of these gifted, virile people who were prone to inter-tribal warfare and dynastic feuds. They squandered their force in endless competitiveness. Barry Fell (Ref. 18) has allegedly translated an ancient Irish manuscript of the 2nd century B.C. which appears to be a copy of a 3rd century document, because of reference to certain Italian and Sicilian coins of the latter century, and which appears to be a code of laws for Irish Celts, written by a Spanish Gael. This would indicate a much earlier presence of Celts in Ireland then usually stated. The Picts of Scotland were never a united people in these early centuries and the tribes warred with each other constantly.

SCANDINAVIA

Scandinavian tribes continued to expand and this may have been the period when they displaced a Mongolian people akin to or antecedents of the Laplanders and Esquimos, pushing them into the frozen north.

EASTERN EUROPE

Southern Russia and the Eurasian steppe was still the breeding ground of various barbarian Aryan tribes which periodically moved toward Europe proper and down into southwestern Asia. The Scythians were gradually being replaced by their racial and linguistic kinsmen, the Samaritans, about whom we have written previously.

1 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

2 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

5 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

6 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

8 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

14 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

15 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

16 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

17 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

18 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

1.  14,000 Gaul mercenaries signed up with Hannibal and in addition a whole series of Celtic units in the Roma legions killed their officers and taking their victims heads along, deserted to the Carthaginians. (Ref. 14)

2.  There were generals named Hamilcar, Hannibal and Hasdrubal in the 5th century B.C. as well as these apparent descendants in this 3rd century B.C.

Europe: 200 to 101 B.C.

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

As the commerce of Rhodes declined the government allied itself with Rome, a situation which was to continue for several centuries. In the Cyclades there were frequent changes of control. Crete remained a somewhat wild area with nests of pirates while Cyprus was still subservient to Egypt. (Ref. 1)

GREECE

From this time on for a number of centuries the affairs and destiny of Greece became intimately connected and almost inseparable from the Roman Empire and the military and political expansion of Hellenism lost momentum. The Romans fastened their control on Macedonia and Greece with remarkable ease between 200 and 146 B.C.. Sparta, under Nabis, attempted a revival of independence in 195 B.C. but it ended with Roman conquest. At the request of the Aetolians, Antiochus III brought Syrian forces into Greece in 192 B.C., but they, too, were routed by the Romans in the following year. Various members of the Achaean League fought as late as 146 B.C., but they did so in a divided way and fell, to become a mere backwater of the Roman Empire. As a political entity Greece disappeared from history for 2,000 years. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

UPPER BALKANS

It was mentioned in the last chapter that Philip of Macedonia had given some help to Hannibal and that had started the Second Macedonian War in 200 B.C. Although Philip was beaten in a final battle at Cynoscephalae in 197 B.C. he was graciously restored to his throne by the Roman victor, T. Quincteus Flamininus. (Ref. 5) As Rome took over more territory in Asia Minor Greek-Macedonian and Roman interests again collided, opening the way for the Third Macedonian War (171-168 B.C.) in which Perseus was defeated at Pydna. After seventy Macedonian towns were razed the Romans took direct rule of the country in 146 B.C. In the latter half of the century with its gold deposits exhausted and its manpower weakened by wars and emigration, Macedon could hardly maintain its former place among the world powers.

On the western coast of the Balkan area the Romans conquered Scodra (Albania) with its King Genthius, and established Illyrium as one of the earliest of the Roman colonies. Living in the areas of modern Yugoslavia and Serbia the Dalmatians split from the Illyrians and in several later battles Dalmatia was also then conquered by the Romans. The first Germanic tribe to reach into this area was the east German Bastarnian, which settled between the lower Danube and the Black Sea. (Ref. 6, 7)

ITALY (The map on page 242 will be applicable again)

In the first half of the century Rome continued the imperialistic conquests in the Mediterranean basin so that by 150 B.C. its territories included most of Spain, all of Italy to the Alps, Sardinia, Sicily, Illyria and the entire Greek peninsula. Allies included Numidia, Egypt, Pontus and after 133 B.C. Pergamum. In 159 B.C. after encouraging the Numidians to encroach upon Carthage to stimulate a fight locally, Rome moved in on the pretext of a broken treaty, declaring the Third Punic War. As noted in an earlier section, by 145 B.C. Carthage lay in burned ruins and Rome was in control of the Mediterranean. A typical Roman of this time was Cato, a sour, revengeful man - publicly moral, but individually cruel and selfish. He could not stand happiness in other people and it was he who urged on the Third Punic War with the slogan "Carthage must be destroyed".  (Ref.8)

Meanwhile at home all was not well and the signs of social downfall were already appearing. An uprising of slaves and free workers began in 196 B.C. and gradually increased in intensity. In 193 Tiberius Gracchus passed the Agrarian Law which was an attempt at reform, dividing large farms into segments to be given to the poor. Octavius, another tribune, opposed the reform and Tiberius had him thrown out, dividing Rome into two bitter factions. Tiberius was soon murdered and although his brother, Gaius Gracchus, became tribune and continued the reforms, the aristocrats won in the end and the land again began to be accumulated in large tracts and wealth concentrated in the hands of a few. Coupled with this was a general moral degeneration with restriction of the size of families by abortion and infanticide. The plunder from the provinces provided funds for orgies of corruption. The great indemnities exacted from the captured countries, with gold and silver seized, turned the propertied classes of Rome from men of means to persons of opulence so that reckless luxury resulted. It was a time of the rise and prominence of women, sexuality, and licentiousness.

In 144 B.C. another Agrarian Revolt broke out as a result of four factors:

The import of grain from abroad reducing the domestic price
The growth of large farms, as mentioned above
The influx of slaves for farm labor, which led to
The migration of the small farmer to the city

This revolution raged for 73 years and gradually passed into an actual civil war at the end of the century. Related were revolts of slaves on Sicilian plantations in 135 and 103 B.C. (Ref. 9) Finley (Ref. 10) writes that "--there was no action or belief or institution in Greco-Roman antiquity that was not one way or other affected by the possibility that someone involved might be a slave"1. Millions of slave owners bought and sold slaves, overworked them, beat and tortured them and sometimes killed them, without legal retribution.

Other troubles also developed with the invasion in the north by two Celtic tribes, the Cimbri and the Teutones, who defeated Roman armies as they rolled on down through Gaul. In addition the Numidians in North Africa turned on them and attacked under the Leadership of Jugurtha, as we have detailed in section 1, B of this chapter.

Originally Roman medicine had been inherited from the Etruscans and was based chiefly on religious healing, but Greek medicine gradually infiltrated from Alexandria. The first well known Greek physician to go to Rome was Archagathos of Sparta who had arrived with much celebration and honor just before this century opened, but who was later repudiated and called "butcher". (Ref. 11, 12)

CENTRAL EUROPE

The Germanic or Teutonic tribes now began to dominate central Europe. They were fair-haired like the Celts, but taller. By 150 B.C. the pressure of these tribes in the north and the Romans in the south had begun to tip the military balance against the Celts and their culture started to disappear in central Europe except in the kingdom of Noricum (present day southern Austria) from which the Romans had been forced to with- draw, and Switzerland. By the end of the century the Romans had pretty well reconquered these areas also.

WESTERN EUROPE

The Celtic peoples were now concentrated all along the Atlantic states. We insert at this time a few remarks about the Celtic religion, since the only source of inf ormation has been from the Roman records as they conf ronted the Celts in Gaul. Throughout all their tribes, the Celts had a priestly caste of Druids, although each group seemed to have its own local dieties and cults. The Druids were teachers of the young nobility and they forecasted the future. Once a year, Druid priests from all over met in solemn assembly near Chartres, France. They mediated disputes between tribes and enforced their judgments by excommunication or exclusion from the sacrifices, which seemed central to this religion.

The sacrifices included humans, of ten criminals or prisoners of war, and they were of ten burned in a sea of flames. (Ref. 13) The suggestion has been made that the astronomical knowledge and the basic cult of the Druids may have been passed to them from prehistoric peoples in England.

The Germanic tribes continued raids into western continental Europe, pushing the Celts into more and more rather narrow bands along the Atlantic and into the British Isles. The Cimbers and the Teutons had left Jutland and Schleswig-Holstein about 120 B.C., migrated into Gaul, defeating several Roman armies and spreading fear and terror. The two tribes finally separated, however, and were then defeated by the Roman Marius, in 102 B.C. The Cimbrians met their defeat at Aqua Sextia and the Teutons at Vercellae. But the Cimbri had already sent forces into Spain from Germany and in Portugal the Lusitanian tribes, led by Viriathus, defeated all Roman armies for eight years before they finally fell as their leader was assassinated. In Gaul, Rome had to fight "barbarians" all along the Rhone River to protect Massilia, and by 120 B.C. they had organized southern Gaul into a separate Roman province. (Ref. 14, 15)

What appear to be Phoenician beads have been excavated near St. Sampson, Cornwall, dating from the 2nd century B.C. on, seeming to confirm the presence of the Carthaginians there as traders for tin. (Ref. 16) In Scotland the fusion of Picts, Celts, Norwegians and Bell-Beaker people continued, with the Picts probably the dominant group, although accepting some Celtic speech. (Ref. 17)

SCANDINAVIA

The Germanic tribes spread all through Scandinavia moving up across the Skaggerak and Kattegot into Norway and even northern Sweden. Many of the tribes seem to have originated, or at least made their preliminary proliferations, in the Denmark area. This period appears to have been the first of some recurring times of tremendous population growth in southern Scandinavia with the resulting necessity for migration of multitudes of people from the area.

EASTERN EUROPE

An Iranian tribe, the Sarmatians, had conquered and gradually displaced almost all the Scythians, although a few of the latter remained east of the Caspian Sea. After the Sarmatians had extended all across the whole of the Russian steppe they, in the second half of the century, divided into three groups:

Iazygians, west of the lower Dneiper
Roxolani, between the Dneiper and the Don, and
Alans, to the east and just north of the Caspian (Ref. 18)

 Greek colonies around the Black Sea fell into decay and the Kingdom of Pontus, under Mithridates IV, took control of most of the Black Sea shore, including the Crimea. In the upper Dneiper basin, the northward advance of the Dneiper Slavs began to result in the ejection or absorption of the Balts in the area.

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [77] "GREEK MEDICINE", (Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Newsmagazine, Vol. 3, No. 9, Sept. 1959).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

11 [125]  LYONS, ALBERTS., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

12 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

13 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

14 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

15 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

16 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

17 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

18 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

1.  Reference 249, page 65

Europe: 100 B.C. to 0

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

This was the century when Rome gained control of most of the Mediterranean. Augustus took the Cyclades and conquered Crete in 68 - 67 B.C. and Cyprus in 58. Rhodes was already under Roman jurisdiction. (Ref. 1)

GREECE

Greece became a battle ground for several different campaigns including the First Mithridatic War when the Pontus king was stopped only after he had gotten well down into this peninsula. Athens, which had allied itself with Mithridates, had its prosperity come to an end when it was sacked by the troops of the Roman Sulla in 87 and 86 B.C.. After the sea battle of Actium of 31 B.C. in which Antony and Cleopatra lost to Octavian, Rome legally as well as effectively held the whole of Alexander's heritage in this land and Greece began a reign of peace as an integral part of the Roman Empire. The island of Delos had now become the center of the Athenian world and served as the greatest trading center for slaves in the civilized world.

UPPER BALKANS

The basic population of this area remained Celtic and as a frontier of the Roman Empire it served as a battle ground for the Roman-Celtic conflicts, as well as part of the First Mithridatic War. The southern Illyrians were finally conquered by the Roman Augustus between 35 and 34 B.C. The Kingdom of Thrace remained intact and north of this the large Dacian Kingdom also kept its independence in the area of Romania. The Greeks called these people "Getas".

ITALY

As the century opened there was still some indecision as to the actual scope and power of Rome over the remainder of the Italian peninsula. In 91 B.C. there was one final war between Rome and her neighbors over the idea of a united Italy and the scope of the rule of the Roman Senate. It ended by the practical surrender of the Senate to the concept of reform which allowed thereafter all Italians to become Roman citizens by decree. The classical Latin language emerged about 100 B.C. af ter some imprints from the languages of Asia Minor, the Balkans and Greece and this classical tongue then held sway for about 300 years.

On the government scene, while Sulla was in Asia Minor and the Balkans, the consuls Cinna and Marius had instituted a reign of terror, dissolved the Senate and ruled with "iron hands" until Marius' death. When Sulla returned he made himself a dictator and while restoring law and order and the Senate to power, he desolated large parts of Italy, executing over 5,000 people. He tried to establish a permanently aristocratic constitution but this was followed by all sorts of complications. Among these was the revolt of the slaves under Spartacus in 73 B.C., just after Sulla's death. The slaves held out in southern Italy, using Vesuvius' crater for a time as a fortress but when they were at last captured after two years by Crassus and Pompey some 6,000 were crucified along the Appian way. The two generals, former cronies of Sulla, had risen to power through separate and originally conflicting ways. Gnaeus Pompeius, after prevailing upon Sulla to give him the title of Magnus (The Great), won prominence by subduing the traitor Quintus Sertorius, who as a governor of Spain had attempted to set up a separatist regime of his own in that province. Crassus, in addition to his victory over the slaves, had made himself fabulously wealthy through various and sundry unscrupulous deals and now the two men united to undue Sulla's constitution and had themselves elected consuls in 70 B.C. This was the era of Marcus Tullius Cicero, a lawyer who had as his fondest desire to be accepted into the inner circle of the Senatorial class and his whole career was geared to that aim. By prosecuting one of the corrupt provincial governors Cicero gained a praetorship and a rise to power. Meanwhile Pompey gained still more esteem by conquering the Cilician and Cretan pirates who had been preventing normal sea commerce in the Mediterranean and disrupting the great slave emporium at Delos. Soon, therefore, with Cicero's help, Pompey was given absolute power over both land and sea forces through the entire empire. It was then that he went to reorganize the entire Near East. When he returned after several years involvement in the Mithridatic wars, organizing Asia Minor and Syria and conquering Jerusalem he allegedly brought back some two million slaves. (Ref. 2)

Gaius Julius Caesar was the youngest ruler of the late Republic. By 58 B.C. he had been a high priest, staff officer, finance minister, military governor, senator and consul. He had married three times, had countless love-affairs, led campaigns and been involved in various intrigues1. As he ascended the ladder of political power his offices entailed enormous expenses and this got him involved with the multi-millionaire, Crassus, from whom he had to borrow large sums of money. After a period as governor of Spain, Caesar returned to Rome to join the power group of Crassus and Pompey.

Although meeting some opposition in the Senate led by Cato the Younger, a follower of Greek ideals and standing for an honest financial policy in government, Caesar, Crassus and Pompey formed an extra-legal coalition called "the First Triumvirate". Each soon went his separate way, however, with Caesar conducting his victorious campaigns in Gaul2, Germany and Britain, then returning to take control of Rome, over Pompey's objections. This was followed by a victorious trip to the Middle East in Syria and Egypt. When Caesar then returned to Rome there was great inflation and the "annona", or free grain distribution from the public granaries was excessive. Even by 71 B.C. some 40,000 adult male citizens had been receiving free grain, and in the next decades it increased greatly so that Caesar thought he did well to cut back to 150,000 free-loaders.

Meanwhile Crassus had obtained command of the eastern forces and prepared to emulate the glories of Lucullus and Pompey in Asia Minor and Armenia, but Crassus ran into the Parthians. These fierce Iranians, perhaps with Turanian Mongolian mercenaries, killed 20,000 Roman soldiers along with Crassus and captured 10,000 more at the Battle of Carrhae (53 B.C.) in Syria. The hold of the Romans on Mesopotamia was never very secure.

After Crassus' death Caesar and Pompey faced each other as antagonists and as the months went by definite lines of battle and forces were drawn up and actual civil war followed. Caesar soon won control of all Italy and gained Sardinia, Sicily and North Africa. After defeating Pompey's forces at Ilerda in Spain he returned to Rome to be made dictator. Pompey fled to the east where he built up a loyal military establishment but all for naught as Caesar caught up to him in Thessaly in 48 B.C. and defeated him. Pompey fled to Egypt only to be assassinated by the teen-aged Ptolemy XIII. After having been made dictator "for life" by the Senate in 45 B.C., Caesar was assassinated by "friends" to whom his divine aspirations were intolerable. The extent of the Roman Republic at the death of Caesar is shown in the map below.

NOTE: Insert Map 28: THE ROMAN REPUBLIC AT THE DEATH OF CAESAR

Marc Antony, who had shared a consulship with Caesar, considered himself the sole heir of Caesar and he, with the latter's nephew, Gaius Julius Caesar Octavianus (later Octavian) and Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, who had followed Sulla as consul, all together formed the Second Triumvirate. Publicly the purpose of this association was to avenge the death of Caesar but actually it merely set up power bases for Antony and Octavian. Inevitably they could not abide each other and the quarrels terminated with the Battle of Actium off the Greek coast in 31 B.C. with Octavian winning and subsequently ruling alone as emperor, called Augustus. The people accepted his dictatorship because they had been faring so poorly under the previous senatorial oligarchy. A reign of peace, another "Golden Age", resulted.

Before this time the Romans had raised armies only for specific tasks, disbanding them after the mission was accomplished, but Augustus created a standing army of 25 legions with the equivalent of another, the Praetorian Guard, in Italy as his personal protection. Of the others, 8 legions were stationed along the Rhine, 3 along the Danube in the Balkan area, 4 in the Yugoslav territory, 4 in Syria and Lebanon, 2 each in Egypt and Portugal, and one each in northern Spain and Carthage. Each legion contained 5,000 men divided into 10 cohorts of 480 each.

In spite of the "Golden Age", the relief roles had again built up in Rome to 320,000 so that just under one-third of the population had to receive free government grain to exist. It took some 14 million bushels of grain each year just to supply the city itself where 1,500,000 citizens lived, housed in some 46,600 insulae (apartment blocks) three to eight stories high, made of wood, rubble and brick. Windows were simply wall openings and were covered with shutters or hangings. Only the rich had wells or taps into the city conduits; the rest got water from public fountains. There were public lavatories and toilet receptacles which were frequently emptied into the street. Menial work was done by about 2,000,000 slaves, a middle class citizen owning about eight while the rich might have up to one thousand and an emperor twenty thousand. Slaves made up 35% of the population of Italy. (Ref. 4) Livy stated that it was common for Roman orators to state that "--Jews, Syrians, Lydians, Medes, indeed all Asiatics are born to slavery"3 Horses were of little use as a source of energy in this Roman period as they were badly harnessed with the yoke tending to throttle them and they could draw only a light load. Four slaves could do as much. Engineers did manage to change water wheels to the vertical position and add gears which greatly increased their efficiency for turning mill-stones. (Ref. 5)

NOTE: INSERT Map 30: ROME 100 B.C.

Hellenic culture continued to pour into Rome and literature and art took new dignity.Cicero, Catullus, Virgil, Horace and Livius the historian, all translated and adjusted Greek learning to the Latin tongue. A great philosophical poem, giving the views of Democritus and Epicurus was written by Lucretius, the Roman Epicurean, during this century. The wealthy hired Greek nurses and teachers for their children. The Roman physicians of this period were chiefly Greeks or at least Greek-trained. Asclepiades, originally of Bithynia, developed a high reputation as a physician and was a friend of Cicero and Lucretius. He abandoned the old Hippocrates doctrine of the four humors and felt that the physician, not nature, cured disease. Most Roman practitioners were either freedmen or slaves. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14)

Lucius Licinium Lucullus, one of the Roman generals in the Third Mithridatic War, is credited with bringing the cherry into Europe from the - shores of the Black Sea. Every Roman (as well as every Greek) had his beehives, as honey was the only sweetening common in the West. Indian cane sugar was more expensive and the raw cane was actually less tasty than honey, so there was no attempt to import it, except for medicinal purposes. (Ref. 15, 16)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

There was now a predominance of Germanic tribes in the area of present day Germany and Caesar and the Romans never actually penetrated that area although Roman merchants and traders did appear with goods to trade for furs and slaves. As the Germanic tribes came south their first encounters were with Celts, but whether much fighting was involved or not is unknown. Actually the Germans were very little different from the Celts; their religions and their languages had common origins. The Romans said the Germans were rather blonder, but otherwise little physical distinction was made.

Drusus conquered the Bavarian region for Rome from the Celts in 15 B.C. and Rhaetia, which included parts of southern Bavaria along with the Tyrol and east Switzerland, was established as a Roman province late in the century.

AUSTRIA AND HUNGARY

Having conquered the Celtic Cimbri and Teutones coming down at the edge of Italy and Austria, the Romans now squeezed the Celts out of Austria and consolidated their authority along the Danube clear to Budapest. Some of eastern present day Hungary appeared to be a part of the Kingdom of Dacia, which held out against Roman control for another century.

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

The Celtic Boii people, for whom Bohemia was named were driven out of Bohemia at this time by the Germanic tribes descending from the north.

SWITZERLAND

As noted above east Switzerland was included in the Roman province of Rhaetia. The crowded Helvetii around Lake Neuchatel began a migration westward with cattle and wagons, leaving 400 villages and thousands of homesteads. Fearing a threat to her Mediterranean coastal province, Rome sent Caesar north to intercept the Helvetii and this he did as they poured through a gorge leaving the Lake Geneva area. Of 368,000 Helvetii, only 110,000 got back to Switzerland as the Romans retained control of the area. (Ref. 17)

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

Both of these areas continued as part of the Roman Empire. It has been noted under ITALY above that Julius Caesar was sent to Spain in 59 B.C. to suppress the guerrilla warfare and he did get some help from local groups. It was still later, however, after he had been given Gaul in the First Triumvirate that he became locked in a power struggle with Pompey and returned to Spain, defeating Pompey's son in the great battle of Munda near Cordoba in 45 B.C., thereby gaining mastery of the world. The Iberians then adopted the Roman language and culture. (Ref. 18)

FRANCE AND NETHERLANDS & BELGIUM

Gaul (France) was still essentially Celtic and Caesar's conquests began the Latinization of the country and helped to contain the Teutonic people to the east of the Rhine. The curly-headed Parisii, a Celtic tribe consisting of fishermen and navigators, settled a five acre Ile de la Cete in the river which is now in the center of Paris. The Batave Germanic tribe settled in the Rhine delta, now known as the Netherlands about 14 B.C. and they and the Frisians became the ancestors of the modern Dutch. (Ref. 19)

After Julius Caesar massacred the Swiss, as noted in a paragraph above, he proceeded in the next eight years to "pacify" all of Gaul, taking some eight hundred towns and killing, by his own count, 1,292,000 men, women and children. He may have enslaved nearly another 2,000,000. In 55 B.C. Caesar experienced and described the greatest naval battle that he had ever been called upon to mount4. His opponents were the Celts of Brittany and their allies from Britain, who had no less than 220 ships, all larger than and superior in construction to those of the Romans under Admiral Rutus. These vessels, which towered over the Roman galleys, had the capability of crossing the Atlantic (Barry Fell's concept) and were apparently under the leadership of the Veneti of Armorica with their allies, the Curiosolites, the Venelli of the Channell Islands and Cherbourg, the Namnetes and Lexovii of Normandy. The high-bowed, graceful ships propelled by the wind were only defeated when the Romans hurled falces into the rigging of the Celtic vessels, then rowing away, tearing out the rigging. Then grappling irons were thrown and the 200 men in each trireme would board the Celtic vessel and in hand-to-hand combat they finally won. (Ref. 20, 21)

NOTE: Insert Map 27: GAUL IN CAESAR'S TIME

On land it required a great engineering feat for Caesar's legions to breach the "murus galliciul", a box-like grid of timbers filled with rubble and stone that surrounded the Celt town of Avaricum (present Bourges, in the center of France) and then slaughter the 40,000 people within. The Gauls at last rallied behind a young chief, Vercingetorix, who first had his people burn their fields and towns as they retreated so that the Roman troops could not live off the land, and then he initiated guerrilla warfare to cut off new supplies to the Roman troops. Vercingetorix was finally cornered in the hills of eastern, central France behind some fortifications. Caesar further surrounded these with nine and a half miles of fortifications of his own to try and contain the Celtic chieftain. Even then Vercingetorix slipped out some cavalry by night and had them gather an additional quarter of a million Gauls from some forty different tribes. In the interim Caesar had built still another circle of fortifications fourteen miles in circumference, facing outward to meet the Gallic reinforcements. For days the battles raged, with the methodical butchery of the 40,000 legionnaires of Rome finally prevailing. Vercingetorix emerged alone from the fort of Alesia, surrendered and was taken prisoner to Rome where he was paraded through the Forum and finally strangled to death some six years later. Caesar allegedly obtained enough slaves after Alesia to give one to each of his legionaires. The course of Gallic civilization was all down-hill from this time on. (Ref. 23, 24, 25)

BRITISH ISLES

The Belgic tribes were the last of the successive waves of Celts into Britain. They were a people of chariots and horses who introduced a coinage of silver and copper and established themselves as a tribal aristocracy. The Belgic capital was Colchester. The most ancient lettering known in Britain is to be found on the Belgic coins. This tribe seems to have been a mixture of Celtic and Teutonic origin from the region of the lower Rhine. Their new country produced corn, cattle, gold, silver, iron, hides, slaves and hunting dogs. Caesar crossed the channel starting at midnight August 26, 55 B.C. with 80 transports for his legions, experiencing considerable trouble in so doing, with the loss of some ships and men. He won a few victories over the Belgae under their leader, Cassivellaunus, but hastily departed England before winter set in. (Ref. 26, 27)

Scotland and Ireland were probably not yet involved in these new invasions and remained essentially as in the last century.

SCANDINAVIA

According to Tacitus, writing about A.D. 100, Sweden in the first century B.C. was dominated by the Suione Teutonic tribe. Scandinavia was never entered by the Romans, although trade was carried on with Danish amber, fur and various slaves exchanged for several Roman products, including wines and some iron objects.

EASTERN EUROPE

In this and the past century the Germanic Goths had appeared around Sweden and the Baltic Sea and started migration down into northeastern Germany. Just to the east of them were the Finno-Ugric speaking Estonians and just south of them in the Polish area and extending into middle Russia were Slavs. In southern Russia the Sarmatians were in the ascendancy and they spread out well to the east to the Caspian.

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

4 [249]. FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

6 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

7 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

8 [21] BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

9 [1] ABBOTT, SHIRLEY, The National Museum of American History, (Harry N. Abrahams, Inc. New York, 1981).

10 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

11 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

12 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

13 [185] ROMAN MEDICINE, in Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, 3: No. 8, Aug. 1959.

14 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

15 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

16 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

17 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

18 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

19 [175]. READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

20 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

21 [65] SEVERY, MERLE, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

22 [65] SEVERY, MERLE, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

23 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

24 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

25 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

26 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

27 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

1.  These remarks about Caesar were taken almost verbatim from Herm (Ref. 3), page 164

2.  The reader will find some interesting material regarding the difficulties of Caesar's conquests of the Gauls under the heading of WESTERN EUROPE, in this same chapter

3.  As quoted by Finley  (Ref. 6), page 119.

NOTE: INSERT Map 30: ROME 100 B.C.

4.  According to Barry Fell in America B.C. (Ref. 22), Caesar described this sea battle in "De Bello Gallico"

Europe: 0 to A.D. 100

EUROPE

An interesting bit of trivia is that while fermented drinks had been known and used by mankind for thousands of years, the process of distilling was discovered only in this first century of the Christian era. The Gaelic uisge beatha was corrupted to "whiskey" and the Germanic Gebrannterwein or Brandewin meaning "burnt wine" was eventually Anglicized to "brandy". (Ref. 1)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

A part of the Roman Empire.

GREECE

The city-states of Greece continued to govern themselves although theoretically they were under Roman rule. They were poor by virtue of Roman taxation and were almost destitute morally, spiritually and physically. This was the-time of Plutarch and of Epictetus, the slave philosopher who combined the concepts of the Stoics and Cynics into many ideas paralleling the attitudes of early Christianity, including the Golden Rule. Thus Stoicism, originally the proud and scornful philosophy of aristocrats, found its final and most eloquent voice in a slave. Its doctrine of a final conflagration of the world, its rejection of all pleasures of the flesh, its humble surrender to the hidden will of God, all were preparing for the theology and ethics of Christianity. The age of the Cyrics paved the way for the Christian monks.

Corinth became the wealthiest city of Greece while Athens remained an intellectual center. Eleusis, across the Aegean Sea, became a religious center of sacraments and "mysteries". (Ref. 2)

UPPER BALKANS

The Roman province of Pannonia, the most southern portion of which comprises present day Yugoslavia, was established in A.D. 9 after defeat of the native Illyrians.

Moesia, which had never been penetrated by Grecian influence, was organized as a province in A.D. 44. The upper Balkans now showed increased activities of all kinds. There was considerable agriculture, mining and herding, as well as commerce with Asia through the port of Salonika in Macedonia. Great cities were built and roads constructed, such as the Via Egnatia, that ran across the Albanian alps to Salonika and Constantinople. In Dacia (Romania) there was a strong tribe of the same name who were never subdued by the Romans in this century. In A.D. 85 they surged out across the Danube into Moesia (now Serbia and part of Bulgaria) but were pushed back by Domitian. The Romans could go no further, however, as the Marcomanni and Quadi, who had occupied Bohemia west of Dacia, joined the fray and defeated Domitian. A peace was signed with the Dacian king, Decebalus, and he subsequently turned on the Germanic tribes and defeated them. Iazygians were also squeezing in between Quadi and Dacians and Roxolani were approaching Dacia from the east. In the area that they did control, the Romans found Thracians useful as soldiers, slaves and especially as gladiators. (Ref. 3, 4, 5, 6)

ITALY

This was a century of some great and some lesser emperors of Rome in what has been called the "Silver Age" to indicate that it was not quite as good as the previous "Golden Age" under Octavian. The Julio-Claudian Dynasty continued under TIBERIUS Claudius Nero who reformed the government and law, advanced construction of public works, elevated the legal status of the provinces and re-subdued and Romanized Gaul and Britain. Tiberius' reign had been saved from any serious Parthian threat because of dynastic quarrels within Parthia. In A.D. 37 when Tiberius was dying he indicated as his successors his young grandson Tiberius Gemellus and the surviving son of Germanicus, Gauius Caesar Germanicus. The latter soon put the former to death and ruled alone as "CALIGULA", a probably insane, megalomaniac given to excesses and obscenities of all kinds. He was assassinated in 41 and Tiberius CLAUDIUS Drusus became emperor. His four wives were his undoing but he actually was a fairly able man and instituted some definite administrative improvements.

He was followed by Nero who began his reign well under the guidance of Seneca, but in spirit he was an actor and had to play the monarch in the grand manner. He was recklessly cruel to the aristocrats, but generous to the poor, with the possible exception of the new Christians who were first persecuted about A.D. 64, when Rome was burned.

Thereafter followed the Flavian Dynasty. Vespasian was a man of sense, ability and honor who directed the war against Judea and established the first system of state education. The last of this line was Domitian (A.D. 81 - 96) who managed the flourishing empire well during a great age of construction. At the end, however, like many others, he became very cruel, deified himself, indulged in sexual discrepancies and became paranoid about possible conspiracies against him. Throughout this age there was a decay of the native religion in Rome and the multiple gods of Jove, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and others began to give way to the Stoic philosophy. (See GREECE, above)

We should mention some of the non-political figures of this century. Seneca was born in Spain in 4 B.C. and became a copious writer, tutor to and later financial backer to Nero. Pliny the Elder (A.D. 23 - 79) was a great mind of the day, but his book Natural History with dissertations on humans, animals, metals, chemistry, medicine and astronomy, was actually a monument to Roman ignorance. He also compiled an encyclopedia citing 150 Roman and 400 Greek scholars, before he was killed in the eruption of the volcano Vesuvius in A.D. 79. Of interest also is De Materia Medica by a-Greek botanist, Pedanios Dioscorides, who had served as a military surgeon in Nero's army. He detailed the properties of some 600 medicinal plants in this text, which remained an authoritative guide for 1,500 years. (Ref. 7) At about the same time a patrician layman, Celsus, tried to summarize all knowledge. Only eight of his many books have survived, the De Medicina, and even these were lost for centuries. (Ref. 8)

As noted above it was in the year 79 that Mt. Vesuvius on the Bay of Naples erupted after 16 years of violent surrounding earthquakes. The cities of Heraculaneum and Pompeii were buried and thousands were killed. At 95 a severe form of malaria appeared in the farming areas surrounding Rome and became endemic there for the next 500 years. At that time ten aqueducts supplied Rome with 250 million gallons of water per day. (Ref. 9, 10)

Throughout this century Roman legions continued to probe the frontiers in Gaul and in the east, gradually extending the empire boundaries. Comments about some of the battles will be found in the paragraphs concerning the regions involved. The population of the Roman Empire at this time was about 54 million, while that of Han China was an estimated 57,600,000. Rome now began to break the Arab monopoly on spices from the east by building ships large enough to sail from the Egyptian Sea to India. The journey was still hazardous and at one time pepper cost $125,000 per 12 ounces. As the secret of the changing monsoon winds in the Indian Ocean was solved, however, pepper became cheaper. Gold was taken to Malabar to be exchanged for pepper. Pliny wrote that Roman ships of this period sailed from the mouth of the Ganges to Ceylon in seven days. The sailing ships were up to 420 feet long with 50 foot beams. One commercial ship had room for 200 sailors, 1,300 passengers and 93,000 bushels of wheat. Wines made from the very prolific Italian vines were now generally preferred to the Greek product. (Ref. 11, 12, 13, 14, 185)1

1 Because of the severe geological instability of the region, however, earthquakes and adjacent volcanoes have subsequently resulted in a sinking of the land and marked shifting of the city of Naples. (Ref. 15)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

In this century there were three to four million people living in the area of modern Germany with three main divisions of the Germanic tribes; The eastern Germans on the Oder and Vistula who were the Visigoths, Ostrogoths, Burgundians and Vandals; the northern Germans of the southern part of Scandinavia, the Baltic islands and Jutland; and the western ones between the Elbe, the North Sea, the Rhine and the Main. The last group preserved their ancient Germanic traits and are the present day Germans, Dutch, Flemings, Anglo-Saxons and, in part, the French.

The early Germanic peoples lived simply, eating horse meat and living in log houses. They were monogamous and held slaves. Super-individual motivations such as patriotism or religious idealism were strangely lacking as these people were highly personalistic. The boundary line between the Roman Empire and the Germanic lands became fairly well established at the Rhine, but battles raged back and forth from time to time. Domitian crossed the Rhine at Mainz to campaign against the Chatti and early victories allowed him to construct a series of forts which were later extended along the central Rhine and then across to the upper Danube. Where this joined an older line of forts on the Danube part of this fortification line became known as "the limes".

AUSTRIA AND HUNGARY

The Emperor Tiberius started as early as A.D. 25 to strengthen the frontier forts of the Danube limes to keep out the northern barbarian hordes. Vindobona (Vienna) was one of three important military bases of the Danube Valley and watch towers were erected all along the river and boats were on constant patrol. At the end of the century there was a completely fortified military road from the Boden See (Lake Constantine) to the Danube limes. The southern portion of what is now Austria and Hungary, along with the western Balkans, was included in the Roman province of Pannonia.

CZECHOSLAVAKIA

As we noted earlier, the Marcomanni and Quadi Germanic tribes had occupied the area of Bohemia and then went south to help the Dacians defeat Domitian, slowing down the Roman advance in this area. The Dacians then turned on the Germans, however, and drove them from the territory.

SWITZERLAND

All under Roman control.

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

All of this area also was Roman controlled. In addition to slaves, there were several groups of free men in Roman Spain - land holding aristocrats, a middle class of merchants, professional people and bureaucrats, manual workers, soldiers and smiths. The Seneca family of Rome had originally come from Cordoba. (Ref. 16)

FRANCE

The Gauls of France progressively reached higher levels of culture and were enfranchised as a province of the Roman Empire. Thomas (Ref. 17) says that about A.D. 100 the Celts invented the metal-hooped, wooden barrel which changed the wine industry greatly since the drink could be stored much better in barrels than in emphorae. He does not say which Celtic group made this progress, but we know that advances in the Gaulic wine industry offered such a challenge to the Italian vineyards that Domitian ordered half the vines in the Rhone region uprooted.

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

The Batavi of the Netherlands were allied with the Romans until A.D. 70 when a chieftain called Civilis revolted, building a line of forts along the southern bank of the Rhine to mark off his own empire. The Frisians stayed in the north in a "no-man's land". (Ref. 18)

BRITISH ISLES

Rome conquered Britain in this century but it was not easy. It took about four decades to completely Romanize England after the A.D. 43 invasion by the army of Claudius, using four Roman legions (out of 29 in the entire empire), each legion containing about 5,600 men. (Ref. 19) Boadicea (or Boudicca), a widowed queen of the Iceni tribe became a famous heroine by leading her tribe against the Romans in East Anglia as she moved against various Romanized towns in A.D. 61 and massacred all, a total of about 70,000 people, including 30,000 to 40,000 in London alone. She was finally defeated in a terrible battle by Suetonius, who had only 10,000 fully armed men against some 80,000 Britons, but these included women and children. Emperor Claudius finally managed to have eleven British kings surrender to him at Colchester.

At this period the Celtic Britons still followed their Druid philosophers in a religion that apparently involved human sacrifices. The Celts had three groups of learned men:

Bards, who composed and preserved poetry and music
Vates, who were priests responsible for carrying out sacrifices to the gods
Druids, who studied natural science and philosophy

 Myles Dillon, who was a professor of Celtic at the University of Dublin, contended that the Druids should be likened to the Brahmins in India, since they carried out their professions including teaching, study, poetry and law in a similar way1 Julius Caesar wrote that the Celtic Druids had knowledge of the stars, the universe, the dimensions of the earth and other related matters. Standing stones in linear or circular groupings serving as astronomical markings are found in all Celtic lands. (Ref. 20)

Perhaps it was in this century that the Picts finally grouped themselves in two dominant tribes; one in the north to be called in the next century "Caledonii" by the Romans, and secondly a southern tribe of the south, later called "Maeatae". The Roman historian, Tacitus, says that in this century the Romans fought a great battle of Mons Grampius2 against heavy legged, tall, red-haired men who fought savagely with long swords and round shields, led by a man called "Calgacus, the Swordsman"3.

Early Celtic Ireland had not writing until the 4th century C.E., and the early history that descended orally through the centuries contains so much myth and legend in the sagas that it is difficult to separate fact from fiction. Apparently in old Celtic fashion, young men of upper class were considered to be men at 16 or 17, in essence "knights", and they had to demonstrate their maturity by raiding enemy territory for cattle and human heads. It is said that the men of Ulster did not keep the skulls of victims as trophies but only their brains, formed into little balls with gypsum. The men liked to sit, eat and drink together in large banquet halls, with the women looking on from a balcony above. Ireland had five main areas, each called a "fifth"- Ulster in the north, Munster in the south, Con- naught in between on the Atlantic side and Mide and Leinster on the east side. (Ref. 23)

Prince Caradoc, called "Caractus" by the Romans, was a Welsh leader who was not defeated until A.D. 50 after he was betrayed by Queen Cartimandus of the Brigantes (Ref. 24) and he was taken prisoner to Rome. In Wales, the Romans put in roads and worked copper and gold mines, but they could not pacify the Welsh who were not actually considered won for Rome until A.D. 78.

SCANDINAVIA

There was a proliferation of various Germanic tribes throughout Norway and Denmark. The Swedish peninsula was dominated by the Suione tribe, while the island of Gotland and other Baltic islands were probably inhabited chiefly by Goths. Snorre Sturlasson, a learned Icelandic scribe, described the origin and ancestral home of the Scandinavian kings as on the border between Europe and Asia along the eastern shores of the Black Sea.

This work has been translated by Holtsmark and Seip4 Snorre gives a detailed, geographical account of the early migration through Europe, passing from Saxony into Denmark, Sweden and Norway, having been chased out of the Caucasus by the ravaging Roman armies and led by the Viking King Odin. Snorre named thirty kings before reaching the generation of Harold Fairhair, of which we shall hear more later in the 9th century.

Rich Stone Age finds show that from prehistoric times the Finnish peninsula has been the meeting place of peoples from Russia, Scandinavia and central Europe. Ancient Lapp and Nordic stocks went north, as Finno-Ugrian speaking peoples came in from the east.

In the century under consideration there were three groups of people: The Karelians, who were a dark, short, brachycephalic people entering from the southeast; the Tavastians, with high cheek-bones coming across the Gulf of Finland; and the Finns, proper, from the southern shore of the Gulf of Finland. (Ref. 26, 27) All of these northern people were probably excellent seamen. A forty-two foot, slender, rowing canoe has been found in Denmark dating to this century.

EASTERN EUROPE

BALTIC AREA

Estonians had already settled on the southern Baltic coast, while Goths inhabited the Baltic islands and perhaps some of the south shore, particularly in the Vistula River basin of Poland. Eastward were the Balts (Letts), who eventually became the Latvians, Lithuanians and the now extinct Old Prussians. The language was an individual, separate Indo-European group entity, neither Germanic nor Slavic. The Roman Tacitus, writing in this century, called the Estonians the "Aesti". (Ref. 28, 29)

RUSSIA

Most of Russia was still sparsely inhabited but in the central, western part were chiefly Slavs and farther east and south there were Huns. In the Caucasus a new Sarmatian people, the Alans, may have been pushed there by the western expansion of the Kushans, whom we have met in Central Asia. These Alans, in turn, pushed the westward lying lazygians entirely out of Russia into the Theiss plain of modern Hungary and Yugoslavia. (Ref. 30)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

3 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

4 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

5 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

6 [171] PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

7 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

9 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

10 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

11 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

12 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

14 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

15 [281] GORE, RICK, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

16 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

17 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

18 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

19 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

20 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

21 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

22 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

23 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

24 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

25 [118] FAY, HOWARD, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

26 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

27 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

28 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

29 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

30 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

1.  As related by Herm (Ref. 21), page 146.

2.  Mountains of central Scotland.

3.  As recorded by Prebble (Ref. 22), page 1.

4.  Taken from Thor Heyerdahl (Ref. 25), page 127.

Europe: A.D. 101 to 200

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Part of the Roman Empire.

GREECE

The home place of the Hellenic world enjoyed an "Indian summer" which was mistaken for a "Golden Age". A thousand city-states lived peacefully together but an impalpable censorship from the Roman overseers was already slowly eliminating intellectual and artistic vitality. At the end of the century the Germanic Costobii raided down through Greece to within 14 miles of Athens. (Ref. 1)

UPPER BALKANS

Almost all of the present day Balkans belonged to the Roman Empire, including Dacia or Romania, Moesia or Bulgaria,Thracia and Dalmatia. The very northern portions of Romania and Bulgaria may have been outside the Roman jurisdiction, in the large area known then as Sarmatia and extending over into Russia on the north shore of the Black Sea. In the upper Balkan area, however, only Romania can be said to have been truly Latinized.

ITALY

The first half of the century, under Emperors Trajan and Hadrian and their immediate successors, was one of the great periods of the empire, with general prosperity and with limited exceptions, such as the Romano-Jewish Wars and Armenian squabbles, a period of peace. The Mediterranean world had a fullness of life not seen before or since. The Greek spirit ruled the mind and the East, while the Roman spirit ruled the state and the West. Under Trajan the empire reached its greatest geographical extent, as indicated on the map and in the summary of the empire at A.D. 117 to follow.

AFRICA. All of Egypt and the north African coast, including Mauretania, Syrtica and Marmarica.
THE NEAR EAST. A portion of Arabia, all of the eastern Mediterranean coast, all of Syria, Iraq, Media in Persia, Asia Minor, including Bithynia, Pontus and Cappadocia, Cilicia, Lycaonia, Gallatia and Armenia.
EUROPE
SOUTHERN EUROPE. Greece and most of the Balkan area, including Dacia (Romania), Moesia (Bulgaria), Thracia and Dalmatia (southern Bulgaria, European Turkey, Yugoslavia and Croatia), and all of Italy and Sicily.
B. CENTRAL EUROPE. The Austrian-Hungary area, known then as Pannonia, Noricum and Baetia, and those parts of present day Germany which lie west of the Rhine and south of the Danube, including Bavaria, Switzerland and the parts of Germany about the Black Forest.
NOTE: Insert Map 29. THE ROMAN EMPIRE AT THE DEATH OF TRAJAN A.D.
WESTERN EUROPE. Hispania (Spain and Portugal), Brittanica (England and Wales), Gallia and Belgica, etc.

The empire was surrounded by Germania, Sarmatia, Parthia and the remainder of Arabia.

A few words about the emperors themselves seems indicated. Trajan was the first emperor to have been born outside Italy, coming from a Roman colonial family living in Spain. He lived simply and was a tireless administrator who completed extensive public works including roads, buildings, bridges and aqueducts. He awarded 5,000 scholarships to needy students and he financed secondary schools and pensions for teachers. Romania was conquered because it was on the road to Byzantium at the Bosporus. When his armies reached the Indian Ocean and Trajan went home, revolts spread and his nephew, Hadrian, in command in Syria, withdrew to the Euphrates. Tacitus did his historical writing during this reign.

Hadrian (117 - 138) was the most brilliant of the Roman emperors and his reign the most prosperous. Under him the Pantheon, which had previously burned, was reconstructed.

Later in the century (A.D. 161) Marcus Aurelius came to power and brought thousands of Germans into the empire, both as settlers and as soldiers. The ultimate effect was that the "barbarians" gradually began to dominate Rome. Marcus was one of the greatest exponents of the Stoic philosophy and a good public servant and administrator. It was during his administration that a great plague was apparently brought back by armies from the East. Although Rome had epidemics as far back as 387 B.C. the one of A.D. 165 was the worst. The disease, perhaps small-pox, remained epidemic in various cities for fifteen years and in some areas 25 to 35% of the people died. The population of all Mediterranean lands subsequently decreased overall for the next 500 years. Following Marcus' death, Rome began to visibly decay. At the last of the century the barbarian tribes began to attack again in various parts of the empire, with the Chatti, Chauci and Lombards raiding Italy from Germany and other Germanic tribes raiding through the Balkans into Greece. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

Overall there were some 54,000 miles of Roman roads, making a network for communications throughout the empire. The middle of each road was raised and covered with gravel to allow drainage. There were post stations every 10 to 12 miles on main roads and each station had horses, veterinarians, surgeons, cartwrights, carriages and wagons. In the outer empire donkeys and camels were available. Still, the bulk of internal trade went by water. (Ref.6)

On the medical scene, Galen, born in Pergamum, Asia Minor practiced medicine in Rome and was physician to Emperor Marcus. He dissected the Barbary Ape and left some good anatomical and physiological knowledge for posterity. His works were considered as an unimpeachable authority for nearly 1,500 years even though much was in error.

Galen used an old Asia Minor combination of medicinals called "theriac"(FOREIGN) (related to Greek word for "wild beast") and he increased the number of ingredients to over 70. This also persisted as a treatment well into the Middle Ages, but at least some of its popularity may have been due to the presence of opium among its ingredients. Other 2nd century contributors to medicine included Soranus, writing especially on diseases of women, and Rufus, also from Ephesus, who made important anatomical observations while in Rome particularly about the eye and brain. Celsus, a Roman, wrote De Medicina which actually codified Greek medicine of the previous century. (Ref. 7)1

1 (Ref. 8)

CENTRAL EUROPE

Northern Germany seethed with a multitude of Germanic tribes. Bordering on the Baltic were the Gepids and farther west the Goths, while just south of them were the Burgundians, bordered on the east by the encroaching Slavs. On the North Sea coast were Frisians, then Sennones, Hermanduri, Marcomanni and Quadi, in turn going east. The last two named tribes were actually in the region of Bohemia. An Iranian tribe, a branch of the Sarmatians, now occupied most of present day Hungary. The Romans had their farthest advance against the Germanic tribes in A.D. 110, under Trajan, when they fortified boundaries from Holland down the Rhine to near Mainz and then east to near Frank-on-Main, and then down the Danube. All areas south of this line were dominated by the Romans for four centuries, and were eventually filled with cities and roads. After Christianity dominated the area, the few regions of Germany and Austria below the above mentioned line later remained Catholic, while north of this line civilization developed much slower and Christianity appeared much later and then of the Arian variety from the East. These northern areas are now essentially Protestant. To return to the 2nd century, however, the Franks, as a loose confederacy of Germanic tribes, developed up to A.D. 200 between the Weser and the Rhine. (Ref. 9, 10)

Emperor Marcus died at Vindobona (Vienna) in A.D. 180 after 8 winters of campaigns on the frozen banks of the Danube fighting against the Marcomanni and Quadi. They were finally destroyed as kingdoms in A.D. 165 about the time that the Lombards (also Longobards) began their first raids down into Roman territory and they never were quite conquered by the Romans.

WESTERN EUROPE

In Spain, although Romans built roads for their legionnaires, it was still far cheaper to carry wheat by ship from Syria to Andalusia than to carry it overland from south to north Spain. The south of this country was the most prosperous, growing wheat, grapes and olives. At the end of the century Spain was invaded by Moors from northern Africa.

Gaul (France) was ruled completely by the Romans but again at the end of the century there were rumblings of Germanic tribes pushing against the eastern barriers into Gaul. (Ref. 11, 12)

All of western Europe, including England and Wales, enjoyed an era of law and order and peace under Roman rule. The Hadrianic frontier was generally maintained in Britain by the legions, modified only by the conquest of southern Scotland in A.D. 142. The complete annexation of Scotland was attempted from time to time but always failed because the legions could not supply themselves in such a sparsely populated country. In addition the Picts had become a force to be reckoned with. In the last few years of their independence they had finally united under the stimulation of savage battles against the Scots and Norsemen. Emperor Hadrian, feeling that Caledonia was not worth the potential loss of men if it was to be conquered, built his great wall (A.D. 122) 70 miles from sea to sea, with a causeway of stone, forts, camps and signal towers, from the Solway firth to the northeast. Because of constant barbarian attacks on the wall, however, the Romans later advanced their frontier and built still another wall, Antoninus' (A.D. 140), between the Forth and the Clyde. This one was 39 miles long and had 20 forts. (Ref. 13) The Roman port of Dover, protected by two great lighthouses, helped keep immense trade going to from England. Vessels bringing jars of wine, oil and fish-paste came from Spain and Italy, while tableware was brought from Gaul. (Ref. 14, 15, 16, 17)

In Ireland the ruler of Connacht, Conn, formed a large kingdom about A.D. 150 but neither he nor his successors could manage to unify the entire country.

SCANDINAVIA

The Scandinavian tribes had considerable trade with the Roman world, chiefly through the Marcommanic kingdom in Bohemia and after the annihilation of the latter late in the century, the quality and quantity of goods imported into the north declined considerably. In A.D. 150 Ptolemy, the Egyptian scientist wrote about several far northern tribes, including the Goestoi (also Gautor and Geatas) and the Chaideinoi, who were probably the Norwegian Heidnir. (Ref. 18)

EASTERN EUROPE

An older name for the Balts was Aistrians, taken from Aestiorum gentes, mentioned by Tacitus (A.D. 98). Sometime near this 2nd century these Balts separated into Lithuanians, Letts (Latvians), Old Prussians, Curonians, Semigallions and Selonians. The east Ger- man Goths who had been building up a population pressure along the Baltic for two or more centuries particularly about the mouth of the Vistula, about this time moved south to the Carpathians and the Black Sea, dominating all the people with whom they came in contact. Once inside Russia these people, then called "Ostrogoths" (East Goths), soon formed a kingdom of their own and rapidly began to spread still farther along the river systems. Along the Black Sea they abutted against the Iranian Roxolani (also Rhoxolani) branch of the Samartians, who were the successors to the Scythians in this area. (Ref. 19, 20, 21)

The territory between the Black and Caspian Seas was occupied chiefly by the Irania Alans, closely related to the Samartians. Just south of these Alans the old Caucasian kingdom of Iberia remained as a Roman protectorate, although those ancient people were only nominally subservient to Rome. Otherwise, in more central Russia, the Slavic people continued to live and expand unobtrusively, while in the far north the Finns-Lapps continued their sparse existence. (Ref. 22)

1 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

2 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

3 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

4 [185] ROMAN MEDICINE, in Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, 3: No. 8, Aug. 1959.

5 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

8 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

9 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

12 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

13 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

14 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

15 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

16 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

17 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

18 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

19 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

21 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

22 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

Europe: A.D. 201 to 300

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS |GREECE | UPPER BALKANS

This entire area was an integral part of the Roman Empire and was administered in three parts: The Dacian diocese, comprised of eastern Yugoslavia, western Bulgaria, Moesia Superior, Dacia and some smaller areas; the Macedonian diocese consisting chiefly of Greece; and the Thracian diocese, which was made up of eastern Bulgaria and the European part of Turkey, which in turn, included Lower Moesia, Scythia, Thrace, etc. Of these only Dacia used the Latin language, while the others all spoke Greek. The Goths arrived in the Black Sea area by A.D. 214 and soon occupied all the region west of this sea, splitting into two divisions, to be known as Ostrogoths (East Goths) and Visigoths (West Goths). They battled the Romans in this area throughout the century and the Roman Emperor Decius was slain by them in Dacia as the Romans withdrew in A.D. 275 to safety south of the Danube. Many native Dacians took to the hills with their Latin language, to reappear centuries later as ancestors of the modern Romanians. Gallus, a former legate of Moesia (chiefly the area of Bulgaria), became emperor of Rome in 251. In 268 Claudius II (Gothicus) became the first of a series of emperors from Illyria. They were a capable group and prepared the way for Diocletian. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

ITALY

Although already diminished by some severe pestilence, the population of Rome at the beginning of this 3rd century was at least one million. An epidemic hit again between 251 and 266, with 5,000 dying each day at its peak in Rome and with the rural populations also heavily affected. The disease may have been either measles and/or smallpox. Civil disorders and barbarian invasions simply added to the problem. Vacancies within the legions on the Roman frontiers, caused by deaths from disease and mutinies, resulted in invitations to the barbarians to both enter the legions and settle the lands. Rapid die-off around the entire Mediterranean hampered commerce and diminished the flow of cash to the imperial treasury and this resulted in no pay for the soldiers, thus further mutinies, military uprisings and civil wars in outlying areas. (Ref. 4) Armies in different provinces tried to set up their own commanders as emperors (the "Thirty Tyrants"), but this situation was eliminated between 268 and 284. Of course almost constant war with the powerful Persians in the east did not help and a succession of emperors of anarchy came and went, usually by murders. The resources of the rich were consumed by war and by the government. The menial work of Rome was performed by about 400,000 slaves, with even middle class citizens owning about 8 and the rich from 500 to 1,000. (Ref. 5)

The eastern part of the empire was momentarily saved in name, if not in truth, by Odenathus and Zenobia, as we have reported in the section on THE NEAR EAST. Gaul had revolted and assumed its own autonomy under first Postumus and then Tetricus. Aurel- ian, emperor from 270 to 275, however, temporarily restored Gaul, Spain and Britain to the fold and built the existing walls of Rome as a protection against future incursions by barbarians. To keep the expanding poor of Rome reasonably happy, Aurelian added free pork-fat and wine to the "Annona", as well as giving bread instead of just grain. In order to pay troops, the government gradually debased the silver currency and along with devaluation this culminated in rapid inflation. Increasingly slaves were used in all capacities, even in positions of dependent management of farms, shops, ships and banks. (Ref. 6)

The whole Roman realm had a short period of peace under one of the Balkan emperors, Probus, until his troops murdered him in 282. Then Diocles, or Diocletian, a man of genius and statesmanship became emperor and reorganized the empire. A native Illyrian and Dalmation soldier, he abandoned Rome and made his headquarters at Nicomedia, a few miles south of Byzantium in Asia Minor. He delegated control of the western half of the empire to his general, Maximian, as co-ruler in the city of Ravenna, Italy, and then made extensive political reforms including the division of the empire into four major prefectures and then forming further subdivisions as dioceses and finally provinces. (Ref. 7) At that time the empire was said to have 435,000 men under arms, chiefly infantry. Finally Diocletian, falling prey to the common curse of ancient men of power, claimed that he was the earthly embodiment of Jupiter, while Maximian consented to be Hercules. This identification of god and king meant the final failure of republican institutions of antiquity and a reversion to the forms and theories of Achaemenid and Egyptian courts. From this orientalized monarch came the structure and form of Byzantine and the European kingdoms until the time of the French Revolution. All that was needed now was to ally the oriental monarch in his oriental capital with an oriental faith. Byzantinism began with Diocletian. (Ref. 8, 9)

CENTRAL EUROPE

As the Germanic tribes migrated westward, behind them the Slavs began to cross the Elbe and filter into modern Bohemia, Moravia and parts of eastern Germany. The Marcomanni, who were already in this area, raided westward and southward, even into Italy itself. The Frankish tribes invaded across the Rhine and along with the Alemanni also attacked directly into Italy. In battles from A.D. 270 to 275 the Emperor Aurelian finally stopped these invasions and held the Germanic tribes essentially at the Rhine once again. In the Pannonian diocese, which included most of Austria, Hungary and the western edge of Yugoslavia, the Asding branch of the Vandals had replaced the Iazygians as the dominant element in the southern portion, while the Gepids (related to the Goths) occupied the north. (Ref. 10, 11)

WESTERN EUROPE

Spain became a large scale producer of wine, olive oil and other products, including a delicious fish-paste. Some insurrections in this country, as in other parts of the empire, were eventually put down by Aurelian. Revolt leaders Postumus and Tetricus in Gaul were also eventually defeated. In Belgium the Franks swept the Gaulic Celts into the south, giving rise to the original language barrier with the northern Germanic tongue dominant at that time. In England, late in the century the pirates were so numerous around the coasts that Carausius, who happened to be a Belgian sailor, was assigned by the Roman authorities to clear the North Sea and the channel of these brigands. He did so, using mercenaries of Germanic and Frankish origin. But he made enemies in Rome and was murdered in A.D. 293 by his finance officer, Allectus, who then kept England independent of Roman control for three years, until Constantius Chlorus re-conquered the area using a new navy and fresh troops. (Ref. 12, 13, 14, 15)

SCANDINAVIA

In this area the most significant change from recent centuries was the replacement of all Lapps and Finns in Denmark by Germanic tribes by A.D. 250. Included in the latter group were the definitive Danes. Roman coins of the 3rd century have been found on Iceland, presumably taken there by the Roman Emperor Constans who sailed in pursuit of Celtic pirates who had raided Wales and then led their pursuer to an arctic island.

(Ref. 16, 17)

EASTERN EUROPE

Traveling from north to south in this region, we would find Finns in the sparsely settled far north, but south of them going from west to east along the Baltic, we would find first the Balts, then a large area of Slavs and finally, just north of the Black Sea, various Iranian tribes, including the Roxolani and Alans. By A.D. 300 the Ostrogoths had expanded eastward across the Ukraine to dominate the Roxolani, but otherwise there was not much change throughout this century with the possible exception that there may have been some Turkish-speaking Hunnish people already drifting into this area. (Ref. 18, 19)

1 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

2 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

3 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

4 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

8 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

9 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

10 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

11 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

14 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

15 [24] CERRUTE, JAMES, "Belgium, One Nation Divisible", National Geographic 155:314, March, 1979.

16 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

17 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

18 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

19 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

Europe: A.D. 301 to 400

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

At the end of the century Crete and most of the Cyclades passed from Roman to Byzantine control. (Ref. 1)

GREECE

Greece remained an integral part of the Byzantine Empire and in this period was intimately connected with the activities of the upper Balkans. After the Visigoths were victorious at Adrianople in 378 they subsequently tried to settle in Greece (396-399) but after the Athenians paid them a large ransom, they wandered back north and west toward Italy.

UPPER BALKANS (Please also see RUSSIA and ASIA MINOR, this chapter)

There was much migratory activity and inter-tribe fighting in the Balkan area. The Ostrogoths had suffered a military defeat on the Dniepner by the Huns and as they retreated westward they in turn pushed the Visigoths ahead of them. One group of the latter, under Athanaric, went on into Pannonia (Hungary) while a second group under Fritigens appeared on the lower Danube and asked Emperor Valen's permission to enter Dacia. The request was granted but famine in 377 resulted in the Goths raiding south.

Joined by some Ostrogoths, some federati1, renegrades and later even some Huns and Alani, they crossed the Danube in 378, killed Valens and annihilated two-thirds of his troops. The Goths then ravaged the Balkans from end to end. Separate peace treaties with various Gothic groups were forged between 380 and 381 and many other Goths individually or in groups eventually joined Roman forces. The original Visigothic troops had been thinned by epidemics and desertions. In 384 or 385 Huns crossed the frozen Danube and raided down the west shore of the Black Sea and in 386 struck both east and west of the Goths' area on the Danube. The Ostrogoths defied their Hun overlords, striking violently in great numbers from the east, but even so, by 392 the Huns were raiding through the Balkans, not under a single king, but as individual tribes.

At the end of the century there were three powerful groups prowling through the Balkans. We have mentioned in an earlier paragraph that as the dead Theodocius' troops returned from Italy they raided through this area up to the walls of Constantinople. The Visigoths, after raiding Greece went to Epirus on the Adriatic and renewed an alliance with the eastern Roman government, and as just noted above, the Huns were foraging into the area from the east. (Ref. 2, 3)

Although a proto-Germanic tongue was probably spoken simultaneously with Sanskrit, early Greek and other early languages, the Gothic translation of the Bible by Bishop Ulfilas in this century is the earliest satisfactory record of a Germanic language. Having been taken to Constantinople in his younger years as a hostage, he mastered Latin and Greek, invented a special alphabet on the Greek pattern and returned to his Visigothic people on the lower Danube preaching the Arian creed which then spread throughout the Germanic tribes. His Bible is virtually the only source of knowledge of the original Gothic language which sired all the Germanic tongues, including Runic. (Ref. 4)

ITALY

In the western Roman Empire there was a complex picture of recovery and decline, literary activity and sterility, political pomp and military decay. Gaul's 20,000,000 people prospered and threatened Italian leadership in every field. There were 6,000,000 Italians while in the empire there were another 44,000,000 Greek-speaking orientals and Rome, itself, was an oriental city with a great middle class now weakened by economic decline and rising taxes. Among both pagans and Christians alike there was an immorality rarely known in history. Until the last third of the century the western emperors were military men who kept strong holds chief ly through their armies. These included Julian, who as a Caesar, had fought the Alamanni and Franks in 355 and then marched against Emperor Constantius of the East, to become emperor overall in 360. He was succeded almost immediately in the west by Valentinian I and then by Gratian (367-383), a bookish adolescent who lost control and the barbarians soon crashed through the borders. Initially Gratian had served as co-emperor with his father Valentinian but upon the death of the latter he was joined by his half-brother, Valentian II.

Magnus Maximus usurped the emperor's army and murdered Gartian in 383 and then ruled the western empire with the child emperor Valentian assisted by the boy's mother, Justina, and a pagan general Bauto, a Frank. In 387 Maximus' army was needed to repel barbarian invaders from Panonnia and he took the opportunity to also swoop down and take Italy itself, running Valentian II and his mother to the East. This was the time when the eastern Emperor Theodosius marched with an eastern army chiefly of Gothic mercenaries, and defeated and killed Maximus in 388. Arbogast, a German and pagan was then the chief minister to the restored Valentinian II, but conflict soon developed and the emperor was killed or committed suicide. Thus, in 392 Flavious Eugenius, a nominal Christian, but having pagan sympathies, became emperor. He also was defeated in northern Italy by Theodosius in 394 and paganism as a political force almost disappeared. The son of Theodocius, the child Honorius, was set up to rule under the administration of Stilicho, the son of a German officer and husband of Theodocius' niece.

All historians are pretty well agreed on a certain sequence of events which led to the fall of the western Roman Empire, this including the western movement of the Huns, who in turn, put great pressure on the Germanic tribes, who in turn, then invaded the empire which was already decaying from its own inadequacies and problems. But each historian may have his own concept of the relative importance of each of these factors in the down- fall. There are those who think that the "barbarian" advance was the major factor, and there is no doubt that the Germans had already heavily infiltrated the ranks of the Roman army, particularly the cavalry units and the lesser officialdom. Furthermore, the German soldier had a better sword, made of better steel. Richard Lewinsohn (Ref. 5) insists that the horse brought the collapse of the empire. Cavalry had always been a neglected part of the Roman army and in Rome, the horse was more a symbol of affluence than of real power. The mounted troops of the barbarians cut the Roman legions to pieces and cavalrymen became the conquerors and for 1,000 years retained mastery over Europe.

Others were more concerned with the internal problems of Rome, itself. Throughout its history, the imperial frontiers were closely aligned with the borders of the wheat growing regions of the classical world and now much of this wheat growing area was otherwise occupied. Egyptian wheat now went to Constantinople; southern Italian agriculture was declining and losing out to African and Spanish competition, so that the west was caught in the spiral of dwindling revenue and increasing exactions. Inflation was a tremendous factor. Even in A.D. 302 Diocletian had inflicted the death penalty for any infringement of fixed prices which he had established in an attempt to present further inflation. (Ref. 6) Even so, a measure of wheat for which the Romans had paid six drachma in Egypt in the first century C.E. cost two million shortly after A.D. 344. This resulted in a subsequent drift back to a barter economy of a thousand years earlier and helped to ruin not only international trade but the western empire as well. About A.D. 350 there were 120,000 people who received six half-pound loaves of bread free, daily, from the government.

By this time Rome had 12 aqueducts, largely underground, feeding 352 fountains. One tunnel, taking water from Lake Fucino in the Apennines, was 3 1/2 miles long. As the empire fell, however, there were no longer slaves to care for this system and the fountains became dry. (Ref. 7) Perhaps scarcity of both food and water were very important in the decline of Rome' There is still another emphasis by Kenneth Clark (Ref. 8) - "So if one asks why the civilization of Greece and Rome collapsed, the real answer is that it was exhausted." "The late antique world was full of meaningless rituals, mystery religions that destroyed self confidence. And then exhaustion, the feeling of hopelessness which can overtake people even with a high degree of material prosperity.”2

Of course the Greek-speaking eastern realm survived to become the- Empire of Byzantium. Part of the success of this eastern part was due to its urbanization and the West's failure to urbanize had made that area less easy to tax and more expensive to administer. Failing to collect taxes, the military could not be paid. Furthermore, the government's price-fixing had made many professions profitless and its attempts to avoid the economic consequences of such by making the practice of such professions obligatory and liability hereditary must have created many white-collar outlaws. We have already mentioned that a sizeable portion of the masses were slaves3 who had a low reproduction rate and there was a high death rate in the urban people from pestilence. A plague which may have been anthrax reduced the empire's population by 5% early in the century. Caught in the spiral of dwindling revenue and increasingly demanding exactions and inflation, the West was doomed. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16)

By the end of this century, although written Latin had not changed its appearance, spoken Latin had developed a new sound pattern. Stressed vowels were drawled; unstressed vowels were dulled, weakened and often dropped. As the great civilization which had been unified by the Latin language collapsed, what Freeman Dyson (Ref. 18) calls a "clade" of new Latin-derived languages - French, Spanish, Italian, Portuguese, Romanian and a few lesser ones, grew and developed in relatively rapid fashion. At most, 20 generations separate unified Roman Europe from the Europe of well-established local languages. (Ref. 19, 20)

CENTRAL EUROPE

This century saw the beginning of "Die Volkerwanderungen", meaning "peoples' migrations". The Alemans were on the upper Rhine while the Angles, Saxons, Jutes and Frisians were along the North Sea. The Vandals, related to the Goths, were on the upper reaches of the Oder River moving (or perhaps being pushed by Goths) from the area of modern Prussia and possibly Denmark, south to the Danube in the area of Pannonia, a portion of modern Hungary. The Lombards lived between the Oder and Vistula in modern Poland and also on the lower Elbe in Germany. The Burgundians drifted westward to the Main River and the Thuringians held their ancient, central position in Bavaria and northward. All these tribes for the most part were antagonistic to each other.

In the early 370s Ostrogoths, led by Athanaric, migrated from the Balkans into Pannonia and after the Fritigen led Ostrogoths had their great victory at Adrianople, they also plundered Pannonia. The Huns were following closely and they set up camps in Pannonia also by 378, enslaving the Gepids (related to the Goths) in the process. The Huns with their flocks now occupied pasture land extending from the Caspian Sea to Hungary. In 383 Juthungi Germans invaded Austria, perhaps with permission of Maximus, but in 384 Hunnic horsemen rode through them on their way to Gaul. General Bauto, of the Roman forces, persuaded the Huns to attack the Germans and they obligingly crushed them in one great sweep before continuing on toward Gaul. Bauto then apparently got nervous about their advance and bought off the Huns with gold and they retreated to their base in Hungary. Thereafter individual Hun tribes pillaged Hungary at will. By 396 a group of Visigoths, headed by Alaric, had settled in Illyrium, the western part of present day Yugoslavia. (Ref. 21, 22, 23) In Bohemia the Germanic tribes were slowly being pushed west throughout all these early Christian centuries by the Slavs, moving in from Russia. Switzerland remained quiet under the Roman yoke.

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

The Iberian Peninsula remained under Roman rule, but somewhat restlessly and occasionally the emperor had to send out expeditionary forces to put down uprisings of rebellious peasants. The Catholic church was recognized to be on equal footing with other religions, but there were many local heresies. By the end of the century there were about 9,000,000 people in this area. (Ref. 24, 25)

FRANCE AND NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

The Gauls of France now numbered about 20,000,000 and had reached a high level of civilization and scarcely rated the title of "barbarian" at this time, although many have labeled them as such. They, in turn, were now having pressure put upon them by new barbarians of the Teutonic variety. A competent general, Emperor Julian, had defeated the last Franco-Alemannic invasion of France, although he allowed some of the Franks to settle in Belgium, keeping their tribal organization while bowing to Rome (A.D. 358). The term "foederatii"(FOREIGN) was used to describe such tribes. By the end of the century the Salic Franks expanded out of Belgium, moving to the southwest and occupying the region between the Meuse, the ocean and the Somme. The origin of our word "enfranchised" is from this ancient tribal name of Frank, which meant "free". The Frisians, who were the main power on the North Sea, were friendly to the Romans through this period. (Ref. 26)1

1 Using the water in the Massif Central of the area, they used overshot, vertical water mills, using water channeled into bucket-like containers built into the circumference of wheels 2.2 meters in diameter, with the weight of that water turning the wheel. Sixteen wheels used in pairs on eight terraces produced a total of about 8 Horse Power for the adjacent flour factory, which in turn, produced enough flour for Arles, with a population of 80,000. (Ref. 27)

BRITISH ISLES

Of all western Europe only Ireland and Pictish Scotland remained completely free of the Roman yoke. The population of Romanized Britain was 1,000,000 or more, with little numerical change since the time of Cassivellaunus. The British lived better as Roman citizens, however, than ever again until about 1900. The wealthy had central heat and warm baths, both of which were nearly absent again in Britain from A.D. 400 to 1900. In this 4th century cities had begun to decline, but country villas still flourished, as did the Roman capital of London. There was no new science, no new thrust of power until A.D. 367 when Picts, Scots, Franks and Saxons, as the great "barbarian conspiracy" joined in a maritime raid on southern England, at about the same time as other Picts at- tacked and flanked Hadrian's wall in north England. Finally Count Theodosius defeated the raiders, using large detachments of Germanic mercenaries, as well as modifying both coastal and inland defenses. Archeological findings now indicate that as the Germanic mercenaries were brought in, there were already separate Saxon forces, perhaps living among the locals as a sort of peasant militia, and thus gradually the defense of Britain began to rely upon these foreigners. At the end of the century, Ninian, a British chieftain's son, went to Rome and was made a bishop, after 15 years of study. (Ref. 28, 29, 30, 31) In Ireland, after 700 years of Belgic and other Brythonic Celtic migrations the Brythonic kingdom of Tara (Mide) was now supreme, but by the end of the century all the Irish had relapsed to the older Gaelic dialect. It was at this time, probably, that the Irish started to use the primitive Ogam alphabet of lines and dashes. Herm (Ref. 32) says that these Irish invented Ogam, but others seem to have demonstrated that it was in use in Spain and Portugal many centuries previously. (Ref. 33, 34)

SCANDINAVIA

Archeologists have called the first four centuries of the Christian era in Scandinavia the "Roman Iron Age" even though no Romans appeared in the north. The people were chiefly agriculturalists or seamen, illiterate and pagan but they already had extensive trade with Romans and the Mediterranean, exchanging furs, skins, robes of seal-skin, dairy produce and cattle for silks, gold, wine, jewelry, glass bowls, etc. They lived in large halls or houses, raised summer wheat, barley and rye. Their boats were of all sizes up to 75 feet long and they were propelled by oars. The areas of Swedes, Norse, Danes, Jutes and Angles were already quite well delineated. (Ref. 35, 36)

The Gothic language was well established and writing began to appear in the system of runes, with 24 clumsy characters brought from the continent and changed by edging to adapt the characters to wood. (See also next chapter, please). After Constantinople became the Roman capital, Denmark found her trade in the south had been transferred eastward to the Baltic and via Russian rivers on to the south. Islands in the Baltic, such as Gotland and Bornholm, thus became trading stations en route and at the same time worth plundering. (Ref. 37)2

2 The largest piece of amber sent to Rome weighed 13 pounds. Even a few Latin words found their way into the Scandinavian tongues. One was leather, there were several meaning "trader" and "caupo", which was the ultimate source of Kobenhavn and Linkoping. Before the Roman Iron Age the chief method of disposal of the dead was cremation, but gradually this changed in some areas to inhumation.  In this 4th century villages became larger, as well as the individual houses. In one 500 square kilometer area of north Jutland there were at least 46 settlements. Forests were reduced as wood was used for buildings and fuel. It was a period of remarkable expansion in Denmark as well as in southwest Norway, southern Sweden and Gotland. In Denmark, eastern Sjaelland seems to have become an important center of power-a chiefdom. (Ref. 38)

EASTERN EUROPE

BALTIC AREA

We have just mentioned the new importance of the Baltic islands in trade between Scandinavia and the Byzantine Empire. On the south shore of the Baltic, the Germanic tribes migrated and changed positions. For example, the Lombards were partially in eastern Germany and partially in Poland, but late in the century almost the entire area was at least governed by the Ostrogoths under their great leader, King Ermanarich, who extended his realm back from the Black Sea to the Baltic, largely at the expense of the Slavs, some of whom fled northward among the Finns and preserved their freedom. (Ref. 39)

RUSSIA

In the far north some Finns remained with a large contingent of Slavs crowding northward in the western portion. Visigoths (Tervingi) and Ostrogoths (Greutringi) lived on both sides of the Dniestr. The latter were ruled by King Ermanarich in an organized group while the Visigoths had a looser political situation and an alliance with Rome, after 332. Large numbers of these Goths had already been won over to Arian Christianity by the heretical missionary, Ulfilas. The Don River originally separated the Ostrogoths from the Iranian Alans to the east, but sometime in the early part of the century these Alans attacked the Ostrogoths, starting their collapse as a political entity. From the east the Huns had advanced into Russia north and west of the Caspian Sea, crossing the Don and overcoming many of the Alans and attacking the almost civilized Ostrogoths in the Ukraine. Along with many of the Alans, part of the Ostrogoths joined the Huns while others fled west and south to join their cousins, the Visigoths. The latter, under Athanaric, fought the Huns on the right bank of the Dniestr but could not hold and retreated west, ten thousand strong, encamping eventually just north of the Danube. The Huns now ruled a large area of south Russia and stood at the mouth of the Danube, about A.D. 370. A fragile Hunno-Alanic alliance lasted about 30 years. Judging from the names of some of the tribes overrun by the Huns at the northeastern shore of the Black Sea, other Turkish tribes must already have been in this area and some of these may also have joined the Hun hordes as they went west4. (Ref. 40, 41)

In the Caucasus region Lazilia and Iberia were two kingdoms of the ancient Georgians which had been pretty well Christianized under Roman suzerainty but the more primitive Abasgians, also of Georgian stock, remained heathen and outside Roman jurisdiction. As detailed on pages 358 and 369 the Huns went through the Caucasus on raids to Persia and Mesopotamia and on their return they may have brought some two-humped, Bactrian camels with them to the Ukraine. (Ref. 42, 43, 44)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

3 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

4 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

5 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

9 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

10 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

11 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

12 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

14 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

16 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

17 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

18 [56] DYSON, FREEMAN, Disturbing the Universe. (Harper and Row, N.Y., 1979).

19 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

20 [56] DYSON, FREEMAN, Disturbing the Universe. (Harper and Row, N.Y., 1979).

21 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

22 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

23 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

24 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

25 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

26 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

27 [307] FLEMING, STUART, "Gallic Water Power: The mills of Barbegal", Archaeology 36, No.6: 68, Nov./Dec. 1983.

28 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

29 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

30 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

31 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

32 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

33 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

34 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

35 [237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

36 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

37 [237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

38 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

39 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

40 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

41 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

42 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

43 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

44 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

1.  Goth mercenaries previously with imperial units

2.  Quotations from Clark (Ref. 9), page 4

3.  Christian emperors still ordered the execution by crucifixion or burning of slaves who brought accusations against their masters, without trial. (Ref. 17)

4.  For comments concerning the original group of Huns, see page 331, and for detailed information concerning their lives and characteristics, see the section on HUNGARY, 5th century C.E.

Europe: A.D. 401 to 500

EUROPE

This is usually considered the beginning of the European Middle Ages and it was a period of warming climatic change. (Ref. 1) The towns of the Roman Empire had been declining even before the arrival of the "barbarians", but now, with the end of the empire, the West truly lost its urban framework. (Ref. 2)

SOUTHERN EUROPE (See also TURKEY and CENTRAL EUROPE)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Most of these islands were under Byzantine control and both science and literature flourished, particularly on Rhodes, in these early Christian centuries. (Ref. 3)

GREECE

Greece was submerged in the affairs of Constantinople. The only unique feature was a raid on the coastline by Vandals from their bases in Africa at the end of the century.

UPPER BALKANS

In the early part of the century the area of present day Yugoslavia was part of the Visigoth kingdom and after the Goths were defeated while invading Italy in 402 and 403 by Stilicho, they retired again to that region. In this same area and in northern present day Albania the last real western Roman Emperor lived from 476 to 480, isolated in the old Roman province of Dalmatia. Meanwhile in the western part of the upper Balkans, Slavic tribes first settled in what is now Bulgaria with the Bulgars (probably a mixture of Huns and other nomads) right behind them. The Black Huns, probably encouraged by the warming European climate which made fine pasture land for their horses, raided through- out the Balkans and ruined the area for some three centuries to follow. They had arrived about A.D. 400 under their ruler, Uldin, who proceeded to lead them into Thrace on raids in the winter of 404-405. This happened again in 408, 422 and several times in the 430s. In 441 Illyrium was the target. Resumption of Balkan raids in 442 brought big tribute concessions from the Byzantine emperor, Theodosius. When he later reneged on the payments Attilla himself led a great Hunnic invasion of Thrace in 447 and it cost the emperor still more in gold payments. (See TURKEY, above)

Ahead of the Huns had come Slavic peoples, some from the so-called eastern Slav groups, but chief ly from the western Slav tribes and these settled to become the ancestors of the Serbs, Croats, Slovenes and Macedonians. The Huns, themselves, had actually settled in Hungary, but made their periodic raids back into the Balkans as noted. During their various invasions and raids, many of the Hun soldiers took native women as wives, thus putting Asiatic blood from the Black Sea to Bavaria. After A.D. 455 there were only two pockets of Huns remaining in the Balkans - one in a portion of modern Bulgaria along the west shore of the Black Sea and the second in Dacia, -somewhat west of the first group. In 465 these Huns attacked the Goths who were in Pannonia, but they were defeated. A second Gothic-Hunnic War developed south of the Danube in 465. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

ITALY (Please also see TURKEY, THE BALKANS, and CENTRAL EUROPE)

At the beginning of the century the weak Roman Emperor Honorius put the Vandal, Stilicho, in command of the army of the West and he was immediately put to test by invading Alans and Visigoths. Stilicho defeated them using Vandals and even some Alanic mercenaries in two great battles in 402. There were several other invasions by Alani, Vandals and Goths in the next few years, during which time Honorius moved his court to Ravenna, supposedly out of harm's way. In the early battles, Stilicho had to strip the Rhine frontier of troops so that in the following years a new coalition of Ostrogoths, Quadi and Asding Vandals, along with a clan of Alans who had fled from the Hun-dominated Caucasus, moved west almost unopposed and crossed the frozen Rhine into the now almost defenseless France. Stilicho was executed by his own emperor in 408, thus opening the gates to King Alaric and his Visigoths, who now left Yugoslavia, entered Italy and by 410 had sacked Rome1. Alaric died shortly thereafter and Athaulf became king of the Visigoths as they moved to Gaul in A.D. 411.

Upon the death of Honorius in 423 the Emperor Theodosius II of Constantinople became the sole ruler of both East and West. The usurper John was proclaimed Western emperor by the Ravenna court in 424 but Eastern armies under the Alan General Ardabur and his son Aspar, defeated the forces at Ravenna, executed John and made Valentinian III the emperor. John had expected help from 60,000 Huns who had been recruited in Pannonia by Aetius, but they arrived too late and were sent back. From this time on the military had the greatest power and used increasing numbers of Germanic and Hunnic auxiliaries. Aetius became the senior general in 430. Under Emperor Valentinian III, Leo I, surnamed the Great, became the Bishop of Rome and in essence the Pope of Western Christendom. By courage and statesmanship he raised the Apostolic See to new heights of power and dignity and we should note that this, in effect, marks the beginning of the very definite separation of the head of the western Christian Church, soon to be known as the Pope, from the few remaining weak Western Roman emperors. For the record these emperors are as follows:

455 - Petroneus Maximus
456 – Avitus
457 - 461 Majorian
461 - 465 Libius Severus
467 - 472 Anthemius
472 - Olybrius
473 - 474 Glycerius
474 - 475 Julius Nepos
475 - 476 Romulus Augustulus. End of the Roman Empire, West

To return to our narrative, in 440 the Vandals landed in Sicily and in 452 Attila invaded Italy with his Huns. After plundering Etruria, however, he retreated because of famine and epidemic and apparently some gold payment from Rome. General Aetius was murdered in 454 by Valentian III and his associates, but then the emperor himself was murdered a year later and the Vandals attacked Rome again, plundering the city for two weeks. No aid came from the East, and the new Emperor Petronius Maximus was killed. The next emperor, Avitus with some allies from Gaul won some victories over the Vandals in Sicily and off Corsica, but then Avitus' general, Ricimer, revolted and deposed the emperor. But Ricimer was a German and could not become emperor, so Majorianus assumed that role. He built a navy and beefed up the army with Ostrogoths and restored some vestige of imperial prestige in Gaul. But he was decapitated by the wily Ricimer after loss of a sea battle off the coast of Spain. The Western Roman Empire was now in poverty. In this one century Rome shrank from a population of 1,500,000 to 300,000 as Italy was invaded six times. Finally in the sixth decade of this century the Eastern emperor, Leo I (not to be confused with the Bishop of Rome), decided to help defend Italy against the Vandals and sent a large eastern army and fleet to join with the western Emperor Anthemius' forces. In 468 an army of 100,000 and navy of 1,100 ships still lost to the Vandals.

As indicated above, the line of Western Roman emperors came to an end and Zeno in Constantinople had jurisdiction over all. The Germans who had been brought into Italy in ever increasing numbers now, as a result of their multiplication and intermarriage, became a very prominent faction in Italy. Within 20 years southern Gaul, Dalmatia and Italy were all German kingdoms. Odoacer, the son of Edecon, a minister of Attila but himself from German tribe under Attila's rule, governed Italy as "Patricius", under the distant Emperor Zeno. The latter soon became afraid of the power of Odoacer and actually encouraged the Ostrogoth King Theodoric to invade Italy. After four years of war, from 489 to 493, Theodoric became master of an enlarged new Gothic-ltalian kingdom with a court at Ravenna. The Ostrogoths were Arians and this religious heresy situation became a part of the civil wars that disrupted the political unity of the empire. (Ref. 9, 10, 11, 12)

Still unconquered, the Vandals controlled western Sicily and Sardinia as part of their north African kingdom throughout the remainder of the century.

CENTRAL EUROPE (See also TURKEY, THE BALKANS and ITALY)

GERMANY

"Germanic" is a designation of a great many tribes who spoke related Germanic languages. Several, such as the Saxons, East Franks and Alemanni eventually settled in the region between the Alps and the North Sea, the Rhine and the Bohemian mountains and their languages gradually evolved into modern German. Others, settling in Scandinavia, England and along the channel laid the foundation for such modern languages as Swedish, Norwegian, English and Dutch. Germany, in this 5th century, was a sea of slowly changing and migrating people. The Huns were pushing in from the east, driving a Slavic people before them who settled in what is now eastern Germany, as Wends and Poles. The Huns themselves veered to the south through what later became Austria-Hungary and then pushed on into Bavaria and to the Rhine, engaging in a tremendous battle with Romanized Visigoths at Troyes in 451. The effect of these migrations and raids was to push the original Germanic tribes west and south with the Vandals, Suevi and Alani ending up in Spain. The Huns decimated the Burgundians with the remnants settling as "federates" near Geneva. (Ref. 13, 14, 15)

By the last of the century, the Franks were well established on both sides of the Rhine in a large area including parts of both modern France and Germany. In 481 Clovis became king of all the Franks and formed the first of the large, central European monarchies. When he adopted Christianity about A.D. 500 his western Frankish followers readily joined his conversion, but east of the Rhine there was not a pre-existing local Christian population and the Rhenish Franks remained pagan. At this same time the Marcomanni left Bohemia and invaded Bavaria. (Ref. 16, 17, 18)

AUSTRIA

For awhile Austria was on the march route of the Huns and we shall discuss these people more in detail later. After Odoacer (See ITALY above) annihilated the Rugier tribe in 488 the Lombards moved down into northern Austria and southern Moravia. Vindo- bona (Vienna) remained as a fortress and apparent sanctuary to all of Celtic-Roman descent. Rome had completely withdrawn from the Danube area by 488 and the vacuum was filled by the Huns. (Ref. 19)

HUNGARY

By 406 the Huns were in eastern Hungary with Ostrogoths just to their west and Lombards and Rugiers in the Czech area just northwest. At this time Uldin was ruler of the Huns in Romania and after making an alliance with Stilicho in 406 together they defeated a wave of Goths invading Venetia and Lombardy, with the captives taken to be sold later into slavery. There were no Alans in Hungary after about this date and thereafter the Huns dominated the area. Very little is known about them in the 2nd decade except that they had a King Charaton who received gifts from Honorius of the Roman Empire. The climax of Hunnic power came after 420 but in 427 they were attacked by Romans and some were conquered so that as a people they lost cohesion and had no central authority. By 432 Ruga was king of some of the Huns, but his exact territory is unknown. The East Romans waged war against him until his death in the late 430s. The Huns then had two kings - Bleda in the east and Attila in the west. These men were apparently brothers and their forces together broke into Illyrium in 441. In 445 Attila murdered his brother, however, and became the sole ruler. Four years later he met with East Roman ambassadors just over the Illyrium border on Italian soil and Attila was made a "military magistrate" and given land along the Sava and a yearly salary. In spite of this he raided Italy in 452 after a relatively unsuccessful invasion of Gaul the year before. He was bought off before he crossed the Po, but Milan was taken and much booty found. Disease was probably a big factor in preventing further forays. Attila died in 453 and while his sons were quarreling over the estate a coalition of German tribes led by Ardaric, king of the Gepids, revolted against their overlords and after several battles, defeated the Huns at Nedao River2, with allegedly some 30,000 Huns slain, including Ellac, Attila's oldest son. Thus ended the height of the Hun power and although they made a few more raids of the Eastern Empire, they finally returned to the Russian steppe about 470 and settled on the shores of the Sea of Azov. At about 444 Attila had been the most powerful man in Europe and a contemporary of Valentian in Rome and Theodosius II of Constantinople. He was not entirely a savage but actually had some sense of honor and justice, in spite of the fact that his men at times did pillage and ravage and that he murdered his own brother. Such atrocities as the latter, however, were common among all ruling families of that time and even much later, in history. (Ref. 20, 21, 22)

Some further description of the Huns and their lives is warranted at this time. The origin, race and language of these people is still in some dispute. Paleo-anthropological evidence indicates that they were a racially mixed group with both Mongoloid and Europoid3 elements. Up until the 1940s the classical concept was that the European Huns were one and the same people with the Hsiung-nu originating in Mongolia on the northern border of China. These definite Mongoloids allegedly moved first to middle Asia and then spread westward. But there were Europoids in eastern Asia and western China also, some of which were conquered and enslaved by the Hsiung-nu. Some skeletons on the borders of China dating to 450-230 B.C. show features of both great races - flat faces of the Mongoloid and yet the wide open eyes of the Europoid. One of the nineteen Hsiung-nu tribes, the Chieh, was massacred in northern Honan in A.D. 349 and the great majority of them were found to be Europoids. The Wu-sun (part of the Jung) neighbors of the Hsiung-nu had cerulean eyes and red beards and were predominantly Europoids. We must conclude that at some point in time a group of these mixed peoples, part Mongoloid and part Europoid, started west through the steppe area to become known as Huns.

We have no written language from the Huns - their scribes were borrowed or enslaved Romans, writing in Latin or Greek. But the Hun aristocracy had chiefly Turkish names, with some Germanic ones apparently borrowed from their sometimes allies, the Goths and Gepids. Many of their names and place names were Latinized by their Latin chroniclers. Many languages were spoken in Attila's kingdom - Hunnish, Gothic, Alanic, Latin and Greek, but it is probable that their native tongue was Turkic, from the Eurasian steppes. The name "Attila" comes from the Gepid "Atta" meaning "father" and his brother's name, Bledas is also German. Other names and particularly tribal names, however, were definitely Turkish.

The Huns were semi-nomadic, keeping all kinds of domestic animals, but essentially living on their horses and off their sheep. From the latter they had mutton, milk, cheese, felt, tents, shoes and caps (curved and pointed). They spun the sheep wool and made linen but agriculture was apparently at a minimum. By Attila's time, Hun nobles had houses with walls of well-planed planks and panels, containing seats, beds and draperies. They loved gold and extracted extremely large sums at regular intervals from the Romans. In the 440s East Romans paid the Huns about 13,000 pounds of gold and they also received some for auxiliaries lent to the Romans and as ransom for prisoners and through the sale of slaves obtained as prisoners of war. Trade was brisk at times, involving not only slaves but horses in exchange for gold, wine and silk, which was greatly prized by all the "barbarians". The Huns had an aristocracy and they had slaves, although most of the latter were quickly sold to the Romans. Their wharf are was rather typical of all barbarians from the steppes - confined principally to wild cavalry attacks, accompanied by much terrifying noise, lightly equipped but with accurate bows, lances, swords and shields. There is some evidence that the nobles had some types of armor, chiefly scale armor made from horses hoofs, but the commoners often fought naked, a feature which added to the terror experienced by their "civilized" enemies. They appeared to be glued to their short-legged, big- headed, shaggy, long-bodied ugly horses. They had no spurs, but did use whips. The question of whether or not they had stirrups is still not settled. Some nomad barbarians definitely had wooden or even metal stirrups (as the later Magyars) and the Huns wore soft shoes adaptable to round, wooden stirrups and it is possible that they had them. Accurate bow shooting is difficult and lance fighting without stirrups is almost impossible unless the lance is more or less tied to the horse. Saddles with a wooden tree have been identified. Horses were branded and ear-marked for identification and the warrior horses were almost all geldings. Although archeological evidence is scant, it is assumed that the Huns used horse drawn carts for supplies and loot. The stories of their atrocities are legion and most must be looked at somewhat skeptically and they were probably not much, if any, worse than any of the nomadic invaders from the steppes or even the Romans, themselves.

Their bows were reflex, composite4 types, 140 to 160 centimeters in length and very accurate up to 50 to 60 meters, with an effective range up to 160 to 175 meters. An unusual weapon of the Huns was the lasso, with which they entangled the arms and legs of the enemy so that he could not ride or walk. The Hunnic shields were probably of wickerwork, covered with leather and there are no archeological remains of these. They did have some art work and many diadems of gold sheet over bronze plaques have been excavated, along with gold and silver earrings. Hunnic bronze cauldrons are plentiful from Hungary and the upper Balkans.

The contemporary description of the physiognamy of the Huns are undoubtedly influenced by the extreme terror they produced in those about to be attacked, but there is no question but what they were a short, thick-limbed people with flat noses, the latter having been produced in infancy by binding, to deform the developing skull. It has been surmised that this allowed the wearing of a special helmut with a flat nose-piece extension, in later life. In addition, the male's faces were early scarred by intentional knife cuts, so that beards could not grow in the mature, scarred faces. These old healed cuts and scars, with their resulting flat, ugly faces certainly did not detract from the overall impression of the devil incarnate. (Ref. 24)

CZECHOSLAVAKIA

About A.D. 400 the Lombards (Langobards) drove from the Elbe eastward and southward, appearing about 430 in Bohemia and later moving into Moravia and Austria. The Rugians crossed the Danube south from Bohemia but were annihilated by Odoacer who had taken over Dalmatia on the death of the Western Emperor in 480. A confederacy of Suevic bands, the Bavarians and Marcomanni now occupied Bohemia. (Ref. 25) The Bavarians, of course, were later to move west into Germany, but the Slavs who stayed and settled permanently in Bohemia were the ancestors of later day Czechs, Vlachs and Slovaks. It was only after the retreat of the Huns that the full extent of the Slav migration would be realized. (Ref. 26)

SWITZERLAND

In this century Switzerland was invaded by the migrating Alemanni and Burgundii so that finally the domain of the latter stretched from Switzerland south to the Mediterranean. The Huns then almost annihilated these Burgundians in their westward raids in the middle of the century with the remnants remaining under Roman domination near Geneva. (Ref. 27, 28

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

The Franks, Burgundians and Alemanni who had annexed the left bank of the Rhine, allowed the Alans, Vandals and Suevi to cross the Pyrenees and seize land along the Atlantic seaboard of Spain. They went to the Straits of Gibralter and some even crossed to the African Coast and the old Romano-Hispanic ruling classes were overthrown. Later in the century, after having made a treaty with Emperor Honorius, about 100,000 Visigoths under King Wallia, successor to Alaric and Ataulf, entered Spain and nearly exterminated the Alans and the Siling Vandals. The Suevi and the Asding Vandals retired to the northwest corner of the peninsula and the northern areas of the Basques was never taken. (Ref. 29) Some of the Vandals retreated to Andalusia in the south, from which they later continued their conquest of North Africa. Finally there were about 200,000 Visigoths against a native population of some 6,000,000, but the former were much more mobile and dynamic and easily controlled Spain. (Ref. 30, 31, 32) Under Theodoric II (453-466) the Visigoths finally defeated the Suevi at Oporto and then broke with the Roman Empire. Euric (466-484), brother of Theodoric II, completed the conquest of the peninsula, but lost the original Visigothic home base in Gaul to the surging Franks who detested the Visigoths because of their Arianism. (Ref. 33)

FRANCE AND NETHERLAND AND BELGIUM

We have seen above (See ITALY) that Stilicho, in effect King of Italy, withdrew troops from the Rhine to fight various Germanic tribes in central Europe and then the Marcomanni-Quadi group, collectively known as Suevi, easily crossed the defenseless, frozen Rhine into France. (Ref. 34) Meanwhile the Franks had settled on the western slope of the Rhine, had captured Cologne and were in Franconia on the east. By 430 Gaul was about half Frankish and half Gothic and Celtic, and it was the most prosperous and intellectually advanced of the western provinces. The agriculture of the Germanic tribes was better suited to that climate than the Roman Mediterranean style of agriculture so a German style of life took its place.

As recorded above, in A.D. 451 Attila and his German auxiliaries, possibly at the request of Gaeseric5, the Vandal king, moved far into France to Orleans and after a battle near by against a mixture of Burgundians, Romans, Franks and Visigoths, Attila finally withdrew to Hungary after massive casualties had been experienced by both sides. Only the Salian Franks in the northeast of France, escaped the Huns domination in the first surge. In 470 the Visigoths again expanded to the Loire and the Rhone and then again conquered Spain, except for a few northern areas, as we have mentioned above. Clovis started his control of the Franks by conquest in 481 and his conversion to Christianity occurred in 496. The Celts on the west side of the Rhine had been exposed to this religion for a long period and Clovis' conversion only solidified his control over them. Although his original territory included only the northern areas about Cologne, Hesse, Tournai, Cambrai and Treier, he soon destroyed other chieftains of the Rhine, Moselle and Meuse valleys. His final mastery over all Gaul began with his defeat of Syagrius, "King of the Romans" at Soissons in 486 and he then became truly "King of the Franks"- (Ref. 35, 36)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

Roman evacuation of England was probably complete by 407, and in 410 the Roman Emperor Honorius wrote to the leaders of British towns telling them to look after their own defence. This was almost simultaneous with the revolt of peasants, rampant disease and raids by Picts, Irish, Angles, Saxons, Jutes and Frisians. (Ref. 38) In the 420s Vortigern, one of the British tyrants, rose some in power and used the previously tried Roman policy of using German mercenaries to swell his armies. Others soon did likewise and the fate of Celtic England was probably sealed. There was a continuous influx of new Saxon immigrants and from 440 on they occupied the eastern and southern coastal areas of Essex, Kent and Sussex and controlled the mouth of the Thames. The Angles came from Slesvig and brought with them to England a knowledge of Nordic mythology, as found in the "Song of Beoweulf ". In the southwest the Britons kept out the Saxons, under the leadership of King Ambrosius and the shadowy King Arthur. In A. D. 500 these Britons won a pitched battle at Mount Badon, somewhere in the southwest. (Ref. 39) Some Britons escaped the Germans by going to the Brest peninsula of France, subsequently becoming known as Bretons. (Ref. 40, 41)

SCOTLAND

In Scotland there were now four political nuclei; Picts, Dalreada, Welsh refugees and Ida of Bernicia's realm. At the end of the century the Gaelic Scotti migrated from the north of Ireland to Scotland, giving the country its final name. The kingdom of the Picts and Scots resulted from the fusion of these Irish raiders and the Pictish tribes- men. By the end of the century the Irish had taken the Hebrides, there to contest with the Vikings, and many had beached their ships on the western Pictish coast. (Ref. 42, 43)

IRELAND

A powerful new family, the Ui Neill (sons of Niall) burst out of Mide to take virtually the entire northern half of the island under control, including a large part of Connaught and demolishing Ulster. Their original home near Tara in Mide, near modern Dublin, appears to have been an early sacred place, and perhaps using this as a lever, the Ui Neill laid claim to kingship over the entire country. Whether their claim was generally recognized is not known, but certainly the Eoganachta family did not, as they set up their own state in Munster and part of Leinster. The Ulster remnants crowded into a small area on the Irish sea coast of Dal Riata and from there they migrated on to Pictish territory of Scotland, called Argyll. The Romans called these Irish "Scotti" and so this name and their Goidelic language was given to this neighboring island. (Ref. 44)

Ireland started to become Christianized about 431 and shortly thereafter Patrick became the Irish bishop. He was originally a slave taken from a Christian home in Roman Britain Irish raiders, but he escaped and went to France, where he received monastic training before returning to Ireland. Pious tradition tells of hundreds of miracles performed by Patrick and the nun, St. Brigid, including restorations of sight to the blind and hearing to the deaf, raising people from the dead and similar procedures. (Ref. 45)

WALES

Wales was now becoming occupied by Irish. Celtic people related to the Feni of central Ireland gave rise to the Gwynedd in north Wales and the Desi of southern Ireland became the Dyfed of south Wales. But these Irish were later expelled by the P-Celtic speaking Cymru and the former left behind only Ogam monuments in the Gaelic tongue. (Ref. 46)

SCANDINAVIA

The Sveas (or Sviar) established their kingdom on the west side of Sweden and legend has it that the Goths developed their civilization in south-central Sweden. Helgo, an island in Lake Malar, became a trading post in the center of the Sviar Kingdom.

Archaeologically this era is called the "Teutonic Iron Age" in Denmark. (Ref. 47) A Nydam boat over 60 feet long with an outward resemblance to big boats of today, with oars and perhaps sail and very little keel has been found there, dating to this period. These boats were similar to the ones the Angles sailed to England from Slesvig throughout the century. There were numerous internecine wars and wars between Norwegians and Danes and Swedes. It was a wealthy period for the region but also a time of troubles, with construction of forts for each community. At the end of the century, each community hoarded gold. The use of the runic characters, the Scandinavians' own system of writing to show the sound of their languages, had been quite fully developed by this time. As mentioned in the previous chapter, the runes, or letters, were edged and particularly adapted for writing on wood.

The ancestors of the Finns, a Finno-Ugrian family of peoples, may already have been in Finland by this time. They were at least definitely in the region of the Baltic.1

1 Perhaps the gold was paid to soldiers or frontier tribes. As the land routes were cut there was some increase in sea trade, so Jutland and Norway benefited. Norwegian boats of this century were 20 to 37 meters long, but archeologists have been unable to tell how they were propelled. In Sweden the city of Helgo began to flourish and it remained an important center for the next 500 years. (Ref. 48)

EASTERN EUROPE

As mentioned previously the Finno-Ugrian peoples were spread from the Baltic to the middle Urals and were primitive hunters and fishermen. Some of these people were the ancestors of the present day Finns and those in the Ural area were now called Magyars. In this century, for some unknown reason, the latter started to migrate westward.

The original home of at least part of the Slavs seems to have been the marshes of the western Ukraine in southwestern Russia. Originally they were a drunken, unclean, cruel people with a passion for pillage but nevertheless a good natured folk loving games, dances and songs. They fell easy prey to the Huns who drove them ahead westward, much as one drives cattle, using them as a vanguard and in a sense, as slaves. (Ref. 49) By A.D. 420 almost all of Poland was Slavic. Related to the Slavs were the Balts on the southeastern shore of the Baltic but by A.D. 450 all of these were subservient to the Huns. (Ref. 50) After the latter's defeat in the Pannonia area, most of them retreated to the Russian steppe (A.D. 470) where they settled down with related tribes on the north of the Black Sea along the shores of the Sea of Azov, where they became known as Kutrigurs and Utigurs. On the Crimea, there remained a small pocket of Ostrogoths.

In the last quarter of the century, the full extent of the Slavs in Russia and west to the Elbe River and down to the lower Danube in eastern Europe could be appreciated. The Antes of south Russia were the wealthiest and most powerful but politically all Slavs as well as the related Balts were naive and easily dominated by others. (Ref. 51)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American ent day Albania the last real western RomaHeritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

6 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

10 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

11 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

14 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

15 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

16 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

17 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

18 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [181]. RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

20 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

21 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

22 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

23 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

24 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

25 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

26 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

27 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

28 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

29 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

30 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

31 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

32 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

33 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

34 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

35 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

36 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

37 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

38 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

39 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

40 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

41 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

42 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

43 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

44 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

45 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

46 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

47 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

48 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

49 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

50 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

51 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  It is of interest that Alaric captured 5,000 pounds of pepper in Rome. (Ref. 8)

2.  This river was apparently in southern Pannonia (Hungary), south and west of the Danube

3.  The terms "Mongoloid" and "Europoid" as used here are based on a classification by Russian anthropologists (Ref. 23)

4.  A bow with laminated construction, using wood, sinew and horn. These had been excellently crafted and used in Asia and China for many centuries

5.  Maenchen-Helfen (Ref. 37) says this idea is "grotesque" (Page 130) and says the reason Attila went into Gaul instead of Italy is unknown

Europe: A.D. 501 to 600

EUROPE

An interesting map showing the extent and location of the various barbarian migrations and their kingdoms about A.D. 526 will be found on the next page.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

All, including Malta remained a part of the Byzantine Empire.

GREECE

Greece was an integral part of Byzantium. The Emperor Justinian closed the University of Athens and some of the professors fled to the more enlightened Persia to continue their work there. All pagans were ordered to become Christians. About A.D. 600 Slav tribes crossed the Danube and descended into Greece, driven by Avars behind them and soon only a few southern coastal cities remained Greek, in the old sense. (Ref. 1)

NOTE: Insert Map 32: The Barbarian, Migrations and Kingdoms AD. 526

UPPER BALKANS

For most of the century, the Ostrogothic king of Italy, Theodoric, also reigned over the Balkan area bordering the Adriatic in the region known as Dalmatia. At the end of the century, however, the Bulgars, Avars and a mixture of southern and western Slavs entered the area and remained to become the Croats, Serbs and finally the Yugoslavians. The Avars were a Mongolian people of mixed Turkic background who had moved from Turkistan through southern Russia, enslaved masses of Slavs, as the Huns had ahead of them and moved on into Europe, ravaging the Balkans on the route and almost wiping out the Latin speaking peoples. Except for Salonica, Macedonia was permanently settled by Slavs in this century. Their occupation of ancient Dacia cut the land contact between Rome and Constantinople. The Bulgars, who moved in from beyond the Danube, controlled the Slavs in their area but gradually took over the Slavic language and culture. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

ITALY

At the end of the last century, the Byzantine Emperor Zeno had commissioned the Arian Ostrogoth King Theodoric to conquer Italy and he had promptly done so. He then reigned over southern Italy, Sicily and a portion of the southern Balkans, Dalmatia, which was nominally under the Byzantine emperor. In addition, early in the century Theodoric defeated some of the Franks and kept the French Mediterranean strip as well as later increasing his holdings in Provence. He was a relatively just and progressive ruler encouraging a revival of learning and literature. His minister of state, Cassiodorus, a Roman of Greek lineage, tried to reconcile the Germanic and Roman types of culture and failing, he withdrew to found a monastery. He composed a history of the Goths, written in Latin.

The original has been lost, but excerpts by Jordanes, another Gothic official, are to be found in his Getica. Cassiodorus was responsible for saving some books from the great Roman libraries, including some works of Hippocrates and Galen, which he stored with other classic manuscripts in his ultimate monastery. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8)

The long Gothic wars ruined Italy. The problems included the existence of two distinct races - Roman and Goth - and two religions - Catholic and Arian, trying to live side by side, each practicing its own laws and traditions. The eastern Emperor Justinian, through his General Belisarius, retook Sicily in 535 and invaded Italy proper in 536 but did not crush the Ostrogoths until 563 when the Germanic Lombards, perhaps originally from Scandinavia and now driven west from Bohemia and Germany by the Avars, arrived to conquer the northern half of the Italian peninsula. These Lombards were the last invaders of Italy, and they ruled their half for two centuries. An outbreak of bubonic plague had weakened the defense of Italy and some say that these Germanic people came into what was practically an empty country. This plague raged in Rome in A.D. 590 and in that same year a Byzantine counter-attack cut the new Lombard Kingdom into two parts, across the waist of Italy but the Lombard vitality continued in spite of this. In the area at the head of the Adriatic Sea, the Veneti tribe and refugees from other regions formed an island empire of sea-farers. (Ref. 9, 10)

Throughout the peninsula the old Roman institutions were rather quickly abandoned and among the first to be dispensed with were those of law and medicine. For some reason not entirely clear, non-clerical physicians just ceased to exist. The Benedictine monks encouraged care of the sick but only through prayer could cure come, so St. Benedict forbade the study of medicine. (Ref. 11, 12)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY AND AUSTRIA

The Slavic Wends had pushed into Germany as far as the Elbe River. West of the Elbe and Saal rivers were the surviving German tribes in the following locations, each retaining its own identity:

Saxons in the north central region.
East Franks along the lower Rhine.
Thuringians between the Saxons and Franks.
Marcomanni (Bavarians) along the middle Danube. They had migrated from Bohemia in this 6th century into an area of collapsing Ostrogoths.
Suevi (Swabians) along and between the upper Rhine and upper Danube and along the northern Alps.

Of these tribes, the Franks were culturally of the greatest significance. Reinhardt (Ref. 13) says that this culture stands out as the fountainhead and pattern of the future German civilization. There is some disagreement concerning the language changes. Wells (Ref. 14) writes that the Franks were akin to the Anglo-Saxons in speaking a "low German" which later developed into Dutch and Flemish, but Reinhardt does not agree, stating that the Franks, Alemanni and Bavarians from A.D. 500 to 800 had the high German sound shift ("p" to "pf" or "f"; "t" to "ts", "z" or "s"; and "k" to "ch"), while Anglo-Saxon, Dutch, Flemish (Walloon) kept the original low or north German sounds. Clovis ruled the Franks until 511 and more about this dynasty will be found below under FRANCE.

By A.D. 560, Clovis' sons and grandsons had extended Frankish rule to take over dominance of Thuringia, Bavaria, Rhaetia and Alamannia in Germany as well as the Burgundian kingdom in Switzerland and southern France. There was little displacement of the native popuIations, however, and German and French developed as separate languages while the government remained in the hands of bishops and counts from the old Gallo-Roman aristocracy. The real power, however, remained with the Frankish army.

The migrating and raiding Avars (See HUNGARY and CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA, this chapter) came in contact with the Franks on the Elbe in 562 at which time the Avar Khanate was perhaps one-half as large in north-south and east-west dimensions as the previous Hun Empire, but by A.D. 600 the Avars domain was almost as great as the Hunnish one, as they took over Hungary and most of Austria from the Gepids and the Lombards. By this time the Marcomanni had also reached lower Austria.

It is of some interest that falconry, although known from the Persian court as far back as 400 B.C., was really perfected in Europe by the Visigoths and Franks and became an important part of the hunting culture as well as an aristocratic pastime. (Ref. 15)

HUNGARY

History does repeat itself in Hungary. Just as the Huns had previously set up headquarters in Hungary now a new war band, fleeing from upheavals in central Asia and known as "Avars", established themselves on the Hungarian plain and launched raids far and wide, pushing the Lombards into Italy, the Slavs into the Balkans and allowing the Bulgars (another nomad tribe) to come along the lower Danube. These Avars, who raided Constantinople as well as western Europe from this base, were a mixture of Mongolian Juan Juan, pushed west by the Blue Turks, and various nomad Turkish or Hunnish tribes which they had picked up on their journey through northern Iran and the Russian steppe. (Ref. 16)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

As the Bavarians moved west out of Bohemia, the Slavs moved in and then also spread to Moravia.

SWITZERLAND

This land was still occupied chiefly by Burgundians under Frankish suzertainty and in this century they were joined by Suevi.

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

The regions of both Spain and Portugal were ruled by Visigoths but under Roman supervision. Through the influence of the church, which used Latin in her rituals, the Visigoths, within a century after their Spanish conquest, forgot their Germanic speech and corrupted the Latin of the peninsula into Spanish. This was a gradual language change and Spanish, as we know it now, did not actually mature until the 19th century, at least in written form. (Ref. 17) In this Spanish society, great gulfs remained between Christians and Jews and between rich and poor. The early Visigothic aristocracy was in close cultural contact with Rome and Byzantium and lived lives of affluence and taste. (Ref. 18)

Early in the century the Visigothic kingdom was ruled by a boy king who actually left the power to the Ostrogoth King Theodoric of Italy. The combined Gothic power was great and was such that the Vandals even gave up the western end of Sicily. (Ref. 19) An intra-Gothic war occurred in 554, however, allowing Emperor Justinian's General Belisarius to occupy southern Spain. As if to make up for this, the Suevi kingdom in Galacia was absorbed into the Visigothic kingdom in 585. (Ref. 20) A series of East Roman-Visigothic wars followed.

For awhile two legal systems existed in Spain, one a written German law and the other Roman law. Although many of the Visigoth nobles were publicly converted from Arianism to Roman Catholicism in 589, religious division persisted and the problem was augmented by the prosecution of Jews by order of Emperor Heraclius, early in the next century.

Architecture was poor, libraries small, common schools non-existent but a hospital under non-clerical administration was established for the first time at Merida in southwestern Spain in this century. (Ref. 21, 22)

FRANCE & NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

The army of the Frank King Clovis defeated the Visigoths at Voluille in A.D. 507 and then the remainder of Gaul fell quickly to the Franks as the Goths withdrew to Spain. This conquest of Gaul by the Frankish tribes marks a milestone of German and European history and transcends in importance the other migrations. All other groups were soon absorbed numerically and culturally by the native Roman populations, but the Franks, under Clovis, as founder of the Merovingian Dynasty, and his sons established a military kingdom with strong agricultural underpinnings and it persisted, with a capital at Paris. (Ref. 23) Wells (Ref. 24) says that those Franks who did not become Latinized became the Flemish and Dutchmen of South Holland but that North Holland is Anglo-Saxon in origin.

The development of various Germanic languages from the original Frankish tongue was discussed under GERMANY above.

Although Clovis became an orthodox (Nicene) Christian, much of the conversion of his people was accomplished by Irish and Anglo-Saxon monks. He made Gaul into France but after him the dynasty degenerated. His sons conquered the Burgundians about 532 but the Burgundian state still remained separate under Merovingian princes throughout the remainder of the century. Provence was acquired from the weakened Ostrogoths in 536. Frank chieftains intermarried with remnants of the Gallo-Roman senatorial class and generated the aristocracy of France. In spite of Christian conversion seldom has an upper class shown such contempt for morality as this one. (Ref. 25, 26, 27, 28)

As at Merido in Spain, Lyons had a non-clerical hospital in this century. (Ref. 29) Hugh Thomas (Ref. 30) writes that leprosy apparently arrived in France and England in this century and that lepers were isolated, declared legally dead and of ten excluded from the church.

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

After the Celtic victory of Mount Baden which was described in the last chapter, there was a period of security in southern England for about two generations but then the Saxons began to advance again so that by 577 the confrontation line extended to the Bristol Channel, Bath and Gloucester. By 600 only Devon and Cornwall of southern

England were not Saxon. The law, language and economy of the Roman province had disappeared. While the Saxons were valley livers and farmed and formed villages, the remaining Britons were in the hills and highlands. Thus hill, wood and stream names are of ten Celtic in origin, while lowlands and villages have Anglo-Saxon names. The Saxon villages were in open areas and the houses were little more than wattle and daub structures with a single ridge pole, sunken floor and a total space of about 10' by 15'. They used horse-drawn ploughs, milled wheat, barley and oats and grew cattle, sheep, goats and pigs. (Ref. 31, 32)

The transplanted Saxons were converted to Christianity in the last of the century chiefly through the efforts of the Frankish Queen of King Ethelbert of Kent and the papal envoy, St. Augustine, originally from North Africa. North England received Christianity from north Ireland via St. Columba, who succeeded Patrick.

SCOTLAND

Britons and a few Angles migrated into Scotland at this period and shortly after 525 the Irish colonized western Scotland. Soon the word "Scot", originally an alternative to "Irish", became reserved for these northern settlers only. In Scotland, proper, al- though the deserted Antonine wall had crumbled it still formed the loose southern border of Pictland. South of it the north Britons of Strathclyde, related to the Welsh, had organized an aristocratic society with manors, towns and farms. To understand the British Isles in those early days one must consider Ireland, Scotland, Wales and certainly northern England as an inter-related group of communities and it is difficult to completely separate their histories. (Ref. 33, 34)

St. Columba (See IRELAND below) carried Christianity from Ireland to Iona in western Scotland in 543. This religion was separate from control of the Vatican pope and was not related or descended directly from Latin Christianity in England. For four centuries lona was the center of Celtic Christianity and some beautifully decorated Celtic manuscripts survive from that era. (Ref. 35)

IRELAND

Colum Cille, later to be called St. Columba, was born in Dal Riata of the family Ul Neill and when forty-two years old, set out as a pilgrim, accompanied by twelve disciples, toward the land of the Picts. He landed on the tiny island of lona, there to establish his own type of Christian monastery. While still maintaining some ties to Ire- land, lona developed into a spiritual center for all the tribes of coastal Scotland. The Irish spirit shone with its strongest light at that time, with culture and knowledge at a high peak. Many learned men from the continent, fleeing the invading barbarians, ended up on the shores of Ireland. A boatload of 50 scholars arrived at Cork in 550, bringing with them their craftsmen and it was these wanderers who subsequently taught the technique and made princely ornaments as well as weapons. Then learned men from Ireland became missionaries back to England, Germany and Gaul. (Ref. 36, 37)

Monks from the Iona monastery sailed to the Orkneys, Shetlands, the Faroes and Iceland. (Ref. 38) It is even possible that St. Brendan, the patron saint of County Kerry, sailed to the coast of North America in a leather curragh with goat skin sails, in this century.

There is much of this in Irish legend and the 10th century book, Navigation Sancti Brendani, of unknown authorship, as well as some material evidence accepted by some established scholars including such things as 10th century Vikings' accounts of previous Irish navigators, possible ancient Irish Druid alphabet markings on Newfoundland rocks and "100 recognizable Celtic roots in words which were used by pre-European inhabitants of some of the places where Irish monks are supposed to have landed."1 Fell (Ref. 39) concurs in this.

In 590 Columba the Younger, also with twelve companions, went from his home in Leinster to France where he confounded the Merovingian king and founded monastic communities at Luxeil and Fontaine and then went on to Switzerland and Italy. At home, the Irish kings were finally converted to the Irish version of Catholicism, after the whole of Ireland was devastated by the yellow plague in the middle of the century. (Ref. 41)

WALES

Fleeing before the invading Germanic tribes, thousands of Britons went to Wales and mingled there with the Welsh Celts and Irish to form the Cymri people and the country then became known as Cymru. The family and clan were the basis of the social order. Christianity came in this 6th century through Dewi (David), who was canonized as the patron Saint of Wales in A.D. 1120. (Ref. 42) This was also the era of the Mabinogen - Tales of the Bards of Wales.

SCANDINAVIA

About A.D. 600 the Goths and the Svea of Sweden united to form the kingdom of Sweden. From that time on the Goths, as an entity, ceased to exist in the north, although a strong racial heritage is still seen throughout Sweden and especially on the island of Gotland. This was the time of the beginning of Scandinavian art with animal ornaments as the chief feature and which was to continue until the Viking Age.

The Danes had gold and silver and Roman money. Gradually it became the custom to seek one's living on the sea. With a population surplus and the other Germanic tribes blocking migration south by land, they sought paths of expansion on the open sea, although the true Viking Age was far in the future.1

1 There is some suggestion, though, that this was a time of crisis, possibly involving climate deterioration, soil exhaustion, deficiency disease in cattle, violent invasions, internal conflicts and possibly plague. The Swedish city of Helgö, however, apparently was not affected by the decline seen elsewhere. .Frisian settlements along the mainland coast were key centers for contact of the Scandinavians with western Europe. (Ref. 43)

EASTERN EUROPE

BALTIC AREA

The north-south expansion of displaced eastern Slavs between this and the 8th century cut the eastern Balts off from their western core, and in the west the Balts were confronted by Germanic expansion. Just south of the Gulf of Finland, some of the eastern Slavs took to the forests, wedging between the Finns and the Estonians. (Ref. 44) Most of Poland was occupied by various Slavic tribes who had not been disturbed by the Goths, Alans or Avars and their villages were not fortified until near the end of the century when they began to quarrel with each other. (Ref. 45)

RUSSIA

As the Germanic tribes moved west, the Slavs came out of the Pripet marshes, forested, swampy region about 38,000 square miles in area extending along the Pripet River, which is a branch of the Dnieper. (Ref. 46) Early in the century on the north shore of the Black Sea there were Kutrigur or Utigur Huns, along with a small pocket of Goths still on the Crimea. In the Caucasus there were Alans and north of them on the north shore of the Caspian were the Sabirian Huns and east of the Aral Sea were the Ephthalites.

In 559 the Avars, defeated by the Turks in eastern Asia, moved to the Russian steppe where Justinian paid them to control the resident Huns and Slavs who had been raiding the east Roman Balkan areas. These Avars, soon ruling from the Volga to the lower Danube, turned north and west until in 562 they came in contact with the Franks on the Elbe, establishing an extensive Avar Khanate. (Ref. 47, 48) The Western Turks, coming behind the Avars in 576, took part of the Caucasus just west of the Caspian and there known as the Khazar, although Alans still controlled most of the western part of this region between the Black and Caspian seas. North of the Khazar and the now separate Western Turkish Khanate were principally Finnish people, sparsely settled, while the Slavs were still farther west and dominated by the Avars.

The Black Bulgars, originally a mixture of Huns, Ugrians and Turks, lived at this time in the valleys of the Don and Volga rivers. In this 6th and the 7th centuries there were 12 major Slavonic tribes in Russia, including the Polinians living on the middle Dneipner in the Kiev region. They lived in communities, held slaves, and were family oriented in a type of democratic society based to some extent on communal ownership of property. Many groups were governed by "elders" rather than by chieftains. They may have traded some with Byzantium, but the chief economy depended on agriculture of the cut and burn principle.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [125].  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

5 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

6 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

7 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

8 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

12 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

13 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

14 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

15 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

18 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

19 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

21 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

22 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

23 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

24 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

25 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

26 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

27 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

28 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

29 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

30 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

31 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

32 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

33 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

34 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

35 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

36 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

37 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

38 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

39 [86] HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

40 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

41 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

42 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

43 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

44 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

45 [244] MALONEY, STEPHANIE J., "The Medieval Fortress of Mietlica in Poland", Archeology 35: 26-32, Mar./Apr. 1982.

46[8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

48 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  Quotation from "St. Brendan's Fantastic Voyage" by Gerald Schomp, (Ref. 40)

Europe: A.D. 601 to 700

EUROPE

Slavery continued in Europe throughout these "Dark Ages" despite the Christian Church, but in this century, when Arabs gained control of the Mediterranean, it was difficult for Europeans to get slaves from the Levant. Most were then obtained from the Slavic regions. (Ref. 1)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The century began with these islands all a part of the Byzantine Empire but one by one the Arabs began to take them over in the latter decades. Cyprus, with its copper mines, fell to the Moslems in 648 and Rhodes in 654. (Ref. 2)

GREECE

Greece was now heavily infiltrated with Slavic peoples and although nominally under the eastern Roman Empire, only some of the coastal cities were truly Byzantine.

UPPER BALKANS

The Bulgars, whose original Kaganate was in the middle Volga far north of the Caspian Sea, had migrated in the previous century to the Danube region. This group, including one branch of the Utigurs, had founded a Bulgarian kingdom in ancient Moesia, enslaving the Slavs already there but they adopted the Slavs' language and customs and in time intermarried with them. They began to take over more and more Balkan territory from Byzantium by 679 and were recognized as a separate country in 681 when their first king, Isperikh, was crowned at the capital, Pliska. These were the so-called "White" or "Western Bulgars", originally related to the Huns. (Ref. 3, 4)

Farther west, the Srbi (Serbs) settled in part of the old Pannonia and Chrobati (Croats) settled in Illyricum, forming eventually the country of Serbia. By 650 the Slavs \ constituted the majority of the people in the Balkans. Avar horsemen, operating out of Hungary, spread havoc intermittently through the area and repeatedly appeared under the walls of Constantinople.

ITALY

The Lombards regained control of the northern plain of Italy, where the Byzantines had driven a wedge, between A.D. 601 and 605, establishing a progressive state under Duke Agilulf, who was actually a Thuringian. The Lombards maintained intermittent relation- ships with Rome and eventually became Catholics. Venice continued as an independent realm, allegedly having been built up from fishing villages settled by fugitives from the Huns, on some 60 marshy islands. (Ref. 5) Rome continued as a part of the Byzantine Christian Empire although it was no longer its chief city. The remainder of Italy was a patchwork of independent cities or duchies, such as the Duchy of Spoleto and the Duchy of Benevento. (Ref. 6)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

The Germanic and Slavic peoples had little disease and no superimposed imperial macroparasitism1 such as the Mediterranean urban populations imposed on the peasantries there, and so they had tremendous population growths, with the Slavs colonizing the Balkan peninsula, as we have noted above, and the Germanic tribes swarming to the Rhine and finally far beyond to Britain. (Ref. 7)

Even in the previous century the Frankish kings of Germany had to reward their followers and the church by granting away their own land and revenues. By the middle of this 7th century two families had emerged as the principal agents of the kings for these transactions. One of these was from Austrasia, the traditional eastern Frankish land, and the other was from Neustria, the new lands north of the Loire. By 687 Pepin, of Heerstal (near Aachen) of the Austrasian family, had won out, thereafter dominating the Frankish kingdoms. (Ref. 8) At that time several basic or stem duchies became prominent, including Bavaria (named from the Baiuoaril branch of the Marcomanni), Swabia (bordering Switzerland), Thuringia, Saxony, Franconia and Frisia.

By the end of the century northeastern Germany had quadrupled its population over that of Roman times, chiefly due to the more abundant food supply available with the use of the "moldboard" plow, introduced by the Slavs. This plow required eight oxen to pull it but it allowed three-field rotation of crops and allowed not only the production of more, but also better food, containing more amino acids and protein, thus giving the people more energy and greater stamina. (Ref. 9) (See also FRANCE, this chapter)

AUSTRIA

The area now known as Austria was partly controlled by the German duchies and partly by the raiding Avars.

HUNGARY

This was the homeland of the Avars who raided in all directions from this base. Please see this section in the previous chapter.

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Moravians gained independence by holding off the Avars and then they were able to stop the Franks who tried to come in from the west. After the death of their King Samo, however, this first attempt at a Slavic state in central Europe collapsed. Samo may actually have been a Frank but he had managed to unite the Czechs and some of the Wends. The people of Bohemia also repudiated Avar suzertainty and after that the Avar power declined rapidly. (Ref. 10)

SWITZERLAND

This was simply part of the Frankish kingdoms.

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

Between A.D. 612 and 621, Sisebut, a well educated Visigoth monarch, reconquered most of the peninsula from the Romans and his successor, Swintilla, completed the job. Even so, the Visigoths became "Romanized" by legal unification through the Liber judiciorum of Reccesivinth after 649 and the warrior aristocracy of the Goths was united with the plutocratic-bureaucratic aristocracy of the Roman world. The common people raised sheep. (Ref. 11) Although the Visigoths had not used slaves in any significant degree previously, they took over the Roman custom with a vengeance and in the Code of King Erwig (680-687) there were 21 provisions giving severe penalties for harboring fugitive slaves. (Ref. 12)

FRANCE & NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM (See also GERMANY)

At the beginning of the century there were actually three separate Frank kingdoms: (a) Austrasia with a capital at Metz, lying to the east, actually in Germany and having chiefly Teutonic blood2; Neustria with a capital as Soissons and Gallo-Roman blood; and (c) Burgundy. The latter was united with Austrasia by King Clotaire 11 in 613, leaving only two. Partly because of the Frankish custom of rulers dividing their kingdoms among all sons, the Merovingian dynasty crumbled with a series of very weak rulers and the ministers, or major domos, began to be the actual administration heads of the government. Thus in 639 Pepin, as mayor of Austrasia, started the reorganization of the Frankish state. He and his immediate descendants gave much of the old nobles' western land to their own followers from the Rhineland, so that, in effect, France was subjected to a new Germanic invasion.1

1 (Ref. 13)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

In the early century, the Britons of Strathclyde, Wales and Cornwall were all separated by the Anglo-Saxon kingdoms. (Ref. 14) This was a period of adjustment under the Angles and the Saxons, the latter being the most cruel of the Germanic tribes.

They had probably incorporated the Jutes and Angles before the general exodus from Schleswig-Holstein. The Celtic Britons continued resistance on the periphery.

In 655 the Northumbrians regained leadership over Mercia, which had been the chief power from 642 on, and then the Northumbrians reduced the Britons (then all were called "Welsh") in Strathclyde to bondage as well as the Picts and Scots. The bond was short lived though as the latter quickly broke loose and by 679 Northumbria was again subservient to Mercia. (Ref. 15) Augustine became the first Archbishop of Canterbury in A.D. 601 and his early achievements were great. After the novelty of the new religion had worn off, however, many English leaders returned to their old ways so that by 616 even the church in Kent was in danger of extinction. (Ref. 16) Papal Christianity spread into north England through the increasing power of Edwin, King of East Anglia. In 664, after a conference of English (papal) and Briton (Celtic) bishops at the Synod of Whitby, most of the island became Romanized Christian but Ireland remained aloof. Two conferences of the Roman St. Augustine and his Saxon convert Christians with the bishops of the "Far Western Christianity" of Ireland, failed, and the two camps remained enemies. After that Synod a severe epidemic occurred, the nature of which is unknown. (Ref. 17) Bede recorded four epidemic pestilences in England within the 20 years from 664 to 683.

Of incidental interest is the fact that there was no wheel-turned pottery (Anglo-Saxon) in England before A.D. 675. (Ref. 18)

SCOTLAND

The Scots, originally from Ireland, as we have previously noted, pushed their way up the Great Glen and approached Iverness before they were finally defeated by the Picts. In the south the Angles were pushing north from England with both cavalry and infantry but the Picts, under Bridei, were temporarily united and able to drive them back in the battle of Nechtansmere in 685. (Ref. 19, 20)

IRELAND

At this time the Irish were materially and politically more backward than the English but in a special cultural way they were the most advanced of all peoples north of the Pyrenees and the Alps. Both Gallic and British scholars came to Ireland to escape the Germanic invasions. Ireland was never invaded by these tribes and was never Romanized. Its Christianity was a separate brand which was mentioned above as the Far Western Christianity (2) and which maintained an independent existence and development for many hundreds of years, reaching its apogee in the 6th and 7th centuries.

As in England the yellow plague hit Ireland in 664. Although we mentioned Irish exploration of the Faroe Islands in a previous chapter, some authorities believe that they did not discover these islands until about 690.

WALES

This remained as a western Celtic fringe.2

2 The shape and construction came from a long Baltic tradition, but the mast and sails were taken from western Europe. (Ref. 21)

SCANDINAVIA

NORWAY

An excavation at Kvalksund, Norway, shows that by about A.D. 600 sizable sailing ships were being built. These were shallow-draft vessels with planked decks but no keels. Thus, new mobility on the sea, coinciding with increased hunger at home, led to the Viking raids some two centuries later. (Ref. 22)

SWEDEN

This was an age of gold called the Vendel Period, in Sweden. The Swedes were beginning to push north and west to the northwest coast of Norway.

DENMARK

The Danes sea-faring was steadily increasing and they were already occasionally raiding the coasts of France.

FINLAND

This country was very sparsely occupied by Lapps whose early history remains something of a mystery. Speaking a Finno-Ugric tongue, traditionally it has been considered that they originated in central Asia but recent genetic studies indicate that they are true native Europeans.

EASTERN EUROPE

BALTIC AREA

Thomas (Ref. 23) says that the one contribution made by Slavs to human improvement was the re-introduction of the heavy plow, which was a variation of one used in northern Italy in the 1st century C.E. It had a knife-like iron blade in front which slashed vertically into the ground, a plowshare which cut horizontally through the ground and a mold-board which turned the soil over to one side. We have remarked earlier that the German put this to very good use in this century. Closely related to the Slavs were the Lithuanians, who together with the Letts and the ancient Prussians, formed the Baltic branch of the Indo-European family. They lived between the present day Memel and Estonia.

Poland had Slavic people divided into many tribes with no unification or organization at this period.

RUSSIA

Part of far eastern Russia was controlled by the great Turkish Confederacy which simultaneously dominated all of central Asia up until 630. The Khazar Khanate in southern Russia expanded rapidly, defeating their Caucasian neighbors, the Alans and the Bulgars and it was some of the latter who fled to the Danube next to the remaining Avars. Some went to the Volga where they remained under Khazar suzertainty. By 650 the Khazar Khanate extended from the Dnieper to the Caspian Sea, with a very modern city, Itil, as capital on the north shore of the Caspian. Northward they extended almost to the headwaters of the Volga. Their rulers accepted the Jewish religion, apparently to assert their independence from both Moslems and Christians.

Just north of the Black Sea, the Utigur and Kutrigur Huns coalesced and took a new name - Great Bulgaria. (Ref. 24) Elsewhere in western Russia the Slavs lived more or less freely and independently. In the very far north there were still the scattered Finns and/or Lapps. (Ref. 25)3

3 The Kama River valley was rich with a settled population, large grave yards and hill forts. Sassanian and Byzantine silver has been found there, apparently incident to trade. From Kama, the arctic valley of the Pechora was exploited. The Khazars controlled the southern part of that trade route and gathered tribute from a large area north of the Black and Caspian seas. All of this trade was interrupted in the middle of the century by the expansion of Islam and its attempt to conquer the Khazars. As a result, Byzantine and Sassanian coins disappeared from the Caucasus by 700. (Ref. 26)

1 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

10 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

11 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

12 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

13 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

14 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

15 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

16 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

17 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

18 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

19 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

20 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

21 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

22 [160] OXENSTIERNA, ERIC, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

23 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

24 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

25 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

26 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

1.  McNeill's terminology

Europe: A.D. 701 to 800

EUROPE

SOUTHERN EUROPE

In these early Middle Ages, the deadly black stem rust began to ravage the wheat fields, producing famine in various areas of southern Europe. The disease had been brought in, unknowingly, with the barberry bush by the Arabs. The barberry was valued for the curative potion (the stem) and the brilliant berries, edible in a preserve. (Ref. 1)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

In this century Crete, previously under Byzantium control, along with most of these islands, had some bases established by the sea-going Venetians. Cyprus was taken by the Arabs and then reconquered by Byzantium. (Ref. 2)

GREECE

For some centuries now the great classical and early Christian centers of the lower Balkans, - Athens, Corinth, Thebes, Salonica and others, had lost all contact with the world of which they had been an integral part. In 726 Greeks revolted against the Byzantine Leo III, sending a Greek fleet toward Constantinople but they were defeated by the imperial navy using an incendiary mixture called "Greek fire". (Ref. 3) As the century ended the Slavs were once again beating down on the borders of this country.

UPPER BALKANS

As in the last century the Balkans were filled with Slavic peoples, mixed here and there with Bulgars and Avars. In the new kingdom of Serbia the Serbs accepted the Greek Orthodox form of Christianity while the Croats adopted the Roman form. Stress inevitably followed so that by the end of the century the Croats had formed their own independent kingdom. (Ref. 4) The Danube Bulgars had continued to move west into the Balkans, taking land from Byzantium. Tervel, king of the Bulgars, actually exacted tribute from Emperor Justinian II. He was followed by King Sevar, the last of the Dulo Dynasty. (Ref. 5) Periods of war and peace between the Bulgars and Byzantium alternated throughout the century.

ITALY

The Lombards, who now filled northern Italy, fought by bow and arrow from horseback and were essentially a warrior people. As a papal state emerged where a pope (though not an emperor) still lived, it was threatened by the Lombards and the pope finally requested the Frank King Charlemagne to invade the area. At the end of the century Charlemagne complied and Lombardy became a province of the Franks. In an attempt to regain prestige to match that of Byzantine, Pope Leo Ill eventually teamed up with the Frank king to extend the Church's domain, with the result that the pope became the spiritual ruler and Charlemagne the temporal emperor of the Holy Roman Empire. By this time, Rome had dropped in population from about 1,000,000 in A.D. 400 to under 100,000, principally because of famine after the cessation of the giving of free bread. Gradually a coalescence of the Lombards and the Roman people developed with the result that there was a substantial Lombardic contribution to the Italian language and to the artistic and literary fields. The Latin language continued to be Latin, but further and further removed from the classical standards. Cases had all but disappeared by this time and the language has been called Proto-Romance. (Ref. 6, 7)

NOTE: Map 34: Lombard Kingdom Before Its Conquest by Charlemagne in 774 and

Map 35: Expansion of the Papal States 756-817

Maps taken from Reference 97

Naples, Amalfi and Venice continued as independent states with Venice actually helping the Moors enslave some Europeans. (Ref. 8) The first European medical school was founded in this century at Salerno, in southern Italy. Sardinia was invaded by Moslem forces in 720 and in this and the next century Sicily was exposed to sudden, devastating raids by Moslem free-booters. (Ref. 9, 10)

CENTRAL EUROPE

The use of the heavy plow (see pages 439 and 443) in northern Europe accounted for an increase of food and a consequent increase in population. Although there continued to be Merovingian kings in the Frankish kingdoms of Austrasia and Neustria up until 7529 throughout this century the real administration of western Germany, as well as of France, was under control of the House of Pepin, later called the Carolingian Dynasty, all descended from Pepin of Landen and Arnulf, the Bishop of Metz. Among these descendants was Charles Martel, Mayor of Austrasia and Neustria from 714 to 741 (See FRANCE, below), and Pepin III, the Short, Mayor of Neustria and king of the Franks from 747 to 768. It was this Pepin who first responded to the pope's pleas for help against the Lombards and did manage to force them out of Pentapolis and Ravenna. Thereafter the Carolingians maintained a protectorate over the papacy in Italy. (Ref. 11, 12)

In 768 Pepin III's son, Charles the Great (In France - "Charlemagne" and in Germany more correctly "Karl the Great"), became king of Austrasia, Neustria and northern Aquitaine, while his brother, Carloman, ruled over southern Aquitaine, Burgundy and Septimania. Charles (or Karl) was a typical German, six feet in height, a superb swimmer and athlete. He married a Lombardi princess but soon repudiated her and conquered all of Lombard Italy as well as Venetia, Istria, Dalmatia and Corsica. The Bavarian duchy had begun an eastward expansion that drove a wedge between the southern Slavs and the main mass of Slavic people to the north by 758, thus isolating the Balkan groups. Karl incorporated Bavaria into his kingdom in 778 and in the next year took Carinthia (southern Austria) and Vienna became a Carolingian-Frankish border fortress. Saxony fell to Karl in 785 and so all Germany, Austria, Bohemia and even a portion of Hungary came to be a part of his domain. As a result the more northern Slavs were pushed back east of the Elbe River, creating "New Germany", a distinction that has persisted in some degree to this day. The Elbe now roughly corresponds to the border between present East and West Germany. The history of the region of Brandenburg (later Prussia) begins when Karl the Great established forts along the Elbe to keep out the Slavs. (Ref. 13, 14)

In Hungary Karl's troops reduced the Avars to a mere remnant, as they were crushed between this Frankish army and a Bulgar attack from the east in 796. Switzerland was a part of the original possession of the Frankish Empire, included in the regions known as Burgundy and Alamannia and it was administered primarily under Neustria. (Ref. 15)

Charlemagne's Empire was Roman Christian and Germanic, all in one. Economically and socially it never attained to that cohesion and unity that characterizes a thoroughly civilized state. Beer had been made and drunk in large quantities in the German areas for several centuries and it was consumed throughout Karl's territory and even made by master brewers in his palaces. No hops were used. Christianization of northern Germany was completed partly by missionaries and partly by forced conversion by Frankish overlords After Charlmagne was crowned emperor by the pope on Christmas, A.D. 800, his Italian affairs occupied him so completely that he lost control of Germany and the Slavs again entered from the east in the next century. The Weser River represented the farthest limits of the Slav expansion westward. (Ref. 16, 17)1

1 (Ref. 18)

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

In A.D. 709 and 710 Moslem Moors attacked the Spanish coast but didn't land. At about the same time the Visigoth nobles were quarreling over the succession to the dead King Wittiza, finally electing a younger son, Rodrigo. Supporters of the eldest son fled to Morocco to get aid. As a result, a mixed force of Arabs and Berbers, led by the Berber Tariq from Mauretania, invaded Spain in 711, quickly taking the southern part, helped both by Jews and the Visigoth supporters of the eldest son claimant to the throne. Another Moslem general, Muza, landed at Algeciras in 712, quickly took Seville and Merido and then headed north. The surging Moslems went on to cross the Pyrenees and swept into France to be stopped finally at Tours, by Charles Martel, in 732. Falling back into Spain, the Moslems broke up the overgrown estates of the Visigothic nobles and developed a new society. The ruling Abbasid Caliphate was never accepted in Spain and the Spanish Moors declared independence from Baghdad in 756, reviving a branch of the old Omayyad family to form the Omayyad Dynasty of Cordoba which lasted until 1031. No western city equaled Cordoba in size or culture and no government in the west was better than that of Moslem Spain. (Ref. 19, 20, 21, 22)

The unconquered Goths, Suevi, Christianized Berbers of a previous migration, and the Iberian Celts went into northwestern Spain and Portugal, where the Goth, Pelayo, became king of Asturias and founded what was to become the Spanish monarchy. After Pelayo came Alfonso I and II and during this period the Visigoth Spanish Catholics now brought forth Spain's most brilliant and characteristic creation, Mozarabic art, found now in liturgy remnants only in Toledo and Salamanca chapels. These Catholics, allowed to worship as they pleased, although more or less confined to ghettos within the Moslem state and separated from the main European tradition, developed both their own individual brand of Catholicism and art. The latter was a vivid combination of remote classicism, Islamic miniatures and the primitive idioms of Visigothic folk-art. It is of interest that this Muslim conquest of Spain also culminated in a “Golden Age" of Spanish Jewry' (Ref. 23, 24)

Hisha I, emir from 788 to 796, reversed the doctrine of tolerance and attacked the Christians, although he promoted a religious and intellectual aristocracy. This latter group was suppressed with cruelty; however, as Hakam I took control in 796. (Ref. 25)

FRANCE & NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

It is again recommended that the sections on GERMANY and FRANCE be studied together in this and adjacent centuries since both were administered more or less together under the Franks. In 732 Charles Martel, son of administrator Pepin II, extended his father's confiscations to include all income from church lands under Frankish control in order to support a substantial force of cataphracts (armored knights) which gave him military supremacy in the entire area. It was he who stopped the Moslems at Poiters, near Tours in 732, using cavalry equipped with stirrups so that they could ram home lances and use maces and swords while remaining mounted. Without this battle, western civilization might never have existed. Following that victory Europe had to increase its numbers of horses and horsemen to continue to protect itself and "feudalism" was the result. (Ref. 26, 27)

The Merovingian Dynasty came to an inglorious end and the Carolingean Dynasty began with Martel's son, Pepin , who began to dominate a greater area and paved the way for his son, Charles (Charlemagne), the greatest of the medieval European kings. He allowed the pope to crown him "Emperor of the Romans" in 800 A.D. No eastern emperor had visited Rome for some 300 years. (Ref. 28, 29)

In the far north in the Belgium-Netherlands area, the Frisians were on top commercially, trading in wine, salt, oil, glass, textiles and metal work. In the far south of France a few Byzantine goods drifted in and in return the West sent slaves, iron and timber to the East. (Ref. 30, 31) (Continue on pages 488 and 490)2

2 (Ref. 32)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND & WALES

The scholar Bede states that five languages were spoken in England at this time - English, Celtic, Irish, Pict and Latin. The early English was the language of the Angles and differed little from Saxon and was intelligible to the Franks, Norwegians and Danes, all of these being varieties of basic German. The Beowulf, a famous Anglo-Saxon poem, appeared in England in this century. Gradually the Saxons developed kings, as glorified generals, who protected themselves by giving lands to barons and in this way a land aristocracy soon developed. In the last half of the century there were ceaseless wars between some seven kingdoms, all now nominally Christian. But Bede, writing to the Bishop of York, Egbert, in A.D. 734 complained that some bishops were drunken revelers and Boniface wrote in much the same vein to the Archbishop of Canterbury, complaining of drunkenness of bishops and loose living of nuns. So Christianity was not having an easy time. (Ref. 33)

All of this 8th century activity was followed in A.D. 793 by the first great Viking sacking of the monastic center at Lindisfarne, probably by Norwegians. Another group, probably also Norwegian, had come down the English channel in 789, landing at Portland on the Dorset coast. Danes from Jutland also started their raids. There is no doubt that all of these raiders, - Angles, Jutes and the later Danes and Normans as well as the North- men who went down through Russia, and the still earlier Goths, were all waves of one and the same type of Germanic people. (Ref. 34) But to return to England, in spite of all the turmoil, there was some international trade and visitations in this century. There were even Chinese in King Offa lI's Mercia court at the end of the century. Mercia, along with Northumbria and Wessex, were the largest of the English kingdoms. (Ref. 35) (Continue on pages 490 and 492)3

3 The Lindisfarne attack is well documented by letters, but that was not the first place to be raided in western Europe, just one of the more extensive and noteworthy. (Ref. 36)

SCOTLAND

Throughout the last century the Picts had fought against each other, but after a last intramural battle in 729, Oengus became king of all Picts. He promptly made peace with the Angles and then turned to battle the Scots, capturing Dunadd and Dunolly, drowning one Dalriadic king and forcing others to take to the sea. But when he wheeled south again against Strathclyde, his army was annihilated, perhaps through some treachery. (Ref. 37) Iona, the Scottish religious shrine island, was invaded by the Norse in 794 and was burned just after the turn of the next century. (Ref. 38)

IRELAND

The Christian world of Patrick's Ireland was shattered by Vikings in 795 and raided by them for the next 200 years. As a result of this, there are currently genetic similarities of populations of Scandinavia, Scotland and Northern Ireland, even though geographically separated. Irish monks landed in Iceland about 759, in hide-covered curraghs. (Ref. 39, 40)

SCANDINAVIA

NORWAY | SWEDEN | DENMARK

Of the territory of the Germanic peoples, only Scandinavia kept out of Charlemagne's Empire. In Sweden, the town of Birka began to dominate the area of Lake Malar. It was an economic unit of considerable importance. Even a bronze Buddha has been found there. Just west of present day Stockholm, the island of Helgo was the center of industry, including the production of cheap jewelry, iron-working, etc.

The first Dano-Norwegian raid to strike real terror in Europe was the attack on Lindisfarne, England in 789, where a famous convent and seat of learning was attacked and the inmates killed or taken off as slaves. Many of the raids of the Frisian and English coasts originated in the vigorous kingdom of Juteland in Denmark. "Viking" probably means "men from the fiords", because "vik" means "a little fiord" in both Danish and Norwegian. In addition to sea travel, the Scandinavians travelled great distances by land, as from Uppland, Sweden to Trondelag, Norway, by horses, sledges and carts. There was an ox-road from north Juteland into Germany. In winter men used skates and skies and put spikes on horses’ hooves. (Ref. 41)4

4 There were significant increases in imports of glass bowls, beakers, pottery, mill-stones and silver coins from western Europe through Frisia to Denmark and Helgo in Lake Malaren in Sweden. Boat-graves in the latter country contain such glass and coins.  In Denmark there was built the Danevirke, a complex fortification of timbers across the base of the peninsula, perhaps because of Charles Martel's campaign against the Saxons in 738. The Limfjord was open at both ends and that was the normal route from the North Sea to the Baltic. The trade route from Dorestadt up to Limfjord was well sheltered by islands and from the eastern end of the Limfjord the course went down through either the Great or Little Belt, where the exit was commanded by the island of Samso. This was bisected by a canal, either to facilitate tribute or protection. In the east, Courland was subject to the Swedes and Staraja Ladoga was established in the last half of the century on the route leading to the rich fur areas of north Russia.  The Danes and Swedes fought each other almost continuously. King Anoundus of Sweden, exiled in Denmark, got 21 ships from the Danes to add to 11 of his own and returned to attack Birka. In some way this was diverted, however, and he attacked the Slavs instead. (Ref. 42)

FINLAND

In this century the Finns, coming from the south and southwest, took present day Finland (at least Karelia) from the Lapps, who receded northward. As noted previously the Finns spoke a Finno-Ugric language, related to Lapp and Livonian. Their language, although not their blood types, suggest distant relation to the Huns and the Magyars who came from the upper Volga and Oka rivers. There were three basic tribes: the Tavastians, who settled in western Finland; the Karelians; and the true Finns who had originally settled on the south shore of the Gulf of Finland. They cleared the forest and drained the marshes, but the three tribes waged war on each other. (Ref. 43)

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

Related to the Finns were the Borussians (Old Prussians), Esths (Estonians), Livs (Livonians), Litva (Lithuanians) and Latvians who settled the Baltic areas south of the Gulf of Finland. All of these people remained pagan for several centuries.

Throughout this and the next century the Goplani and Lendizi Slavic tribes competed for control of the central area of Poland, with the Goplani initially the more successful. Recent excavations at Mietlica show sunken houses, chiefly of one room, rather typical of early Slavic abodes. Few houses had identifiable hearths, but there were hearths and pits in the central area of the town, suggesting a practice of communal cooking. (Ref. 44)

RUSSIA

The word "Rus" may have derived from the Finnish Ruotsi, old Norse rodr, or may be related to Rolagen in Uppland, Sweden. There were two major trade routes of the Viking Scandinavians down through Russia. The first went from the Baltic directly into Lake Nevo (Ladog) then down the River Volkhov to the great Lake Ilmen, to Lovat and portage to the Dnieper. Along this route, great towns of Kiev, Smolensk, Novgorod and Staraja were founded. The second was a more easterly route, along the Volga where there were already towns established for the fur trade and controlled by Bulgars and Khazars who charged a toll on traders. From the great bend of the Volga traders could strike out across the desert to reach the Silk Route somewhere near the Aral Sea. (Ref. 45)

Itil, on the mouth of the Volga and capital of the Khazars, became one of the great commercial cities of the world. The Arabs raided the Khazar homeland and put an end to the greatness of this Khanate, as the Volga Bulgars took advantage to assert their independence in the north of the area and the same was probably true of the Magyars, a Finnish tribe that had migrated to the steppe north of the Black Sea and had up until then been under Khazar domination. Their language was basically Finnish with a Turkish element added. These three oriental powers - Khazars, Bulgars and Magyars - remained friendly, with the Khazars still somewhat senior in the relationships. Reduced in size, the Khazar Khanate persisted until about A.D. 1,000 and its people did help to re-route the land trade route to the Far East north of the Caspian as Justinian had wanted to do. (Ref. 46) Elsewhere in Russia by the end of the century there was a Slavic Sea, with Slavic peoples spilling over into central Europe and the Balkans.5

5D. 770, after the Umayyads were overthrown by the Abbasids, Persian coins were once again in circulation throughout Russia. The Khazars were again the chief intermediaries. (Ref. 47)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

6 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [213]. THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [222]. TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

10 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

11 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

12 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

13 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

14 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

16 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

17 [181] RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

18 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

19 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

20 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

21 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

22 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

23 [180] RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

24 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

25 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

26 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

27 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

28 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

29 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

30 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

31 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

32 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

33 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

34 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

35 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

36 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

37 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

38 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

39 [143] MENOZZIL, P., PIAZZA, L. AND CAVELLI-SFORZA, L., "Synthetic Maps of Human Gene Frequencies in Europeans", Science 201: 789-7921, Sept. 1978.

40 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

41 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

42 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

43 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

44 [244] MALONEY, STEPHANIE J., "The Medieval Fortress of Mietlica in Poland", Archeology 35: 26-32, Mar./Apr. 1982.

45 [237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

46 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

47 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

Europe: A.D. 801 to 900

EUROPE

As this century opened, and particularly in A.D. 814, the year of the death of Charlemagne, Europe and Asia were recovering from the previous waves of barbarian invasions and a series of powerful empires extended in unbroken sequence from the Atlantic to the Pacific. The northern ones of Europe, however, - Frankish and Bulgarian - were really conquests of war bands and had very little stability. (Ref. 1)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The copper mines of Cyprus continued to be exploited. Over a period of some 3,000 years about 200,000 tons of that metal has been produced on Cyprus. The smelting requires charcoal in the amount that would be the equivalent of 150,000 square kilometers (58,000 square miles) of forest. Since all Cyprus totals only 9,300 square kilometers, the forests of the island must have been destroyed at least 16 times. (Ref. 2) The Turks took Crete from the Byzantine controlled Venetians and in 825 built a base with a surrounding moat, where Moslem pirates dominated until the middle of the next century. Malta was taken by the Moslems in 869. (Ref. 3, 4)

GREECE

The greater part of Greece was a part of Byzantium and, as such, shared in its temporary renaissance. Bulgaria took over part of northern Greece as a part of their expansion early in the century. Demonstrating the geological instability of the region, an earthquake of 856 killed 45,000 Corinthians. (Ref. 5)

UPPER BALKANS

The Avars were conquered by Charlemagne in 805 and as the remnants were pushed out of Hungary into the upper Balkans, they were absorbed by the Bulgars and Slavs. In 811 the still pagan Bulgars, under Prince Drum, defeated and destroyed the Byzantine armies of Emperor Nicephorus and then they took over a large part of the peninsula, even including some of Greece. Their territory then stretched from the Danube to the Theiss and from the Carpathians to the Dniester. Originally a Turkish people, the Bulgars became, by repeated admixture, almost entirely Slavonic in race and language. The Bulgar Khanate, under Czars Malamir and Boris , continued to expand rapidly and their empire even included a great part of Hungary until about 893, when the Magyars overcame the light hold of the Bulgarians in that region. (Ref. 6, 7)

Bulgaria and Serbia were won for the eastern Christian Church in 870 and 879, respectively, through the efforts of Cyril and Methodius, Macedonian Brothers, who helped Khan Boris to evolve a Slavonic or Cyrillic alphabet, thus allowing the development of a national written language and culture. Faced with Slavonic sounds which did not exist in Greek, they stretched the Greek alphabet as far as it would go, then drafted one or two Hebrew characters and invented others. The Eastern Church (Russian, Ukrainian, Serbian and Bulgarian) still uses this Cyrillic alphabet. (Ref. 8, 9) Farther for Western Christianity in 879, after they had made themselves independent of the German Empire in 869. (Ref. 10)

ITALY

We noted in the last chapter that Charlemagne had seized the Lombard Kingdom in 774 and this remained under his control until his death in 814. Italy, as a whole was under divided rule. By the Treaty of Verdun of 843, the Frankish heir, Lothar, got a long central strip of Europe along with northern Italy and down to the frontier of the Duchy of Benevento in southern Italy and he retained the title of emperor. A weak papacy, leagued with France, ruled a central area; the Venetians had their own kingdom; and various dukes ruled scattered provinces. Part of Sicily was conquered by the Aghlabids from Tunisia in 827 and by 840 they held most of that island and the heel of Italy. They were finally expelled by the Byzantines at the end of the century. During the period of the Moslem raids, even Rome had been attacked. (Ref. 11, 12)

While eastern and southern Italy, in spite of the Moslem raids, remained for the most part Byzantine in culture, the rest of the peninsula developed a new civilization, a new language, religion and art from its Roman heritage. The Italian language became the most melodious of tongues; Italian Christianity was a romantic and colorful paganism, - a frank mythology of legend and miracle. Rome itself declined and science succumbed to superstition and only medicine kept its head up through the monasteries. Latin Christendom adopted the Iranian type of heavy armored cavalry and with this began to stem the barbarian tide and pave the way for counter-expansion in the next two centuries. A bright spot on the peninsula was Salerno, where a university with a medical school was founded, which soon became famous throughout Europe. (Ref. 13, 14)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

The empire of Karl the Great (Charlemagne) was a theocratic church-state with his functioning as a priest-king and as an emperor. Included in his religious missions had been the conquest and conversion of the Saxons. He regarded the pope as simply his chaplain. (Ref. 15) At the same time, his empire was actually an artificial construction and did not survive him. Nevertheless, in a sense, he saved civilization because through him the Atlantic world re-established contact with the ancient, Mediterranean culture. He did this by arranging for the collecting and copying of books. With the exception of 3 or 4 surviving original antique manuscripts, our whole knowledge of ancient literature has come only through the copying that began under Charlemagne. These copyists also developed the Carolingian script which has survived until today. Their books were works of art and overall splendid masterpieces. (Ref. 16) The emperor died in 814, five years after the realm had been swept by famine. (Ref. 17) The Carolingian Dynasty immediately declined as the empire was divided by his one surviving son among three grandsons - Pepin, Louis and Karl, all of whom died within 8 years. Their successors were weak leaders and many local wars broke out between rulers, nobles and church with resulting recurrent partitions of the empire. Finally by the Treaty of Verdun (843) the original empire was officially divided into three parts, with Lothair keeping the title of emperor and a central area, extending from the Netherlands almost to Naples. Charles the Bald got the western area and Ludwig the eastern area and in this way France and Germany became dissociated. (Ref. 18) It was not originally a difference of race or temperament but a difference of language and tradition. The western branch was assimilated by the country-side Latin, which became French, while the Germanic group had retained their original Germanic tongue. The Franks in north Germany even differed also from the Swabians and south Germans. Ludwig actually was the first king of Germany, but the artificial divisions of the empire were still poorly arranged because they paid no heed to these growing regional differences. The monstrous territory of Lotharingia (French - "Lorraine") was to be disputed between France and Germany well up into the 20th century. The Italian part was also a continued problem area, with subsequent German emperors having to attempt to reconquer the region at frequent intervals for centuries.1

1 The valleys of the Rhine and Meuse were relatively immune from Viking attacks, except for one major one in 863, apparently because Lothar and Lothar II of the middle kingdom, let the Vikings have the estuaries of those rivers. The Danish leader Harald and his nephew Roric were so treated, with Roric getting Dorestadt. (Ref. 19)

NOTE: Add Map 36: Division of Charlegmagne's Empire at Verdun in 843

NOTE: Add Map 36: Division of Charlegmagne's Empire at Verdun in 843

Map taken from Reference 97.

As the old Frankish kingdom disintegrated in the early century, the separate duchies previously present reappeared as independent political units. These were the stem1 duchies of Frisia (Lowlands), Saxony, Franconia (along the Maine), Swabia, Thuringia (between the Weser and Elbe) and Bavaria. These were based originally on ethnic unity and this particularism made unification of Germany forever difficult. (Ref. 20)

In 857 there a serious outbreak of ergotism in which thousands of Germans died, poisoned by their daily rye bread which contained a fungus producing some 20 poisons (including LSD). The disease produced abdominal pain, delirium, gangrene and sometimes death, or alternately it caused an acute inflammation of the skin, driving people to insanity and giving it its common name of "Holy fire". (Ref. 21) The only physicians present were part of the monastic environment and much of their labor was devoted to prayer, laying on of hands, exorcising, use of amulets, holy oil, relics of saints and other elements of supernaturalism rather than to rational procedures. (Ref. 22)

By treaty in 870 Germany was extended from the Rhine to the Elbe. The limits between the Germans and the Slavs generally followed the Elbe between the North Sea and the mountains of Bohemia. Although this line of demarcation did not last for long, it has through the centuries assumed some political, economic and social importance. As noted previously, to the west of the Elbe is old Germany, to the east is new Germany. The latter became the area of the Junkers, with large estates dominating a servile peasantry, with a large Slavic element in the population. A skeleton of imperial power continued even after Ludwig's death. The last of the direct Caroling ian line, Karl (Charles) the Fat, abdicated in 887. Three weak kings filled the next thirty year gap, until the rule was taken over in the next century by the Saxon kings.

AUSTRIA

Charlemagne's "Ostmark", bounded by the rivers Enns, Raab and Drau, with a fortress at Vienna, lasted until about 880, when the Frankish forces were defeated by the Magyars who had occupied Hungary and then moved into Austria. (Ref. 23)

HUNGARY

In the early century Hungary was lightly held by the Bulgar Khanate, but near the end of the century when the Magyars were finally squeezed entirely out of Russia by the Patzinaks (Pechnegi), they swept through the upper Balkans and took over and settled Hungary. The "native" Szekels were few and scattered and offered little resistance. The Magyars were basically a Finnish people who had an infusion of Turkish blood which had been added while they were living on the Don River and were joined by three hordes of the Khazars from the Volga mouth. The Magyars were free horsemen, living in clans and tribes and using slaves taken from among the Slavs. They spoke the Ugric language of the Finno-Ugric group of Uralic languages. Formerly it was erroneously thought that these people were basically Mongolian or Hunnish, but this is not accurate and they came originally from the Ural Mountains area, not farther east. In Asia, they were called Ugri, from their Ugric language and from this has come our word "ogre". (Ref. 24)

CZECHOSLAVAKIA

Like the rest of Central Europe this area was subject to Charlemagne's religious wars early in the century. With fire and sword he preached the Gospel to Saxons, Bohemians and down into Hungary. Later in 870, Sviatopluk, a Moravian prince, united Moravia, Bohemia and Slovakia into the Kingdom of Moravia and held against further German aggression. It was during his reign that Cyril and Methodius brought Christianity of the Byzantine variety to the region. In the last years of the century, however, the German clergy redoubled its efforts and won back Bohemia and Moravia for the Latin Church. (Ref. 25) The Czechs became dominant over all the Bohemian tribes, while Slovakia came under Magyar rule. (Ref. 26, 27)

SWITZERLAND

In this 9th century part of what is now Switzerland was included in Swabia and the rest was part of Transjurane Burgundy. (Ref. 28)

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN

Charlemagne conquered Catalonia in northeastern Spain but otherwise this country remained politically as in the 8th century, about half or less Christian and the remainder Moorish Moslem. The Christian princes lived in the high, barren northern mountains and the Basques remained in the central north by themselves, while the plains of Granada and Andalusia were the home of the Moslems and the Jews. Agricultural poverty and political disunity kept Christian Spain far behind its Moslem rival in the south and its Frank rival in the north.

The Spanish Moslem rulers continued to be the last remnants of the Omayyad house. Hakam I added Mamluk slaves to the royal guard and continued to cruelly suppress all independent intellectual activity. His successor, Abd-er-Rahman II, was more peaceful to his own people and although his armies waged continuous warfare against the Christians, Cordoba attained its greatest splendor. The second university in Europe (Solerno was the first) was formed around the library of Khalif al-Hakim of Cordoba. It is said that he collected 400,000 volumes (equal to about 20,000 modern books) and read them all, making comments on the fly leaves. The mainstream of Greco-Roman learning thus came to Europe through Spain, with commentaries by both Moslem and Jewish scholars. Cordoba had paved streets, perhaps 500,000 inhabitants and 300 mosques. By about A.D. 9002 paper mills had appeared in Spain. In the last half of the century, however, prosperity lessened and there was much turmoil and many local rebellions. (Ref. 29, 30, 31, 32)

NOTE: Map of The Iberian Peninsula

PORTUGAL

As is apparent in the small map above, Portugal was not yet a separate country but part of the province of Leon of Spain, ruled in greatest part by Moors.

FRANCE

Please see the section on GERMANY, page 484, for details of the collapse of Charlemagne's Empire. During the costly civil wars which followed that collapse of the Frank kingdom, the expanding tribes of Scandinavia invaded France in a new "barbarian" wave. All the cities of northern France were sacked again and again. Tours was pillaged five times in the last half of the century and Paris was hit twice and then burned on a third attack. In 859 a Norse fleet entered the Mediterranean and raided towns from the south along the Rhone. The Saracens had already taken Corsica and held most of the French Mediterranean coast through the next century. The result of all these raids and particularly those of the Vikings was a fragmentation of public authority and a great upsurge of feudalism as a means of protection. The peasant as a freeman virtually disappeared and society was polarized between nobles and serfs. In addition, the descendants of the first generations of French agents of the Carolingians were not as loyal as their fathers and tended to identify with the particular interests of their own localities at the expense of the Frankish kingdom. As noted above, however, Charlemagne's Empire did not completely disintegrate until about 887 or 888 when it gave way to a large kingdom of "France" and a smaller kingdom of Province in the south, while the Bretons still held their northwest peninsula. (Ref. 35, 36)2

2  In 845 an attack on Paris was prevented by the payment of 7,000 pounds of silver. In the next 20 years every major river in western Frankia was exploited by one or more Viking fleets. Soon they were based in the Loire and each year moved farther up the valley. This was the main area of Viking activity for 25 years, probably because of the weaknesses and rivalry of Louis' sons, Charles and Louis. In 862 Charles made systematic efforts to fortify at least the heart of his kingdom.  After the death of Charles the Bald in 877 and then his son two years later, there was much political confusion and the Vikings returned with a large army and fleet. At one time 200 ships, loaded with prisoners, returned home to Scandinavia. Those Vikings who settled in Normandy did not speak a Scandinavian language for long and now there is no trace in Norman names. (Ref. 37)

The French language developed in this period. As early as 813 Charlemagne ordered sermons to be preached in lingua romana rustica, acknowledging this new language, which was nascent French. The six cases of classical Latin were merged into two cases, the predominant morphological characteristic of "old French". Twenty-nine years later came the first written text in French, a treaty known as the "Oath of Strasbourg" between Carolingian princes. (Ref. 38) Sometime in this or the preceding century a university was founded at Montpellier and it soon had a rabbinical school of Spanish origin which taught grammar and later medicine. (Ref. 39)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

On the eve of the Viking period, this area was concerned with a growing commerce in coastal markets called "wics", the greatest of which was Dorestad (with others in England), dealing in supplies of furs, skins and walrus tusks. (Ref. 40) In general, the Lowlands can be considered as a part of the Frankish kingdom and France, at this period.

Frisia disappeared and the North Sea was controlled by no one until the Danish chieftains became rulers of this and various large areas of Flanders at the end of the century.3, 4

3 It was later, when the Frankish empire was divided, that defenses were neglected and the Viking raids really started. The Dane Godfred was granted land in the Rhine estuary, to proteCt against other raiders, but Godfred was killed in 885 and afterwards there was very little trace left of the Vikings in the Netherlands. In Belgium a series of circular forts were built along the coast on each side of the Scheldt estuary, probably in the last years of Louis' reign. These defenses may have sufficiently thwarted the Vikings that they were diverted to start their serious attacks on England. (Ref. 41)

4 (Ref. 42)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

Just before the era of the Viking invasions, participating with Dorestad as a "wic" market, was Hamwic, later to become Southampton. Early in the century Offa, of Mercia, sometimes known as "King of the English", bargained and dealt with Charlemagne apparently almost as an equal. But then the Danish Viking attacks began, first on the island of Sheppey in 835, continuing for thirty years of disturbance and destruction. Usually 30 to 300 Danish ships left home in the spring, raided during the summer and returned home to Denmark with the booty before winter. (Ref. 43) After A.D. 835 hardly a year passed in which there was no reference in the Anglo-Saxon chronicle as to Viking attacks on England. (Ref. 44) The year 865 was a turning point when that autumn a great Viking army landed in East Anglia, under Ivor the Boneless, to stay. In the meantime, however, King Egbert of Wessex had united most of the southern kingdoms under his control, including Wessex, the Cornish Welsh and the southern parts of both Mercia and Northumbria. (A.D. 829). After the Danes had taken the middle 2/3 of England by about 898, it remained for King Alfred, the Saxon, successor to Egbert, to finally defeat the Danes and confine them to the northeastern part of the country in an area to be called the "Danelaw". Alfred's victory involved the use of a great fleet to meet the invaders' reinforcements at sea before they could land. Payments of money apparently helped in this confinement, however, and even after their defeat the Danes kept their own customs and laws while living nominally under the English king. Many Danes later moved south and became important in English government and the church. (Ref. 45, 46)5

5 The Vikings raided usually in small bands and were identified by their leaders, such as the armies of Olaf, Sven or Knut, rather than as Norwegians, Danes, etc., although the English called them all "Danes". Actually Norwegians attacked the north and west British Isles while Danes assaulted the southern North Sea and channel coasts. The first attacks were small, involving 3 to 15 ships. Later, when 60 or more ships were involved they probably came from new bases, such as in the Hebrides. In the years after 866 many raiding Scandinavians, faced with better defences on the continent and finding little left to plunder, turned again to England. In 865 they took East Anglia and in 866, taking advantage of a local civil war in Northumbria, they conquered York.  Their army, led by several kings, then took eastern Mercia but was stopped by Alfred at Wessex. The Viking leader, Guthrum, then retired to rule East Anglia. (Ref. 47)

SCOTLAND

Thousands of second generation Anglo-Saxons, now called "English", were driven into Scotland by the Danish invasion and this resulted in a strong influx of Anglo- Saxon blood in the Scottish people. In the meantime, there was a Norse invasion of the islands and the north and west shores of Scotland and the main Pictish army was destroyed along with their last king, Eoghann. Kenneth Mac Alpin, alleged descendant of forty tribal kings, took this opportunity about 842 to unite the Picts and Scots, forming the small mountain kingdom of Alba (Albainn). After that union the Pictish culture disappeared. It is said that Kenneth murdered seven earls of Dalriada, kinsmen who might have laid a claim to his new throne. (Ref. 48, 49)

The Viking raids became a terrifying experience to the people of Scotland, as in other parts of Britain. They called those from Denmark the "Black Gentiles" and those from Norway the "White Gentiles". Between 795 and 806 lona was wasted three times and the loot taken was extensive. But the Norse made settlements, too. Norwegian jarls ruled the Shetlands, Orkneys and the Caithness. Ketil, sent by Norwegian King Harold Fairhair to the Hebrides, established himself as king. In the hills of Galloway, on the north coast of the Solway Firth, the Norse intermarried with the earlier settlers, creating a fiery and quarrelsome people called the Gallgaels. By the end of the century Kenneth Mac Alpin and his successors, a brother, two sons and two grandchildren had died and were apparently buried on Iona. (Ref. 50)

IRELAND

The Vikings raided Ireland and established some temporary Norse kingdoms, including Cork and Dublin, the latter established in 841 by Olaf, a Norwegian prince. This kingdom lasted some three hundred years and served as a base for further Norse raids. In addition to Cork and Dublin - Wicklow, Arklow and Wexford were all Viking towns. Irish monasteries were especially hard hit and destroyed, probably because these were of ten the only real communities and center of food storage. Actually the Irish themselves at- tacked more monasteries than the Vikings ever did. Conmacnoise, on the upper Shannon, was hit by native Irish at least twenty-seven times to the Vikings' eight. Three times it was sacked by Feidlimid mac Crimthainn, abbot-king of Munster, who plundered many of Ireland's greatest monasteries. Knowth, on the east side of the present Irish Republic, on the River Boyne, had become in recent centuries a site of importance, apparently as the royal residence of the Gaelic kings of Northern Brege. (Ref. 51, 52, 53)6

6 They got control of all the islands around Ireland and then made inland raids from those bases. After 847 the Irish began to win some victories and drove them out temporarily. After 850 there were only 5 attacks on churches in the remainder of the century. There were four possible factors in that situation: (1) The Viking bases were susceptible to counter-attack; (2) some churches paid tribute; (3) Frankia offered better opportunities to accumulate wealth; and (4) the Danes first hit Ireland in 851 and there followed some violent conflicts between them and the Norwegians, so that there was little energy left for local devastation. (Ref. 54)

WALES

In Wales, pirate attacks occurred from Normandy until Rhodri the Great drove them off and gave the country a vigorous dynasty.

SCANDINAVIA

How did these Viking people suddenly leap onto the stage of European history to dominate it for some three centuries, when previous to about 800, they had been a rather obscure, somewhat barbaric group? The reasons for their domination at this time are probably several but, at least included, is the fact that these people had developed a mastery of ship-building and had nautical skills. In addition, a population explosion had occurred in their Scandinavian homelands as a result of warmer temperatures than usual (Little Climatic Optimum) with a resulting abundant food supply. Some have speculated that the raids, in part, were in retaliation for Charlemagne's and other Christians' persecution (Ref. 55) At home in Scandinavia there were no striking changes, barring the population increase, to herald the Viking era. The social structure conformed to a norm characteristic of Europe. At the bottom of the scale was the slave (proel3), who might be anyone from a bankrupt local to a prisoner of war. The son of a slave was also a slave. Next in line were the free peasants (karls), not usually entirely free, but doing service to a proprietor.

Some were craftsmen, soldiers or peddlers. The top of the chain was the aristocrat (jarl) or chieftain, who was basically a warrior. During the Viking Age this class began to hold land from the king in a proto-feudal manner. The basic livelihood was from the land farming, cattle, horses, sheep and goats. (Ref. 58)7

7 There were several centers for long distance trade - Kaupang in Vestfold, Norway, Hedeby in Denmark, Birka in Sweden and Trusco and Straraja Ladoga as Swedish centers in Russia. "Cogs" were cargo boats, developed perhaps in this century and they had the characteristic Viking profile, with a sharp angle between the keel and the stem. (Ref. 59)

The raiders, variously called Norsemen, Vikings or Varangians (in Russia), came from many parts of Scandinavia and were strong, ruthless, blond, Teutonic pirates, but in addition to raiding they also colonized and settled. They were organized with a complex law, had the ability to write and had a vigorous artistic style. (Ref. 60, 61) The Atlantic Vikings were chiefly Saxons, Angles and the kindred Danes and Norwegians, who sailed in long, black galleys, making very little use of sails. Their ships were long and slim, built of oak with symmetrical ends, long, true keel and overlapping wood planks with shell-shapes that allowed them to land in very shallow water. Each one did have a sail amidship, a side rudder and as many as 34 pairs of oars. Those Scandinavians who stormed down through Russia were chiefly Swedish. (Ref. 62)

NORWAY

At home in Norway in the first half of the century there were some 31 principalities, some of which were united by Halfdan the Black about 850. Then by 8721 all Norway was conquered and united by Halfdan's son, Harold Fairhair, who reigned with his Queen Gyda for almost 60 years. We have mentioned that walrus ' tusks were in great demand in commerce in this period. A Norwegian, Ottar, sailed clear north to the White Sea in search of this sea animal. Kaupang was a thriving trade town in southern Norway from which Norwegians sailed to Iceland and later to Greenland and America. (Ref. 63)8

8 He encountered the Lapps who gave him much in the way of tribute, including 600 tame reindeer, skins, feathers, whale-bone and ship ropes from whale and seal hides. (Ref. 64)

SWEDEN

Although we have little certain information about the local political organization in Sweden at this 9th century, we do know that because of the prosperous commercial trade from the Arab world and the Russian plains, Sweden had many rich towns like Birka, on an island in the middle of Lake Malar.9

9 One was surely King Olef, but his power was limited and subject to two assemblies in Birka. Kings were military leaders. In 829 once such king asked the German emperor to send a preacher to Birka. In their attacks along the Baltic coast, the Swedes obtained large amounts of silver that was coming up from Transoxiana. (Ref. 65)

DENMARK

Early in the century the Danes seem to have been disorganized and dependent on Sweden, which apparently had the oldest monarchy of the three basic Scandinavian countries, although details are unknown. By the end of the century, however, Denmark had unity of its own under King Gorm and Thyra the Beautiful, his queen. The social order in Denmark was based on family discipline, economic cooperation and religious pagan beliefs. Hedeby, on the neck of the Juteland peninsula, was a thriving trade town and great commercial center. (Ref. 66) A recent reconstruction of a Viking house from Hedeby shows it had been made of wooden staves or wattle, plastered with mud and roofed with reeds or turf. There was a fire hearth in the middle of the main room, with iron cooking pots, upright looms for weaving, soap-stone lamps and bun-shaped smoothing irons for laundry. There was a central authority with public works and apparently extensive financial resources in the village. (Ref. 67)10

10 Frankish royal annals say that the Danish King Godfred removed merchants from Reric, an unidentified Slav territory, to his own lands. This was perhaps part of a fortification program which he built along the River Eider. The early Danish and Norwegian historians have much conflict in their writings of the early Danish political and military affairs and one must be somewhat dubious of all. The Danish historian, Sven Aggesen, makes a great deal of the activities of Queen Thyri, even stating that she conned the German emperor into paying her a vast sum and giving her credit for having the Danevirke built. We have noted previously, however, that this wall was constructed in the preceding century. (Ref. 68)

FINLAND

The Finns were now quite well established in what we now call Finland but the armed Swedish merchants overran them on their way to Russia and they dominated the Finnish peasants throughout this period.

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

Iceland, which may have been touched still earlier by Norse seamen and perhaps Irish, was at least re-discovered by Norwegians and Danes about A.D. 860 and settlers began to migrate there to live by 870, with settlement completed within two generations Wilson (Ref. 69) says that the first three Viking voyages of exploration into the Atlantic were by a Swede, Gardar Svavarson and two Norwegians, Naddod and Fiokki Vilgerdeson. (Ref. 70, 237)11

11 (Ref. 71)

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

The Baltic area also received the raids of the Scandinavian Vikings and the Balts and Baltic Slavs all fell under the rule of a Swedish minority of armed merchants. About the end of the century the Lendizi tribe of Slavs began to dominate the Goplani and formed alliances with still other tribes in a coalition known as the Polani. Excavations at Mietlica, Poland, show iron and glass which were apparently imported in exchange for food stuffs, leather, wool and perhaps salt. This town, near the Notec River and Lake Goplo was probably a minor commercial center. There is evidence of cows, pigs, sheep, horses, domestic chickens, ducks and various wild game. (Ref. 72)

RUSSIA

Early in the century the eastern Slavs pushed eastward from Europe into the woodlands of central Russia, while the nomadic horsemen (Pechnegs and Magyars) rode westward across the southern steppe. (Ref. 73) Northern Russia had the same fate as the Baltic areas in that the Swedes established principalities at Novorod and Kiev in the heart of Slav territory, as well as a Black Sea stronghold at Tmutorokan (A.D. 825), challenging the Khazar trade route from the Don River to Constantinople. This was just south of the Magyar territory and just west of the Khazar Khanate, which still occupied most of the Caucasus. To the north of the Khazars were the Volga Bulgars. The trade route between the various Swedish principalities made a loosely bound commercial and political empire called "Ros" or "Rus", the origin of which is still uncertain. (See page 465). The Swedes (called Varangians in the next century) did not take their women with them and they married locally, thus becoming Slavicized in 1 1/2 centuries, even in the case of the ruling, and princely families. These Rus spoke a Slavic language and part of their culture was Finnish. Excavations at Staraje Ladoga, Kiev and Smolensk have shown some Scandinavian material, but at the first named city (the only place where 9th century levels have been reached) the buildings seem to have been Finnish, rather than Scandinavian. The Swedes were tradesmen, not craftsmen and their presence in Russia was certainly influential, even if not completely dominating. (Ref. 74)12

12 The Karelians also collected furs in the Kola peninsula and even encountered the Norwegian Ottar there. There is little doubt that Scandinavians known as "Rus" established themselves in Russia in the first half of this 9th century, originally with the object of gathering arctic furs and slaves to sell down along the Volga. By the middle of the century Rurik controlled several bases in northern Russia at Izborsk, Beloozero and Novgorod. Then one group, led by Askold and Dir, went south and seized Kiev. They possibly attacked Constantinople in 860. Rurik died about 880 and was succeeded by a kinsman, Oleg, who overthrew Askold and Dir and became Prince of Kiev. He forced adjacent Slavonic tribes to pay tribute. (Ref. 75)

Eventually Kiev became the center of this enterprise and its rulers, the Norse Rurik and his descendants, may be said to be the founders of the Russian state. This Kiev principality embraced nearly all of the eastern Slavonic tribes. This group made six assaults on Constantinople within the next two centuries but in spite of these occasional wars, trade flourished between Kiev and Byzantium. Gradually Russia accepted a Slavonic liturgy and alphabet and the Greek Church. The Russian Slavs were described by the Byzantines as rough and primitive although musical, honest, hospitable, fierce in battle and fond of hot baths. A major offensive against Byzantium in 860 was led by the Varangian Askold with Norse cavalry and probably Slav infantry. Askold's Kievan area then began to assume aspects of a true state. In about 880 Oleg, from the northern area, captured Kiev and first united the Swedish-Slav principalities. (Ref. 76, 77, 78)

In the meantime Patzinak (Pechneg) Turks had migrated from Central Asia to wedge themselves between the Volga Bulgars and the Khazars, squeezing the Magyars from the east as the Oleg Russian state pushed down from the north. They ended the Khazar control of the Russian steppe, although the latter remained important in that area until the next century. (Ref. 79) The Magyars absorbed considerable Turkish blood from the Kavar branch of the Khazars. (Ref. 80)

In the far east of European Russia there was a Swedish market at Bolgar on the middle Volga where Muslims were eager to acquire furs and slaves which the Swedes could get in the northern forests. (Ref. 81) It was thus that after about 882 Russia was subjected to powerful external influences for almost 500 years - first from the Vikings from the north, then from Byzantium with its Christianity and the Arabs with Islam from the south and southeast and finally, as we shall see later, by Mongols from the east.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [281] Gore, Rick, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

3 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

4 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [168] Pei, Mario. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

9 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

13 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

14 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

15 [181] RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

16 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

17 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

18 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

19 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

20 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

21 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

22 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

23 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

24 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

25 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

26 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

27 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

28 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

29 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

30 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

31 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

32 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

33 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

34 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

35 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

36 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

37 [168] Pei, Mario. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

38 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

39 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

40 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

41 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

42 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

43 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

44 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

45 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

46 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

47 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

48 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

49 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

50 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

51 [194] SEVERY, Merle, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

52 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

53 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

54 [79] GREEN, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

55 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

56 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

57 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

58 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

59 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

60 [17] BREFFNY, BRIAN de, (Editor), The Irish World, (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. N.Y., 1977).

61 [79] GREEN, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

62 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

63 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

64 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

65 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

66 [79] GREEN, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

67 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

68 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

69 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

70 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

71 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

72 [244] MALONEY, STEPHANIE J., "The Medieval Fortress of Mietlica in Poland", Archeology 35: 26-32, Mar./Apr. 1982.

73 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

74 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

75 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

76 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

77 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

78.TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

79 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

80 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

81 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

1.  From "Stamm", meaning "tribe"

2.  This date is from The Times Atlas of World History, (Ref. 33) but Thomas (Ref. 34) gives a later date at A.D. 1150

3.  This date is from Heyerdahl (Ref. 56), but McEvedy (Ref. 57) gives the date A.D. 885

Europe: A.D. 901 to 1000

EUROPE (Beginning the age of feudalism, chivalry and the rise of the German monarchy)

Europe's history now became a maze of alliances, treacheries, claims and acquisitions. Historians usually consider the 10th century almost as dark and barbarous as the 7th, but this is only from the political and written word viewpoint. 10th century art was as splendid and technically skilful as that of any other age. (Ref. 1) Heavy iron horse-shoes which allowed hooves to tolerate wet soil had been brought into Europe from the east in the last century and by A.D. 1,000 they were cheap enough to be afforded by peasants; but still lacking an adequate yoke, horses could still not be used for plowing, harrowing nor even heavy hauling. (Ref. 2)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

Cotton reached the Mediterranean world via the Arabs, from India. (Ref. 3)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Byzantium troops took Candia, the northern Cretan city, from the Turks in 961 and the city was ruthlessly sacked. By 1,000 Genoese colonists had appeared on the same island. Other Mediterranean isles remained unmolested in the Byzantium Empire. (Ref. 4, 5)

GREECE

A part of Byzantium

UPPER BALKANS

The Bulgar King Simeon, educated at Constantinople as a monk, was the first of his people to take the title of Czar. He extended his rule to Serbia and the Adriatic Sea and engaged in wars with Constantinople and Greece. The conversion of the Bulgarians to Christianity did not prevent their monarch from aspiring to the throne at Constantinople and he tried to civilize his people with Greek literature. After his death the country was weakened by civil strife and heretics converted about half of the population to pacifism and communism. Serbia recovered its independence in 931 but lost it again to the Bulgarian Samuel in 989.

But we are a little ahead of our story. In 963 the prince of Kiev, with Byzantine help, had annexed the eastern section of Bulgaria, which was in chaos at the time. By 969, however, led by Chichmanides, the western section managed to break away from the Kievan state and form an independent kingdom in the regions later to be known as Macedonia, Albania, the district of Moravia and some regions of Vidin and Sofia. Under King Samuel, Macedonia became the cultural center of the realm. Four years after Samuel's death the Byzantines had annexed his realm, however, and the First Bulgarian Empire had ended. (Ref. 6)

With regard to Serbia, Chaslav tried to unite the various mountain clans of Serbs in mid-century when they were somewhat out from under the Bulgarian yoke, but in the end the attempt was not successful.

ITALY

At the end of the last century there had been considerable confusion concerning who was "king of Italy" and the Holy Roman Emperor. The title changed hands repeatedly among the late Carolingian heirs. Arnulf, illegitimate son of Carloman, grandson of Louis the German, was crowned king of Italy in 894 and then emperor in 896. Louis the Child was elected king by the magnates in 900. Upon his death in 911 Conrad, Duke of Franconia was elected in the same way. Italy was without effective native rule throughout this 10th century. In approximately the same period there were still others claiming to be the emperor. There was Berengar1, grandson of Louis the Pious, Guido of Spoleto, Lambert his son, and Louis of Provence, who was crowned emperor in 915. In the Germanic portion of the old Charlemagne Empire, King Henry I, called the Fowler, began his reign as the first Saxon king, but he avoided ecclesiastical coronation as emperor. But the "Middle Kingdom" of the three-way split, which included northern Italy, was weak and soon fell to the stronger Germany as Otto I the Great, succeeded Henry. After some difficulties with the pope, he was eventually crowned as Holy Roman Emperor in 962 and claimed all central and northern Italy except the papal territory of Rome and the Sabine region. In the papal state confusion had reigned for some time, with the landed aristocracy dominating. Marozia, mistress of Pope Sergius III1, controlled the Curia, imprisoned Pope John XI and took command of Rome until her son, Alberic II, could assume power.

In A.D. 950 the Mediterranean was almost entirely a "Muslim lake" and such trade as there was between east and west was in the hands of the Byzantine cities of Italy, such as Bari, Amalfi, Gaeta and Salerno and of course the independent Venice. Northern Italy was converted into a crisscross of irrigation canals for shipping goods. The Moslems were finally dislodged from their base on the Ligurian coast. (Ref. 8, 9)

The written Italian language can be said to date from A.D. 960. The old Latin final vowels were retained, but only one case.

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

While political fragmentation continued west of the Rhine, in the east a new Saxon Dynasty under Henry I and his son, Otto I the Great, extended influence over the German duchies and conquered the northern kingdom of Italy so that this Ottonian Empire emerged as an equal of Byzantium. By 925 this Saxon Dynasty had regained some territory from France, defeated the Danes and brought Bohemia and Moravia and the Elbe-Oder Slavs under their wing. Otto I married a daughter of Edward2 of England and this dynasty and the related Salic-Frankish Dynasty then ruled Germany until the middle of the 12th century and led through a female branch to the Hohenstaufen emperors to follow that. The social structure was characterized by the political and economic supremacy of the dukes and counts, bishops and abbots, as representatives of the secular and ecclesiastical nobility.

Early in his reign Otto gave most of Bavaria to his brother, Duke Henry. Germany was soon invaded by the Magyars from their bases in Hungary, but Otto finally defeated them at Lechfeld, near Augsburg, in 955, recovering the eastern Bavarian march and laying the foundation for the future Austria. The Magyar leaders were executed. (Ref. 10) It was after these battles that Otto invaded Italy and was finally crowned "Holy Roman Emperor" by Pope John XII, in 962, with central and northern Italy becoming an appanage of the German crown. This predominance of the German monarchy and the virtual eclipse of the French was a striking feature of the 10th century in Europe. Otto, with the help of his brother Bruno, Archbishop of Cologne, began a cultural revival. Late in life he learned to read Latin, but not to speak it. His court literary circle included Irish and English monks and learned Greeks and Italians. He did have some further trouble with Rome but did get his son coronated as Otto II and married to Theophano, daughter of the Greek emperor, Romanus II. Otto II (973-983) took five years to put down a revolt involving the Duke of Bavaria and Boleslav of Bohemia and then had to repulse an attempted Danish invasion. His infant son, Otto III began to rule in 983 under the influence of his brilliant mother, Theophano. As a young adult, in two expeditions to Italy at the end of the century Otto III decapitated Pope Crescentius II, deposed Pope John XVI and installed Pope Sylvester II. He then settled down in Rome, beginning a theatrical restoration of the splendors of the city, and alienating the populace. He died without heirs and was buried at his request beside Charlemagne, at Aachen. (Ref. 11)

AUSTRIA

In the first half of the century this area was controlled chiefly by the Magyars but after their defeat by King Otto in A.D. 955, the southeastern territories were given to Leopold of Babenberg as a reward for his help in crushing a Bavarian revolt. The Babenberg Dynasty then ruled Austria for the next 270 years, although nominally subject to the Holy Roman Emperor. In A.D. 996 the word "Ostarrichi" appeared for the first time in a document of the emperor. The word simply means "eastern realm".

HUNGARY

The Magyars, who dominated and populated Hungary, raided far and wide between A.D. 937 and 955, going over all central Europe and to Orleans and Tours in France, as well as south to Nimes and then down Italy to the tip of the heel, but they did not settle and the disruption was short-lived. (Ref. 12) After they were defeated by the German Otto in 955 they took up Christianity of the Latin variety, as they were afraid of Byzantium. Throughout all, however, they retained their own Turko-Finnic (Magyar) language.

On the political scene, Arpad, who had led the Magyars into Hungary in about 907, was followed eventually by a great grandson, Duke Geisa, who established friendly relations with the Ottonian court and allowed some missionary activity from them. Geisa (also Geza) and his more famous son, Stephen (997-1038), welded the Magyars into a kingdom. Stephen, whose original name was Vajk, before his baptism, married a Bavarian princess and in A.D. 1,001 was crowned by the pope as King Stephen of Hungary3 (Ref. 13)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

The Magyars of Hungary spent the opening years of the century destroying the Empire of Great Moravia. (Ref. 15) The creation of Bohemia (and Poland) by the Premyslid Dynasty was founded on agricultural development, suppression of tribal differences in spite of many independent tribal aristocracies and the influence of the Christian church. When Bohemia was early threatened by the Magyars, Miesko I made his country a vassal of Germany and then Bohemia emerged as a stable unit after 929 under Boleslav of the Premyslid line. (Ref. 16) Boleslav II founded the Bishopric of Prague, which resulted in the final conversion of the entire area, including Poland and Hungary, to Latin Christianity. Later in the century Bohemia became subject to the Polish ruler, as will be noted under EASTERN EUROPE, this chapter.

Lest we get carried away by the noble concept of kings and queens, nobles and bishops in this area of Europe, we should realize that these people were in many respects still fairly primitive and that cannibalism was not unknown. Some bands sold human meat labeled "pork" or "mutton", and this practice was to continue for centuries. (Ref. 17)

SWITZERLAND

Switzerland had no separate existence at this time with its territory split between the domains of the Saxon Dynasty and the rulers of Burgundy. The relatively inaccessible Burgundy area was raided by Vikings, Moslems and finally Magyars, all within about 50 years. (Ref. 18)

NOTE: 38: The Holy Roman Empire And The Norman Kingdom in South Italy

Map taken from Reference 97.

WESTERN EUROPE

At the beginning of this 1 0th century the map of western Europe, in part as a result of Viking raids, was a mosaic of intricate, interlacing counties, communities, principalities and lordships, all part of the feudal system. By the second half of the century the Viking raids had diminished and western Europe recovered rapidly. The heavy mold-board plow came into general use and made a great increase in agriculture possible, as drainage was obtained. Four oxen and long fields were required for this type of plow. While the mer- chants of the other civilization of Eurasia were primarily caterers to the tastes of their social superiors and were accustomed to regulation and taxation from above in the "command" system, which we mentioned at the beginning of the chapter, the aggressive, ruthless and self-reliant ethos of western European merchants was profoundly different. The distinctive characteristics of subsequent western history arise largely from this fact. (Ref. 19, 20)

SPAIN AND PORTUGAL

Garcia, king of Leon, began an expansion eastward, building numerous castles in the area later to be known as Castile. The chiefly Berber armies of the Spanish Omayyad Caliphate periodically devastated the Christian kingdoms of both Leon and Navarre (Basque territory) but the Christian kings paid tribute and thus survived to eventually return the honors and attack the south. When this did occur, one reason was that sheep, which were vital to the economy of northern Spain, had to be taken south to winter pasture in the region held by the Arabs. Famines occurred in 915 and 929, probably due to the disease "rust" on wheat. (Ref. 21, 22)

In the Moslem area of the south the great city of Cordoba had 700 mosques, 3 public baths, a palace with 400 halls and rooms and a library with 400,000 books, as we have previously noted. This famed library continued to draw poets and scholars from all over the Moslem Empire. Abul Kasim, of Cordoba, wrote the first illustrated book of surgery, named Al-Tasrif, which included descriptions of lithotomy, tracheotomy and thyroidectomy, among other procedures. Eastern Islam carried sugar cane to Spain and to Madeira and the Canaries, where later it became an important industry.

The Jews of Cordoba lavished much money to draw men of Jewish law and letters to the city in an attempt to establish a Jewish rebirth politically and culturally. The most famous Jew of this era was the physician and politician, Hasdai ibn Shaprut, famed as a healer who translated medical works of the Greeks into Arabic, but he was also secretary and ambassador to Caliph Abd-er Rahman III (912-961), greatest of the Moslem rulers in Spain. He was the son of a Frankish concubine and a grandson of a Basque princess. Hakam II, caliph from 961 to 976, was overthrown by a bureaucrat first minister, Al Mansur, who became a dictator. After his death, the caliph deteriorated. (Ref. 23, 24, 25)

FRANCE AND NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

For most of this century in the west Frank kingdom of France there was a gradual decrease of royal power and the development of a strong feudalism, chiefly be- cause of the competition for the crown by the Carolingian and Robertian houses. The Carolingians kept control early, although Charles III, ruling from Laon was the last one with truly effective power. Viking, Magyar, and Moslem assaults all contributed to the royal downfall, as Charles III, called Charles the Simple, was unable to expel the northmen from the mouth of the Seine. In 911 he finally had to give the Viking leader, Rollo, all of Normandy in exchange for Rollo's baptism and oath of fealty. Actually the Viking chief took the oath lightly and filled up Normandy with Scandinavian immigrants, chiefly Danes. Although most historians have labeled Rollo (also Rolf) a Norwegian, Lauring (Ref. 26) says that he was of Danish royal family origin. The last of the Carolingian kings, at least in name, was Louis V and then Hugh Capet of the old Robertian House of Burgundy was elected king and started the new Capetian Dynasty in 987. France was now an independent kingdom, no longer subject to the Holy Roman Empire and so recognized by Otto III as a reward for the ceding of Lorraine to the Germans. Capet could speak no German and was the first French-speaking king. Indicative of the situation throughout most of Europe, France, even as a rather privileged country, still suffered 10 general famines in this century. (Ref. 27, 28, 29, 30)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND AND WALES

The 10th century in England saw a rebirth of monastic life and learning and the beginning of native English literature. Alfred's son Edward (899-924) and grandson Athelston (or Ethelstan) (924-939) carried on the fighting on the frontier, making inroads into Daneslaw and finally conquering almost all of it. The last Scandinavian king of York was Eric Bloodaxe, who was expelled in A.D. 954. As the Danelaw was absorbed, the shire system was extended to it with the old Danish boroughs as a nucleus. The old clan organization was superseded by a quasi-feudal system whereby each man had a lord who was responsible for him at law. The great earldoms began to appear. England, as we know it today, began then to take shape as the boundary between England and Scotland was set at Tweed and Edgar was coronated as king of England in Bath in 973. When Edgar was only 15 years of age, however, he was assassinated in order to make way for Aethelred. (Ref. 31, 32)

For awhile the English kings got homage also from the Welsh and there was stability across the island. In about 980, however, the Vikings attacked again and the new Saxon king, Aethelred the Unready, failed to meet the challenge of the professional Viking army under Sweyn Forkbeard. Both Norwegians and Danes were involved in these attacks at the end of the century. Toynbee (Ref. 33) feels that these attacks actually stimulated the development of the definitive kingdom of England (Ref. 34, 35, 36, 37)1

138) says that the Danish forces which invaded Aethelred's England also included men from eastern Sweden. The rulers of Wessex and Mercia defended their territories well

SCOTLAND

King Constantine II, grandson of Kenneth Mac Alpin, along with kings of Strathclyde and Northumbria, accepted vassalage to Athelstan when he was the English king. Constantine then abdicated in favor of his cousin, Malcolm, who became the 8th king of the Alpin line, most of them having been exterminated by murder. Acknowledging that he was the English king's vassal, he was ceded Strathclyde, although he had to terrorize the people there and burn their towns to get their acknowledgment. But Malcolm was also soon dead from poison and six more Alpins were king before the century was over, all meeting violent deaths. (Ref. 39)

IRELAND

The Norwegian kingdom continued to control Dublin and various northern islands and in addition the Vikings established Limerick about A.D. 920. The native Irish remained amazingly quiescent during this century. (Ref. 40)2

2 The new Dublin rulers coveted the greater wealth of Northumbria and they tried to gain control of the Scandinavian Kingdom of York, but without much success. After the middle of the century the Viking leaders played only minor roles in Irish politics. (Ref. 41)

SCANDINAVIA

As this century progressed the Scandinavians pretty well stopped their piracy and replaced it with European trade. In their written language, the runic characters were now generally abandoned as Christianity brought additional literacy to the area through a handful of English and Saxon missionaries. It was only at that time that the various Scandinavian states finally emerged as organized and even aggressive entities. (Ref. 42)

NORWAY

Haakon the Good, educated at the court of England's King Athelston, tried to introduce Christianity in Norway but made no headway and this religion had to wait for Olaf, son of Tryggve, as he became king in 995 and made the country Christian by the sword. Olaf, himself, remained polygamous. Shortly thereafter in A.D. 1,000 Norway was conquered by Sweden and Denmark, in the first of many inter-Scandinavian wars.

In the battle of Svolder, Olaf was defeated while sailing in his great Viking ship with 34 rowing seats4 and in apparent remorse, he jumped into the sea and was drowned. (Ref. 43)

Weaponsmith was one of the most admired skills of all Northmen and a superb group of tools found in a Norwegian weaponsmith's grave of this century attests to the wealth and status of such craftsmanship. Vikings also carved jet, amber and bone into small ornaments. (Ref. 45)

SWEDEN

There is less information available about Sweden in these years than from the other northern countries but we do know that it was gradually united under the kings Uppland towards the end of the century and that Olaf Skotkonung gained control about A.D. 1000, became a Christian and ordered his subjects to do the same, by baptism. (Ref. 46)

DENMARK

King Gorm ruled the major part of Denmark during the first decades of the century, followed by his son Harold Bluetooth. Otto of Germany marched up into Jutlarld and then marched back without actually gaining any land, but Harold saw the possible danger from the Germans and combined the various smaller kingdoms of the Danes under his one rule, advising them to stay at home and protect their homeland. The Viking raider element in the population did not like this advice and they chose Harold's son, Sweyn Forkbeard, as their leader. Father and son battled at sea (as was the custom) with neither winning but Harold was mysteriously killed that night. It was Sweyn, then, who later battled and defeated the Norwegian King Olav Tryggveson at sea. Sweyn sent fleets westward for years, extracting the Danegeld (a type of "protection" racket) from Aethelred of England. (Ref. 47, 48)3

3 The history of Sven Forkbeard's reign is actually obscure. (Ref. 49)

FINLAND

No special change in Finland in this century.

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS: ICELAND AND GREENLAND

By 934 Iceland was as thickly settled as it would be until World War 11, with perhaps 50,000 to 60,000 people and a great literature accumulated. In A.D. 1,000 the Allthing (Parliament) formally adopted Christianity. One-half the people in Iceland were from Bergen, Norway, having fled from the tyranny of Harold Fairhair in the previous century. Sailing from Iceland, but originally from Norway, Bjarno Herjolfsson visited the coast of North America in 985 and a Norwegian colony was established on Greenland by Thorwald and his son Eric the Red of Jaeder, Norway about A.D. 1,000. (Ref. 50)

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

Some six tribes in Poland were finally united early in this period under the domination of the Polani Slavs with Meiszko I as the first historical ruler of the Polish people. The German Otto had previously subdued many Polish dukes, so in order to avoid further conquest by the Germans, Mieszko placed Poland under the Latin pope. In this attachment with Latin Christianity, Poland, Bohemia and Moravia differed from all the southern Slavs. Subsequently Mieszko resisted Otto II's armies and established the Polish border along the line of the Oder River and the Baltic Sea. His daughter married the king of Sweden and then she later married the king of the Danes and was the mother of Canute, of whom we shall hear much more in the next chapter. The chief city of Poland was Gniezno.

Boleslav I, ruling from 992 after Meiszko's death, was one of the founders of Polish greatness, conquering Moravia, part of Silesia and even Cracow. He had an efficient military machine and laid the basis for an good administrative system. He gained further access to the Baltic by conquering eastern Pomerania. (Ref. 51) Around various feudal centers having local princes, artisan villages developed, each dedicated to a single industry, such as making barrels, or gold-smithing, or horse-breeding. Kruszuica was one of these complexes which developed very rapidly. (Ref. 52)

RUSSIA

The Scandinavian merchants were still prominent in the river trade in Russia. Maureen Green (Ref. 53) quotes the Arab historian Ibn Fadlan, writing of the Vikings' arrival on the Volga in 922: "Never had I seen people of more perfect physiques. They are as tall as date palms, have reddish hair and fair skins. Every man carries an axe, a sword and a dagger, and is never seen without them". But he added: "They are the dirtiest of God's creatures.”

The Slavonic tribes about Kiev (the Varangian principality) were loosely united as "Rus" Thomas (Ref . 213) says that the first Grand Duchy of Kiev resembled the East India or South African Companies, only under Viking instead of English lords. Oleg and later Igor fought to the gates of Constantinople and forced various treaties with Byzantium. Igor's son, Svyatoslav, was the first Kievan prince to bear a Slavic rather than a Scandinavian name. Igor's widow, Olga, ruled for their child-son and introduced tax and administrative reforms which struck down the old tribal systems, and in various communities, types of parliaments were established. In addition to the upper classes (the families of princes, bodyguards, courtiers, etc.) and the working class of freemen and the slaves, there now appeared other classes such as traders and artisans and merchants. Illiteracy dropped. Although Olga became a Christian, with ceremonies in Constantinople in 957, Svyatoslav remained a pagan when he took the throne. He led the Rus in plundering the Khazar capital on the Volga but this was not difficult as the formerly war-like Khazars had largely become merchants and farmers. As the Grand Prince Svyatoslav attempted to destroy these peaceful people in 962 and 963 he only opened up the way for the fierce Pechnegs, who then dominated the southern Russian steppe, and who finally killed the Kievan prince.4

4 Ibn Fadlan originally encountered the Rus in Bulgar in 922 and noted the Scandinavian custom of cremating all the dead in boats. Those early Rus were traders offering slave girls and furs, but by the end of the century they also had amber, arrows, swords, falcons, wax, honey and walrus teeth. Additional information about the early Rus rulers is given by Sawyer. (Ref. 54) It was in 907 that Oleg first attacked Constantinople and obtained trading privileges. Igor, who took over in 913, was probably a direct descendant of Rurik. Although Svyatoslav conquered Slavs, Balts and Finns and attacked Bulgars and Khazars he could not beat the Byzantines and was forced to supply them with mercenaries, which were called "Varangians"

After six years of fratricidal war Vladimir Svyatoslavich (980-1015) of Great Novgorod, with the help of Viking warriors, became the ruler of Kiev and the groom of a sister of the Byzantine Emperor Basil II, thus making Russia a daughter of Byzantium. Through this marriage and trading links, the Greek Christian faith made considerable inroads into the Russian state. (Ref. 55, 56, 57, 58)

The original Georgian kingdoms had not reappeared after the Arab withdrawal although in 978 Abasgia re-christened herself "Georgia" in a bid for rekindling of old Georgian patriotism. (Ref. 59)

1 [116] Lamb Harold, Genghis Khan. (Robert M. McBride & Co., New York 1927).

2 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [160] OXENSTIERNA, Eric, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

4 [41] COTTERELL, Arthur, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

5 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

6 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

7 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

7 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

13 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

14 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

17 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

20 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

21 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

22 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

23 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

24 [196] SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

26 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

27 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

28 [160] OXENSTIERNA, Eric, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

29 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

30 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

31 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

32 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

33 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

34 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

35 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

36 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

37 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

38 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

39 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

40 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

41 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

42 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

43 [34] Clark, Sidney, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

44 [34] Clark, Sidney, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

45 [79] Green, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [34] Clark, Sidney, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

48 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

49 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

50 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

51 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

52 [244] MALONEY, STEPHANIE J., "The Medieval Fortress of Mietlica in Poland", Archeology 35: 26-32, Mar./Apr. 1982.

53 [79] Green, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

54 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

55 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

56 [79] Green, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

57 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

58 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

59 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  Marozia was also the mother of Sergius' son John, later Pope John XI. (Ref. 7)

2.  Alfred's son but not designated as Edward I

3.  Stephen was canonized in 1083. (Ref. 14)

4.  This was the ship "Long Serpent", which may have held 200 warriors and rowers and may have been the largest Viking ship ever built. (Ref. 44)

Europe: A.D. 1001 to 1100

EUROPE

The ages of feudalism and chivalry continued, but under most classifications the "Dark Ages" ended toward the end of this century and the true "Middle Ages" began. Three classes existed in the population of most of Europe at this time:

the nobles, who fought
the clergy, who prayed
the peasants, who worked

(Ref. 1) The West slowly began to develop new sources of energy in the form of wind- and water-mills which could produce from 2 to at most 10 horsepower. These undoubtedly played a part in Europe's first age of growth along with the revival of towns and a new rural vigor, all of which marked the beginning of the continent's rise to eminence. (Ref. 2) A growing monetary economy was also evident. The medieval town was a closed city, self sufficient, exclusive, jealously guarding its confines and its citizenship. The defense against plunderers fell to the small group of knights who rode expensive war horses and had been trained since childhood in the use of arms and armor. The latter were produced by specialized craftsmen about which little is known. But this knightly society proved itself capable of far-reaching conquest and colonization, an example of which we shall see in the Norman invasions.

The bloodshed accompanying the violent period of knighthood seemed well accepted by all peoples north of the Alps. (Ref. 3)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

These islands remained essentially under the control of Byzantium although there was some infiltration by Genoese and Turks.

GREECE

In the early part of the century Constantinople and Greece attempted to regain prestige by resuming the Byzantin-Bulgarian Wars and they did succeed in reconquering most of the Balkans. In the middle two-thirds of the century, however, Greece was caught up in the turmoil associated with the multiple changes of control of the Byzantine Empire as the military commanders, the great landowners and the bureaucracy struggled. The year 1081 was a fateful one for the entire region. The Byzantine general Alexius Comnenus revolted with a force of mercenaries, seized Constantinople and plundered it, while at the same time Normans under Robert Guiscard were landing in Epirus at the northwest corner of Greece. While the Normans besieged Durazzo, Alexius bought the support of the Venetians with extensive trade privileges, but even so, Guiscard defeated the emperor in the battle of Pharasalus and went on to finally take Durazzo. Robert and his son, Bohemund, then attacked various sites on the peninsula, including Corfu, Castorias, Larrissa and Nicopolis. Their advance on land was finally halted by guerrilla tactics of the natives, who hated the "Latins" and by Seljuq cavalry hired by the emperor. In 1085 the Normans were also defeated at sea by the combined Byzantine and Venetian fleets. (Ref. 4, 5)

UPPER BALKANS

It was a bad century for the Balkans. First the region was conquered and made a Byzantine province (1018) so that the First Bulgarian Empire came to an end.

Many of the Bulgarian noble families settled in Constantinople and merged with the Greek and Armenian aristocracies. Next, in about 1027, came the Patzinaks, invading from north of the Black Sea. They were finally driven back over the Danube by Byzantine general, Constantine Diogenes. Lastly, near the end of the century there were several catastrophes. In 1083 all of Macedonia up to the Vardar was conquered by the Normans and in 1086 a religious heretic group, the Bogomils, obtained support of the Patzinaks and Cumans and defeated Alexius and a large army. The Cumans then ravaged the entire eastern Balkan region as far as Constantinople itself, when the emperor then bought them off and used them in 1091 to annihilate the Patzinaks in the battle of Leburnion. The final blow to the Balkans at the end of the century was the sacking by the 1st Crusaders, as mentioned at the beginning of this chapter. By this time Hungary had absorbed Croatia and Dalmatia while the Patzinaks were squeezed into a small area of old Bulgaria between Hungary and the Byzantine territory. On the western coast, Byzantine Slav cities like Zara (Zadar), Trau (Trogir) and Regusa (Dubrovnik) carried on a thriving commerce with the Moslem East. Soon Venice was to conquer Dalmatia with a mixed Dalmatian-Venetian culture resulting. (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

ITALY

Through most of the Middle Ages Italy was divided into three spheres of power as follows:

The northern and part of central Italy, notably Tuscany, belonged to the Holy Roman Empire of the German kings and was known as "Regnum Italicum"
Rome and the rest of central Italy was subject to the popes
Southern Italy and Sicily were together as a separate kingdom called "The Two Sicilies". (Ref. 9)

For awhile the Saracens were in control of Sicily, but they were expelled and replaced near the end of the century by the sea-going Normans who roved the area as pirates and robber-captains. Many came south in bands by land through the Rhineland and Italy, proper, also. Robert Guiscard, one of their leaders even crossed the Adriatic and captured the Byzantian stronghold at Durazzo, as noted in a previous paragraph. Overall it took the Normans about 20 years to completely take Byzantine Italy and Sicily, so that it was in 1071 that the last Italian possession fell to these raiders. (Ref. 10, 11) In order to balance the power of the German emperor, the Cluny pope, Hildebrand courted not only the counts of Tuscany and the Lombards of north Italy but even the Norman conquerors in southern Italy.

There was an upsurge of commercial activity in the Mediterranean with the principal carriers being the Italian merchants of Venice, Genoa and other ports. (Ref. 12) Venice compensated for the decline in power of Rome and Ravena by shrewdly accepting a form of Byzantine suzerainty under cover of which it monopolized east-west trade for awhile. During the century, however, Venice did lose some commerce to Milan and other port cities. The main trade objects going from Europe to the East were amber, furs, fish, tallow, honey, wool and wine. (Ref. 13, 14, 15) It so happens that China had a marked increase in maritime business at this same time. Pisa occupied Sardinia in 1050 and Corsica in 1077.

The medical school at Salerno, originally founded by Benedictine monks of Monte Cassino, although it was remarkably free from Christian dogmatism, reached its peak as a traveler from the Near East and India, known as Constantine the African, arrived to transfer the great works of learning from Arabic into Latin. This included the works of Galen. At Salerno, they developed the "Regimen of Health" which was to be disseminated throughout Europe by returning crusaders who visited there for treatment of illnesses and wounds. This formed the basis of much of European medicine until almost the end of the 16th century. The basic premise of this regime was a balanced diet with a parity of the "four humours"- air, fire, water and earth - or the body counterparts - blood, bile, phlegm and black bile. As an example: the elderly and children always suffered from an excess of water/phlegm, so anything cold and most fruit was forbidden1.

CENTRAL EUROPE

Before A.D. 1000 perhaps 4/5 of Europe north of the Alps and Pyrenees was covered by dense forest so that communications and trade was greatly impeded except along the rivers and over certain passes. By A.D. 1000 the population may have reached 30,000,000 and in the next 150 years it increased another 40%. After the cessation of the Viking raids, the economic recovery of Europe was dramatic as new land was cleared, there was an increase in local trade and local "fairs" made their appearance. The use of iron plows may have made food more abundant, although intermittently famines still occurred in France and England. (Ref. 17, 18)

GERMANY

In 1002 Henry of Bavaria, became Henry II, King of all Germany and in 1014 he was crowned Holy Roman Emperor. Conrad II followed in 1024 as the first Salic Frank emperor and he added parts of the Kingdom of Burgundy and present day Switzerland to the empire. Henry III (Salian or Franconian), crowned in 1039, brought the empire to its zenith and Germany was the most prosperous region of Europe. The church was the educator Germany and in essence its administrator, also. Following Henry IlI's death, however, internal troubles developed, including a civil war with the opposition led by Rudolf of Swabia. Henry IV became the German king at age 6 years and his mother Agnes was regent for 9 years. During this time nobles and clerical magnates appropriated the royal resources and sovereign rights freely, dealing the final blow to the monarchy. This was also the time when Pope Gregory VII, Hildebrand, challenged the right of kings to appoint bishops and demanded that the emperor give up this power of appointment. The pope aligned the church with feudal estates and city-states, which led eventually to the collapse of the empire. When Rudolf died some of the civil strife ceased and the Franconian ruler again became temporarily more powerful, although the struggle with the papacy continued with the pope alternately excommunicating the emperor and the emperor appointing an anti-pope - activities which carried well into the next century. (Ref. 19) To return for a moment to Bavaria, in 1070 the now Emperor Henry IV gave the Bavarian fief to Guelph (also Welf) d'Este IV, who began the Guelph Dynasty.

In this century the German drive toward the east took two different lines. There was expansion by colonization along the shores of the Baltic, up the valleys of the Oder and Elbe rivers and down the plains by the Danube. German speaking cities and monasteries were founded throughout these areas with subsequent extension through Bohemia and Silesia. The second method was political expansion. By 1100 the boundary of the empire had been shifted from the Elbe to the Oder and this new territory eventually became the Kingdom of Brandenburg. Frequent uprisings of Slavs prevented significant growth in this century, however. (Ref. 20)

The towns of medieval Germany, as in all Europe, were relatively small and closely surrounded by grain fields. Pigs roamed the streets which were so dirty and muddy that they had to be crossed on stilts in the areas where no wooden bridges were available. At the time of fairs the main streets of Frankfurt were covered with straw or wood shavings. (Ref. 21) (Continue on page 582)

NOTE: Insert Map 39: Europe in 1100

AUSTRIA

German-speaking people were now the major element in the population of Austria. Although under the suzerainty of the German Empire, it was ruled locally by the Babenburg family.

HUNGARY

As the century opened Hungary, under King Stephen, was a member in good standing of the Christian nations. The descendants in the male line of the old Magyar conquerors made up the body of freemen, having special positions and paying taxes only to the church. Slavery continued and the freed slaves and foreigners attained an intermediary position, paying dues to the king for their land. Upon Stephen's death in 1038 there followed a long series of disputes for the throne which lasted for the remainder of the century. This dynastic warfare did much harm to Hungary, not only because of the blood and devastation but because some of the contestants called in foreign help, German and Polish, leading to political degradation and losses of territory. Christianity was retained, although there were some rebellions of the old Magyar pagans against the tithe, one occurring immediately after Stephen's death and the last one in 1063. At the end of the century the throne went to Ladislas I, a powerful protector of the church. Foreign monks, including Germans, French and Italians, did help to raise the cultural standards of the country. As will be noted on the preceding map, by 1100 Hungary controlled Slavonia and Croatia, most of what is modern Romania, the southern part of current Czechoslovakia, the northern part of present day Yugoslovia and Dalmatia. The Hungarians had ready access to the Adriatic Sea. (Ref. 22)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Although Bohemia had most of the gold ore that was available in the West, it could not really capitalize on this potential wealth because of extraneous pressure from the Poles on the north and the Hungarians on the south. Boleslav I, creator of the Polish state, took Prague in 1013, then in 1034 Bretislav I of the same country made himself Duke of Bohemia. Still another Polish king, Boleslav II, conquered Slovakia. Nevertheless, Bohemia did retain a kingship, with Spytihnev ruling from 1055 to 1061, followed by Vratislav II. (Ref. 23) By 1100, however, as we have seen, the Hungarians took over the entire southern part of present day Czechoslovakia.

SWITZERLAND

A portion of present day Switzerland, along with part of the Kingdom of Burgundy, was added to the Salic Frank Empire of Conrad II, early in the century.

WESTERN EUROPE

Western Europe was the chief contributor to the 40% population increase in Europe in this an the first half of the next century. The Cluniac reforms raised the western monasteries beyond their previous level, so that they became oases of peace, learning and stability. (Ref. 24)

SPAIN

Early in this century Jews of wealth and culture everywhere soared to positions of influence in Spain. Samuel ibn Bagrela, skillful Hebrew poet, superb Talmudist, master stylist in Arabic and astute military strategist and political administrator, rose to be vizierate of Granada in the Moslem area from 1030 to 1056. When the tables were turned and anti-Semitism returned, however, he was massacred. (Ref. 25) Thee were four main principalities in Spain, which can be described as follows:

Moslem Spain in the south As previously noted this had been an area of great prosperity and culture, but in this century civil wars between Arabs and Berbers became endemic, with the latter proclaiming independence in the south and west. They were joined soon by some of the eastern seaboard people so that only a shell of the Omayyad Caliphate remained in central Spain and even it collapsed about 1031. The great Al Hakim library (see page 487) was dispersed or destroyed. Several petty dynasties were founded on the ruins of the Omayyad Caliphate but after Alfonso VI of Castile took Seville, Ysuf-ibn-Tashfin, of a new Almoravid power in North Africa, was called to help and he did – inflicting great losses on the Christians at Zalacca in 1086. Ibn-Tashfin then returned to Africa because of pressing problems there, but he was called back again in 1090 an that time he made himself lord of Spain. As is apparent from the remarks above, part of the Moslems' troubles was the presence of so may diverse, often antagonistic factions, such as Yemenites, Syrians, Persians and Berbers. In spite of their difficulties and eventual withdrawal, the Moslems greatly influenced Spanish institutions, character and psychology, culture and language. (Ref. 26, 27, 28)

Castile in the northwest Upon the death of Sanche the Great (originally from Navarre) Ferdinand I of Castile assumed the crown in 1035, conquered Leon in A.D. 1037 and then reconquered a good deal of Portugal from the Moors. Alfonso VI captured Seville and Toledo and installed in son-in-law as the Count of Portugal in 1093.

THE IBERIAN PENINSULA

NOTE: Insert of the Iberian Peninsula 1037 and c.1100

Maps taken from Reference 97.

It was the aggressiveness of Alfonso VI that precipitated the Moslems' call for help to the Almoravids in North Africa with their alleged 150,000 horse and 3,000 foot soldiers. A Castilian, Rodrigo (Ruy) Diaz, called "Cid" by the Moslems, initially was in the service of the Castilian kings, but after trouble with Alfonso VI he was exiled twice and finally went over to serve the Moslem king of Saragosa, which was an independent emirate in northwestern Spain2. He eventually became the ruler of Valencia and remained as such until his death in 1099. Although cruel, selfish and proud, the legends about him resulted in his ultimate acceptance as a national hero. Among other accomplishments, he founded the world's first leprosarium. At that time in Spain a horse cost the equivalent of 50 oxen. French influence began to penetrate into the country through the Cluniac monks and Toledo eventually succeeded Cordoba as the center for translation and exchange of Mediterranean scripts and ideas. (Ref. 29, 30, 31, 32)

Barcelona in the northeast This remained as an independent area.

Aragon and Navarre in the middle north The Basques of Navarre expanded both at the expense of Christian Leon and the Omayyads, but late in the century when the Arab emirate of Seville broke the Berber hold on the south and pushed northward and the new Kingdom of Leon and Castile again expanded on the western border, Navarre was more or less forced to join Aragon for self defense (A.D. 1076) (Ref. 34)

PORTUGAL

Portugal began its separate existence as a fief under Count Henry of Burgundy, when the area was given to him by Alfonso VI after it had been retrieved from the Moors.

FRANCE

Paris, as a city of philosophers, had become the center of learning in Europe.

The University of Paris was an outgrowth of the cathedral school of Notre Dame. At the same time the Jews of the cities of France, as well as Germany, established academies which developed the Ashkenazic Culture. The missionary zeal of the Crusaders in 1096, however, was turned on the Jews and they were killed or banished to ghettos.

In typical feudal style France became divided into seven main principalities, each ruled by counts or dukes and Normandy was one of the greatest of these. The Vikings had become French in speech and laws and as a race of "hybrid vigor"3 these Normans administered the best province in Europe. William the Conqueror, contemporarily called "the Bastard", became chief of the Normans and in the last half of the century invaded England, since by marriage he could be considered heir to the English throne. (Ref. 35, 36) Another province, Burgundy, had as its last independent king, Rudolph II, who made Henry of Bavaria his heir. (Ref. 37)

With initial support of Normandy, the original Capetian line continued with Henri I as official king of France from 1031 to 1060. He was an active ruler, although illiterate, and he married the well-educated, cultured Anna Yaroslavna, daughter of the Duke of Kiev4, possibly with an eye to helping the sliding Capetian fortunes. Upon Henri's death in 1060 Philip I became the monarch over the entire feudal realm, but as was inherent in this organization, his power was chiefly in name only. Philip was excommunicated in 1095 by Pope Urban II for adultery. The idea of knighthood spread in this century from France to the other European areas of England, Germany and Spain. An uninterrupted food supply continued to be a critical issue and France had 26 general famines in this single century. (Ref. 39, 40)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

Upon the break-up of Charlemagne's empire the Netherlands had originally fallen to the Duchy of Lower Lorraine, but this again split into smaller feudal states.

In this and the next two centuries one of the most powerful of these was controlled by the "Count of Holland". (Ref. 41)1, 2

1 (Ref. 42)

2 For two centuries his successors claimed authority over the Hebrides, under overlordship of Norwegian kings. (Ref. 43)

BRITISH ISLES *** (Page 1196)

ENGLAND

In 1002, on the night of St. Brice, King Aethelred made a very foolish move, in that he had all Danes who were outside of Danelaw murdered. Among those killed was the sister of King Sweyn of Denmark. This sealed England's fate and throughout 1003 and 1004 Sweyn remained in England, ravaging and laying waste far and wide. Finally in 1007 Aethelred produced a Danegeld of 36,000 pounds of silver and Sweyn went home, although his agents got another 45,000 pounds later. In about 1013 the Danish king returned to England and took over as monarch, while Aethelred fled to Normandy5. In about 1014, Sweyn either fell off his horse and died from injuries or was murdered. At any rate the English called Aethelred back and the Danish heir, Canute, now 18 years of age, returned to Denmark and prepared an expedition to return to England once again. This second conquest of England was completed when Aethelred's son, Edmund Ironside, died suddenly and Canute was accepted as King of England. This acquisition was chiefly political, as Anglo-Saxon institutions, speech and ways had, in six centuries become deeply rooted. Canute became a Christian and died an Englishman, in 1035. Another son of Aethelred, Edward the Confessor, then assumed the throne to continue the old West Saxon line. A strong Norman party was active at Edward's court, however, and he may actually have promised William of Normandy that he would be his heir. Edward died in 1066 as the last of the Saxon kings and there followed a hassle for political control with Harold, the strongest son of Godwin, a Wessex earl of the Danish party, competing against his brothers for control.

That year of 1066 was an eventful one. It was the year of Halley's comet and it was also the year in which William, Duke of Normandy, landed at Pevensey with a small, highly trained army on September 28th and marched to Hastings, there to eventually fight Harold on a nearby hill on October 14th. Each army had about 5,000 men but the Normans had cavalry and archers, while the Saxons had only foot soldiers6, who were already tired from very recent battles farther north against Harold's brothers, backed by the Norwegian king. Harold was killed in the battle, along with a large number of English land-owning aristocracy and in further battles that followed almost immediately the Saxon land-holding class was virtually wiped out. This land was subsequently parceled out to Norman barons as a new, horse-powered nobility of about 180 families soon controlled Britain under a truly feudal system. Enormous building projects were developed with castles, palaces, monastic establishments, parish churches and private houses. The Domesday Book of 1086 records 5,624 watermills serving some 3,000 settlements south of the Severn and the Trent. (Ref. 45)3

3 (Ref. 47)

In this century England enjoyed a warmer climate than it had had previously and there were now some 38 vineyards in the country. It was also the first time since the era of the Romans that London gained exceptional status as a city. The fact that England now had a monopoly on tin must have helped the economy. The languages of culture were Latin and French, with English regarded as inferior and all positions of power, both in the church and in the state, went to people of French origin, yet the population was 300:1 English, which is to say - Celt, Roman, German and Viking. By the end of the century, among the majority of the people, Middle English began to supersede Old English. England did not fully recover from this Norman invasion until the 19th century, but it was never invaded again. Celt, Gaul, Angle, Saxon, Jute, Dane and Norman all mixed blood with the original native stock to produce the modern English people. (Ref. 48, 49, 50, 51, 52)

It was in 1086 that the famous Domesday Book was compiled on orders from William I to list the assets of landowners for the purpose of taxation. The book listed 25,000 slaves and 110,000 villains (serfs) among the properties. William died after an accident in 1087 while invading a portion of France and he was succeeded for the remainder of the century by his son, William Rufus. (Ref. 53) (Continue on page 588)

SCOTLAND

The mainland of Scotland, apart from Galloway and the far north, was gradually taken over by Scots. The violence surrounding the Scottish kings subsided for awhile at the beginning of this century as Malcolm II ruled for 29 years. He protected his north by marrying a daughter of the Norse Earl of Orkney and then attacked the English in the south. He was defeated and his spearmen ended up with their heads decorating the palisades at Durham. Near the end of his reign, allied with the king of Strathclyde, he burned Northumbria and made his grandson, Duncan, the "King of all Cumbria". But then Malcolm, like so many others, was murdered by his own nobles and Duncan became king (after a few other claimants were killed). Duncan only lasted 6 years before he too was eliminated by the aforementioned Earl of Orkney and Macbeth (made famous by Shakespeare), who then reigned for 17 years. It was a son of Malcolm who finally killed Macbeth, with the help of Northumbrian troops, in the battle of Aberdeen. The victor became Malcolm III, called "Malcolm Canmore the Great Head (1057) and Scotland finally stepped from the Dark Ages.

Life in Scotland in these ages was a cycle of starvation and over-indulgence, temporary peace and wasteful war, drought and flood. Religion was a mixture of pagan myth and Celtic Christianity. People of the lowlands lived in lake houses high on timber piles; in the mountains they had mud huts, dry-stone walls and sod-roofed sheds, huddled about- early monasteries where they retreated when danger threatened. The social system was loosely tribal, a clan system in formation. By the time of Malcolm Canmore, mainland Scotland probably spoke a coalition of Gaelic and Pictish, with the former predominating and gradually replacing also the original Scandinavian language in the north and on the islands. But the Northumbrian rulers of Lothian, in the eastern lowlands, spoke English and this would soon become the language of most of Scotland and its kings, with Gaelic remaining only among the mountain people.

Malcom III Canmore's second wife, Margaret, was a descendant of King Alfred and a grand niece of Edward the Confessor and with her to Scotland came Edgar Atheling, heir to the English throne. The marriage, however, did not prevent Edward from burning Northumbria and it didn't keep William the Conqueror from continuing a terrible slaughter in that province in his turn. Malcolm retaliated with a vicious raid of Cumbria, taking thousands of English to serve as Scottish slaves. In spite of these invasions and counter-invasions, Normanization of Scotland was soon under way, initiated by the gentle guidance of Margaret and the Norman-English who eventually filled her court. Upon Malcolm III's death in 1093, probably by treachery, his brother Donald Bane and his sons, Duncan II and Edgar, finished out the century on the throne. Donald Bane was the last Celtic king of Scotland, because Duncan II and Edgar, only one-half Scot by parentage, were truly Anglo-Saxon in thought and character. (Ref. 54, 55)

IRELAND

Brian Boru (or Boruma) of Munster was an early century leader who promoted the development of roads and forts. In 1014 he defeated the Vikings at Clontarf, although he was killed in the battle. Thereafter some Norse remained in the cities but they no longer dominated the country and soon most withdrew to various Scottish islands, letting Ireland revert to a Celtic culture. Dublin did remain the chief market of the Scandinavians in the west. After Clontarf there followed a short period of revival of art and literature before another era of civil wars started. The next attempt at union was by Diarmat, who became king of Leinster in the 1040s. (Ref. 56)

WALES

In 1039 the Welsh prince, Gruffydd of Gwynedd and Powys, defeatedan encroaching English force and Wales was left alone for nearly 25 years. In 1063, however,

Harold, then heir to the English throne, with the help of his brother Tostig of Northumbria, conquered Wales again by defeating Gruffydd ap Llywelyn. (Ref. 57)

SCANDINAVIA

After conversion to Christianity the restless energy of the Vikings quickly evaporated, although as marine merchants they did expand the Frisian-North Sea traffic in fish, wine, beer, salt and metals and carried these products on into the Atlantic. (Ref. 58, 59)4

4 (Ref. 60)

NORWAY

After the death of Olaf I Trygvesson in A.D. 1000 there was a period of feudal disruption in Norway until Olaf II took control in 1016. This Olaf II, also called Olaf the Big, like his predecessors, tried to convert his subjects to Christianity by savage and bloody means and he was killed in 1028 while fighting against his own rebellious subjects. At about this same time, young King Canute, as monarch of both England and Denmark, also laid claim to the Norwegian throne and was probably encouraged by those Norwegians who were antagonistic to Olaf. The local, on the spot rulers of Norway in the years immediately after Olaf II's death, however, were so inept that the people began to think much more kindly of their dead king and, recalling that at the moment of his death there was an eclipse of the sun, they began to feel that Olaf's God was angry. With the help of English and German missionaries they then became Christians and in the next century even canonized Olaf. In 1035, under Magnus the Good, the Norwegians finally eliminated all Danish claims to their throne, achieving complete independence.5

5 They had found the advantages that Christianity could confer on kings and thus they evangelized ferociously. In spite of that, pagan customs survived in eastern Norway (and parts of Sweden) until late in the century. (Ref. 61)

Harald II Hardrada (Harold Hardruler) came to the throne in 1046 after having spent many years in the Mediterranean serving the East Roman emperor as commander of a mixed Latin and Norwegian force fighting Moslems along the north African coast. He decided to conquer England but was defeated by the English King Harold in 1066 at the battle of Stamford Bridge in September, just before the Norman invaders landed on the English coast. After Hardrada there was another period of confusion with wars of succession and struggles of the aristocracy against the growing powers of the clergy. In spite of these troubles, increasing trade brought prosperity. (Ref. 62, 63, 64, 65)

SWEDEN

In this and the next century Sweden's Christianity relapsed and the Uppsala stronghold of the old Norse gods was again resplendent. Internecine wars were common, particularly between the Goths and the Sveas and some of these were probably precipitated by religious differences.6

6 All were only petty kings or queens, but violent conflicts over territory probably occurred. Tentative figures, based on graves, etc., in Malardalen indicate 4,000 farms and 40,000 people in that area, which was still not over-populated. There was a gradual rising of new land from the ocean, as the sea-level had dropped 5 meters since the 9th century. Production of iron in Sweden reached a peak, perhaps 4,000 kilograms annually. In some areas there were as many as 8 or 9 furnaces and 100 charcoal pits in each square kilometer. The iron was needed for tools, weapons, household equipment and even ships (as rivets, etc.). (Ref. 66)

DENMARK

Upon the death of King Sweyn his son Harald was proclaimed king of Denmark, while another son, Canute, at 18 years of age was supposedly king of England. Even though he had to fight England's Edmund, when the latter died Canute was accepted as king of all England, in reality. Shortly thereafter Harald died in Denmark and Canute suddenly became king there, also, so that he was monarch over a large empire. When he died in 1035, however, this empire deteriorated rapidly. One of Canute's sons, Hardicanute, became king of Denmark but he was not very competent and did not live long anyway. It appears that he was poisoned by a Danish chieftain living on a fine estate on the Thames, in England. At any rate, the Danes then allowed Magnus the Good, the new young king of Norway, to become the Danish monarch also. He made a great name for himself as he personally led a Dano-Norwegian force against some tremendous hordes of Wends who suddenly poured northwards into Jutland. But then Sweyn Estridson (or Sweyn Ulf son), a nephew of Canute the Great and who had been made the earl of Jutland by Magnus, turned against him and these two young men fought year after year for the crown of Denmark. After Magnus was drowned, Sweyn continued to battle the new king of Norway, Harald Hardrada, who also had an eye on Denmark. In the end Sweyn was the victor and then he sent several fleets across the North Sea to England to help the Danish colonists who alleged that they were being suppressed by William the Conqueror. In each instance, however, the commanders of the Danish fleets allowed themselves to be bought off with the old method – payment of Danegeld. The Viking Age came to an end in Denmark during the time of Sweyn Estridson, but the Vikings had brought Christianity back with them from western Europe. (Ref. 67)

Christianity did not have quite the same meaning in Denmark that it did in other parts of Europe. It was felt to be quite natural for noblemen and kings to have any number of mistresses. Sweyn had three or four wives in succession but none of the five sons, who succeeded him in turn, was by any of these lawful wives. But the religion did make some headway and in 1060 three bishoprics were set up in Denmark by the pope. (Ref. 68, 69) One of Sweyn's successor sons was Canute the Holy, a strong-willed man who defended the legal system, clarified taxation, introduced a tax for the benefit of the church (10% of all harvested grain), worked to liberate all slaves and sent to England for relics of St. Alban. His greatest resolve, however, was to reconquer England and for this purpose he assembled a great fleet in the Limfjord, consisting of 60 Norwegian, 600 Flemish and 1200 Danish vessels. But once again William the Conqueror foiled the expedition by sending emissaries with large amounts of money for bribes, and the fleet was disbanded before it could sail. The peasants turned against Canute as he tried to tax them further and they finally murdered him inside his church, allowing his brother Olaf to become king. Crops failed throughout his nine year reign and he was given the name "Olaf Hunger". The crops began to grow again only upon the ascension of his brother Eric in 1095. (Ref. 70)

Recent excavations in Denmark have revealed three distinct types of vessels:

A classic Viking Man-of -war, 90 feet long, carrying 40 to 50 oarsmen and capable of long distance travel. This was undoubtedly the type of vessel used to attack Britain.
A smaller war-ship with only 24 oarsmen.
Domestic deep-sea traders and light fishing boats.

All of these findings would confirm the two types of Viking themes; peaceful and far flung trade and raiding. (Ref. 71)

FINLAND

The still pagan Finns worshiped Ukko, the air god; Tapio, the forest god; and Ahti, the water god.

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

After Iceland had become Christian in 1000 by vote of the Allthing, it was given its own bishopric at Skalholt in 1054. (Ref. 72) Also see NORTH AMERICA, this chapter.7

7 In the Iceland census of 1096 the total was probably about 80,000 but the fully free population was only about 4,500. After that, erosion and volcanic eruptions reduced available resources and the population declined. Those who weren't fully free included tenants, laborers, servants and landless poor. (Ref. 73)

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

In this and the next century Danes and Swedes tried to Christianize Estonia, without success. Pomerania, on the Baltic Coast, although under Poland from about 980 to 1031, thereafter became dependent to Denmark. South of this Boleslav I created the Polish state and then expanded farther south to take Prague in 1033 and make himself Duke of Bohemia shortly thereafter. Bretislav I followed in 1034 and Boleslav II was a great ruler from 1058 to 1079, conquering upper Slovakia and even putting a relative on the Russian throne at Kiev. His own nobles eventually drove him from the Polish throne after he had Bishop Stanilas murdered and had been excommunicated by the pope. Nevertheless, at its peak Poland extended from the Baltic to the Danube and from the Elbe to the Bug, with Russia as a vassal state. (Ref. 74, 75, 76)

RUSSIA

By 1028 there was a revitalization of an Alani people living first south of the Patzinaks and then later south of the conquering Cumans in the Caucasus. (Ref. 77) The Cumans, as noted previously, were part of the Ghuzz7 Turks and they were variously also called Kipchaks and Poloritse and later, when incorporated into the Mongol state of the 13th century, they were known as Tatars or Tartars. The Patzinaks (Pechnegi, Petchenegs) were a tough, nomadic people of the southern Ukraine, who if thirsty simply dismounted, opened their horses' veins with a knife and drank the blood. They often ate the fattest of the horses, slightly warming the meat over a fire. Later in the century they were virtually annihilated by the Emperor Alexius I. (Ref. 78)

In spite of the fact that the extreme south of Russia was held by the semi-barbarous tribes just mentioned, plus some Bulgars and Khazars, the Kievan state reached its zenith at this time with the absorption of the previous Scandinavian invaders and domination of both Slavic blood and speech. Even so, the Kievan Prince Yaroslav married the daughter of the king of Sweden and gave hospitality to the exiled king of Norway. The social organization was aristocratic, the Russian church powerful. After 1054 Russia had to choose in the religious quarrel between Rome and Constantinople and went with the Greek Orthodox Church. In that same year, however, the last powerful ruler of Kiev died and power fell to the Cuman Turks and the Orthodox world became divided in two. Almost all of the Russian princes had been defeated by these migrating Turks, speaking an east Turkic language, who had crossed into the Russian steppe at about 1060. Even though Kiev, itself, was controlled by Poland's Boleslav II after 1067, the Cumans sacked that city in 1093. (Ref. 80, 81)

Farther north, the principalities of Novgorod, Polotsk, Smolensk and Susdal survived and just to the east of the latter, there still remained the Volga Bulgars. There was still not a united country which might be called "Russia". Much of the area was productive, however, and tallow, honey and wax were exported. (Ref. 82)

1 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

7 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

8 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

9 [68] GARRATY, John a. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

10 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

13 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

14 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

15 279. McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

16 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

17 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

18 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

20 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

21 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

22 [126]  MACARTNEY, c.s., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

23 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

24 [113] Kim, h. EDWARDS, "Seoul: Korean Showcase", National Geographic 156: 770, Dec. 1979.

25 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

26 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

27 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

28 [196] SMITH, Rhea Marsh, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

290 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

30 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

31 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

32 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

33 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

34 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

35 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

36 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

37 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

38 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

39 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

40 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

41 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

42 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

43 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

44 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

45 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

46 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

47 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

48 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

49 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

50 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

51 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

52 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

53 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

54 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

55 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

56 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

57 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

58 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

59 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

60 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

61 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

62 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

63 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

64 [95] HEYERDAHL, Thor, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

65 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

66 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

67 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

68 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

69 [66] Fell, Barry, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

70 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

71 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

72 [66] Fell, Barry, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

73 [301] Sawyer p.h., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

74 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

75 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

76 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

77 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

78 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

79 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

80 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

81 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

82 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  These ideas came from Galen (see pages 328,413 and 435), who claimed that his father had lived to be 100 years old because he never ate fruit (Ref. 16)

2.  This transfer of allegiance was within his rights as a free lord in a feudal society (Ref. 33)

3.  A term used by McEvedy (Ref. 38, page 60) referring to the Norman-Frank mixture

4.  Anna brought with her from Kiev the missal on which all subsequent kings of France swore their coronation oaths but none of the Catholic priests could read the Slavonic inscriptions there-on. It was not translated until Peter the Great of Russia visited there in 1717

5.  There is some confusion about these dates in the literature, in that Barry Cunliffe (Ref. 44) says that after a massive Danish landing in 1009, the force moved on to take London, burn Oxford and rampage through East Anglia. Then Sweyn Forkbeard returned to Northumbria, where he was proclaimed king

6.  A different view is given by Thomas (Ref. 46) who says that Harold's men did have horses and used stirrups, but they did not recognize the value of the latter and dismounted to fight, while William's horsemen charged on their mounts

7.  "Ghuzz" is a shortened name for the more proper "Toguz-oghuz". (Ref. 79)

Europe: A.D. 1101 to 1200

EUROPE

After an adequate horse collar was developed at some place and some time in this 12th century, plowing was done with horses, from the Ukraine to Normandy although the Mediterraneans still used oxen and lighter plows. Flax was grown all over Europe throughout the Middle Ages and was used not only for linen clothing but also for linseed oil, sails and cordage. (Ref. 1) The craze for spices was in full swing and the west gave up its precious metals in the difficult Middle East trade, which went on through to the Far East.

NOTE: Insert Map 41. Crusader States c.1140

Fireplaces were now set in walls whereas previously the round hearth in the center of the room had been used for cooking while braziers were used for warmth. The new system was acceptable for cooking but deplorable for heating for many centuries, awaiting technical improvements. Until the beginning of this century European clothing had remained almost identical with that of Roman times; long tunics falling straight to the floor for women and to the knees for men. Now the men's clothes were lengthened but even this change was minimal. The number of water wheels increased and their use was extended from simply grinding grain to iron works and other purposes. The transformation of windmills from the horizontal to the vertical position greatly increased their power and usefulness.

We mentioned in the last chapter that there was an urban renaissance in Europe. It became apparent in this 12th century that at least in many areas, particularly Italy, Flanders and Germany, that the cities were actually superior to the state, leading completely separate lives. (Ref. 2)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Crete remained basically under Byzantine control, although at the end of the century Genoese colonists had located at several points. During the 3rd Crusade Richard the Lion Hearted conquered Cyprus from Byzantium but the Eastern Empire retained control over Rhodes, the Cyclades and most of the other Aegean islands except for a period in the middle of the century when the Normans, under Roger II, temporarily took some areas. (Ref. 3)

GREECE

The Norman, Roger of Sicily, profited by the 2nd Crusade in being able to seize many of the Greek Islands and attacked Athens, Thebes and Corinth. He went down into the Peloponnesus in 1147 and up the Aegean coast in 1185. Constantinople remained a city of splendor, but there were many wars and the Balkans broke free, so that there was eventually little left of the Byzantine Empire except Greece, itself.

UPPER BALKANS

Hungary absorbed Dalmatia and after 1106 Croatia existed also under the Hungarian King Kalman. Secondary to the turmoil of the 1st Crusade the Byzantines did destroy the Patzinaks, who had finally been crowded into a small area just southwest of Hungary, but the territory was immediately taken over by the Cuman Turks. (Ref. 4) In 1124 Hungary's Stephen II was defeated by the temporarily resurgent Byzantine Emperor John II Comnenus, who prevented the Hungarians from keeping control of Dalmatia, Croatia and Serbia at that time. (Ref. 5) The Orthodox Church considered Islam as simply a Christian heresy and felt that there was little to choose between this and the Latin schismatic and often felt that the "Franks" were even more detestable enemies than the Moslems, for they insisted upon substituting their own creed and rites for Orthodoxy, whereas Moslem rulers allowed the Orthodox Church to manage its own affairs, subject only to payment of taxes and recognition of Moslem political supremacy. This fact did much to assure Turkish success in the Upper Balkans and helped to stabilize later Mongol power over the Russian principalities. (Ref. 6) This feeling was often reciprocated by the Western Church. Petrarch, for example, wrote: "The Turks are enemies, but the Greeks are schismatics and worse than enemies"1.

Near the end of the century Bulgaria again broke free from Byzantine rule and then Serbia was able to separate from Bulgaria to found the poverty ridden Serb Kingdom (1180).

ITALY

The north half of Italy remained subject to the German Empire, but the Papal States had some semblance of self-government and Lombardy and Florence retained some local control. Venice continued to be independent while southern Italy and Sicily prospered under the excellent administration of the Normans. The people of the Two Sicilies had a free choice of religion under Roger I Guiscard and then Roger II after 1101. The latter even started a silk industry at Palmermo, bringing silk workers from Greece, after his expeditions there. Frederick Barbarossa entered Rome on his 4th expedition into Italy, in 1167, and enthroned an anti-pope Paschal III, but a pestilence broke out among his troops and he soon withdrew. The end of the predominance of knighthood was foreshadowed when an army of German knights met defeat to charging pikemen of the Lombard League of cities of northern Italy at Legnano in 1176. The League's subsequent military might was completely defensive with town walls and the massed pikemen infantry. (Ref. 8) At the end of the century the German Emperor Henry VI, with the help of Genoa and Pisa, which was then at the height of its power, wrested southern Italy away from Norman control. Genoa may have minted its own gold coins late in this century and other Italian cities soon followed. (Ref. 9, 10)1

1 (Ref. 11)

In the Italian Alps through Lombardy and Piedmont (as well as in Carinthia and Styria of Austria) the Carthusian monks were dominant in the development of pre-modern iron smelting through the use of strong drafts produced by the enormous water power of alpine streams. Then came a method of refining cast iron, by charcoal fire and the addition of scrap iron to produce steel (Ref. 12). In spite of political changes, the medical school at Salerno continued to function on a high level. Even epilepsy and psychoses were given somatic causes and treatment, although their organic bases were still denied by the followers of Galen. Salerno was a cross-roads of European, Arabic and Jewish medicine. Gerard, an Italian scholar of Cremona, went to Toledo, Spain to learn Arabic and by the time of his death in 1187 he had translated 71 Arabic works, most of them medical, including Avicenna's Canon and the works of Rhazes.

CENTRAL EUROPE

In general Europe experienced another warm period during this century, as in the last one. (Ref. 13)

GERMANY

North German cities soon dominated the Baltic trade and new cities were formed father and farther eastward by the pseudo-crusades of the Knights of the Sword and the Teutonic Knights. (Ref . 137). Cultural advances speeded up civilization in the German realms. The first paper mill in Europe opened at Ravensburg. These areas also saw the mining of copper, silver, gold and iron. There were continued emperor - pope struggles with a temporary peace following the Concordant of Worms of 1122 when it was agreed that there would be a divided ceremony of investiture - one spiritual and one lay, thus assuring the concurrence of both pope and emperor in the choice of bishops.

The Salic-Frankish Dynasty ended with the death of Henry V in 1125 and there followed dynastic battles between two great families for control of the empire. These were the Welfs or Geulfs (primarily in Saxony) and the Waiblingens or Ghibellines (from Swabia and southern Germany). (Ref. 14) The latter was the family name of the Hohenstaufen Dynasty2 which will appear frequently in later German history. Under Frederick I (called Lord of Peace or Barbarossa, for his red beard) as Holy Roman Emperor, Germany rose to the leadership of Europe. Frederick at first forbade wars, but then reestablished imperial supremacy of Poland, Bohemia, Hungary and Burgundy, only to meet failure in Italy as the old Lombard cities united with the pope, against him. He led a strong contingent to join Richard of England in the last part of the 3rd Crusade and died on the trip on the peninsula of Asia Minor.

In spite of the empire, most of the old Stem Duchies of Germany continued their own separate ways, pretty much independent of the empire. In Brandenburg the aggressive leaders of the Ascanian Dynasty, such as Albert the Bear, increased the size and power of their state. Settlers were imported and towns were founded. In Bavaria, from the 9th to the 12th century, all the dukes were at the center of the rebellions of the great German princes against the imperial authority. Early in the period Emperor Conrad II had deposed Guelph Henry the Proud and gave Bavaria to the Babenbergs of Austria, but Frederick I restored its autonomy. He soon put Otto of Wittelsbach in charge, however, and that family then ruled Bavaria until the 20th century.

Frederick's son, the future Henry VI, had married the daughter of Roger II of Sicily and after he was crowned emperor in 1190, he proceeded to take over Sicily after a struggle with the Norman anti-king, Tancred of Lecce. The Waiblingen or Hohenstauf en supremacy then extended over all Italy except for the Papal states. Capturing King Richard on his return from the Crusade, Henry used the captivity to make the crown of England a fief of the empire and to extort an enormous ransom.

AUSTRIA

Although Vienna had been partially fortified since Roman times the ramparts were further improved by 1137 and ten years later work was started on the St. Stephens cathedral. In 1156 Austria was given the special status of an hereditary duchy within the Holy Roman Empire, by Frederick I, Barbarossa. This was an era of great prosperity under the leadership of the Babenberg family.

HUNGARY

After Coloman I conquered Damatia from the Venetians in 1102, Hungary had nearly a century of peace, if we do not count a few dynastic fights and lesser border skirmishes. By the end of the century Hungary had doubled her area and increased the population to 2,000,000 people. There was farming and some good sized towns and gold, silver and salt mines. Promotions to the rank of freemen or nobles became less and less and did not keep pace with the growth of the unfree population and so government dwindled to an oligarchy. Further transition to private ownership of land resulted in changes with diminution of clan and crown lands. In 1150 Germans from the Moselle region (Saxons) were called in to help defend Transylvania against Poland and the Greeks and they settled in the Zips and southern Transylvania. At the end of the century Bela III married the daughter of the King of France and Hungary became the most powerful kingdom in southwestern Europe. Educated at Constantinople, Bela introduced Byzantine customs to the Hungarian court. (Ref. 16, 17)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Following the death of Bretislav II the dukedom of Bohemia was obtained for Ladislav I with the help of the German emperor. There were multiple local "kings" all over this area but all were more or less subservient to the German emperor, except in the northern portion which was controlled by the Polish kings. Duke Ottokar I was restored to power in 1197 and strengthened Bohemia, so that it became a real factor in German affairs. (Ref. 18)

SWITZERLAND

This country did not exist independently at this time.

WESTERN EUROPE

"Western Europe had begun its slow climb out of political dislocation and feudal anarchy during the 12th century"3. Although weakened, kings had survived and now, under feudalism they exerted their rights as "liege lords". There was a prolonged population rise beginning about 1100 and lasting for 2 1/2 centuries. (Ref. 19)

SPAIN

The militancy of the Catholic Church in this period of the Crusades was especially noticeable in the Christian part of Spain. Alfonso I of Aragon even named the Templars and Hospitallers heirs to his kingdom. It is ironical then, that this particular period ushered in 200 years of anarchy and civil war between rival Christian kingdoms of the northern sectors. Aragon and Navarre separated in 1134 and the former advanced progressively while the latter shrunk and lost still more territory to Castile at the end of the century. Leon seceded from Castile in 1139; Aragon and Barcelona united in 1140.

NOTE: Insert SPAIN IN 1180

Moslem Spain in the south was taken over by the Berber Almohades (Muwahids) as the older Almoravid Dynasty (Murabit) collapsed in 1145. Muslim Spain made silk, particularly in the great industrial city of Almeria, which at one time had five thousand looms. The Alpujarras Mountains were covered with mulberry trees, essential for the silk worm. The mining of mercury and silver continued to be important Spanish industries and there was a paper factory in Moorish Spain at least by the middle of the century, with the Arabs using rags, wood and straw as the source materials. (Ref. 20, 21)

The greatest man in Spain in this century was a Moslem heretic - the great physician and philosopher, Averroes. He was the first to explain the function of the retina and did some work on immunity. Philosophically, he pleaded for a better understanding between religion and philosophy, stating that symbolically interpreted, the doctrines of religion could be harmonized with the findings of science and philosophy. His importance for the history of ideas lay in his stimulating effect upon Latin Christian theologians. From the late Roman period Aristotle had been curiously disguised by a Neo-Platonic garb but Averroes work abstracted Aristotle from this alien dress and permitted the theologians of Paris to start their revolutions of Christian philosophy from a more or less authentic Aristotelian basis. Another great Arabist physician of this century was Avenzoar (Abu-Marwan ibn-Zohr), born in Seville, the son of a Jewish physician. He condemned astrology and mysticism in medicine and disagreed with some of Galen's teachings. His reports on tracheotomy suggest that he may have done some surgery. The most famous Jewish physician of all in Arabic medicine, however, was Maimonides (Moses ben Maimon), born in Cordoba and a student of Averroes. When the Almohade Dynasty began to harass non-believers, he fled to Morocco and finally to Cairo where he became physician to Sultan Saladin. Translations of his writings into Hebrew and Latin were widely read throughout Christian Europe. Other Jewish physicians who fled Spain at the same time ended up in Salerno and Montpellier where they brought Arabic science and medicine to Christian Europe. (Ref. 22, 23, 24)

Merino sheep had been introduced into Spain from Africa but they were highly sensitive to temperature and while they could graze in the northern highlands in Castile in the summer, they had to be driven far south to Andulusia for winter feeding. When conflicts between the northern Spaniards and the southern Moors became serious, these movements became difficult and ended as one of the provocations firing Spanish determination to drive the "infidels" from the peninsula. (Ref. 25) Slavery thrived on the Iberian peninsula and in the entire Mediterranean world, as Moors, African, Hungarians, Serbians and others were enslaved from one end of the Mediterranean to the other. Christians even enslaved fellow Christians. (Ref. 26)

PORTUGAL

After winning wars against the Moors and Spain, with the help of papal intrigue, the Portuguese became independent from Castile in 1139 and by 1143 had established their separate kingdom under Afonso I of the Burgundian Dynasty. This did not stop the continuing wars with both the Moors and the Castilians, however. (Ref. 27)

FRANCE

With accelerated cathedral building in the 11th and 12th centuries, western Romanesque architecture developed into Gothic. Steep roof s elongated into spires, the cross-grained vaulted roof was introduced, the pointed arch4 displaced the rounded one and there was development and elaboration of windows and stained glass. Craft guilds began to appear all over Europe so that a new class of people now had to be tallied in addition to the nobles, clergy and peasants. France led the way with the development of the fourth class, the bourgeois, or burgesses, who were bakers, merchants, master-craftsmen and the like. But still the whole of the land was owned by a small number of families and landed property was really the sole source of power. The Crusades and later the English wars decimated the nobles of France and divided their possessions. Actually under a series of weak kings, including Louis VI the Fat and Louis VII the Pious, France remained throughout this century a minor and harassed state. England held an area on the continent that was greater than that held by the French king by virtue of the fact that the English throne had passed to the Count of Anjou (the English Henry II), who had married the heiress of Aquitane. Burgundy was chiefly German, Provence was independent and so was Flanders, the area now a part of the Netherlands. Only at the end of the century, in about 1180, did France get a king, Philip II, who was strong enough to begin lifting France to a significant place in Europe and become strong enough to battle Richard I, of England. The marriage of Eleanor of Aquitaine to England's Henry II not only eventually led to the Hundred Years War, but gave overnight prosperity to the Bordeaux wine merchants who became purveyors to the English court. Eventually a 300 ship fleet was built to carry Bordeaux wine to England. (Ref. 28, 29, 30)

NOTE: Insert FRANCE IN 1180

Of 15 universities established in France in the Middle Ages, only two allowed the study of medicine - Montpellier and later the University of Paris. After 1180, Jews and Arabs could be admitted to Montpellier. (Ref. 32)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

We have previously noted that in this century commercial development in Italy took a quantum jump. A secondary commercial center appeared in the Low Countries where the navigable Rhine, Meuse and Scheldt rivers converge. Overland portage routes linked these channels to Italy and exchanges between the two centers occurred regularly at great fairs in Champagne. (Ref. 33) The independent area of Flanders had the great, busy port of Bruges, which was the center of the Hanseatic League, an alliance of merchants from ports all across the North and Baltic seas. It was designed to promote member cooperation against external competition and pirates, to arrange for congenial association of merchants away from home and to protect against fluctuating currencies, defaulting debtors and feudal tools. The League had a detailed Code of Maritime regulations and initially, at least, was an agent of civilization. Merchants of Flanders brought English wool to Flemish weavers and then sold the cloth throughout the north, soon dominating all this north trade. It is unfortunate that eventually the league became an oppressor as well as a defender of rights. (Ref. 34, 35)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

The Thames at London was already bordered by a continuous line of docks for the business of exporting wool, cloth and tin and importing such things as Arabian spices, Chinese silks, Russian furs, and French wines. Iron was mined and this necessitated a revival of coal mining to process the metal. While prior to the Norman conquest all English wool had been taken to Flanders for weaving, now Flemish artisans went to England and taught the English how to use wool, so that it eventually became a foundation of British wealth. Up until the middle of the 12th century Anglo-Saxon (Old English) was the language of England; then Middle English developed. (Ref. 36)

The early kings of this century - Henry I (the last Norman), Stephen and the six month queen, Matilda, were of little consequence to history. Near the middle of the era a six year civil war broke out and as a result Henry II of the Plantagenet line became king (1154). The name Plantagenet comes from "Planta Genesta", the broom, which was the emblem of the house of Henry Fitz-Empress of Angevin. Henry II, as noted above in the discussion of France in this century, married the heiress of Aquitane and thus acquired the Norman Angevin and Aquitanian fiefs on the continent. He became one of England's greatest kings, known for establishing the jurisdiction of the secular courts over the clerical and thus liberating English law from feudal and ecclesiastical limitations. He quarreled with his former friend, Thomas Becket, the archbishop of Canterbury, as the latter began to champion church against crown. Killed by the king's knights, Becket became a martyr and the king lost the people's confidence. Nevertheless, his reign marked the beginning of the English Common Law and the beginnings of trial by jury. Jurymen were witnesses as well as judges of the fact, picked because they were the most likely to know the facts. (Ref. 37, 38)

Near the end of the century, Richard I, son of Henry II and more French than English, became king, fought with Philip of France, lived the life of an adventurer and participated in the 3rd Crusade. Returning from this jaunt to the Near East he was taken prisoner by the Holy Roman Emperor and was finally ransomed at a high price. When Richard, called the Lion-Hearted, died in 1199 he was succeeded by his brother John.

SCOTLAND

There was continued racial and political turmoil in Scotland. After Edgar and Alexander I, David I, another son of Malcolm and Margaret, reigned from 1124 to 1153 and continued the gradual Normanization as an Anglo-Norman aristocracy arose including the Baliols (de Bailleul), Bruces (de Brus), Lindsays and Fitz Alans. These Normans – built timber palisaded towers with fortresses throughout the southern regions and the local people were greatly impressed by the apparent strength of the new rulers. Put to a test by a Celtic revolt from the men of Moray, the Norman horsemen were easy victors and subsequently raided and burned the Moray glens. Battles with English troops also occurred with the loyalties of the new Norman-Scottish aristocracy divided so that the outcomes were only confusing. David founded the city of Edinburgh, giving his friends strips of land on either side of the castle rock. Upon his death there was incessant fighting for years over the succession and stability was not regained until 1165 when David's second son, William I, called "The Lion"5 became king. In 1174 William was captured by the English and for his release, he accepted feudal allegiance to the English crown. (Ref. 39)

IRELAND

Irish-English conflict began in this century when an Irish chieftain, Tiernan O' Rourke, lost his kingdom and wife to a rival and sought aid from Henry II of England. The king sent some Normans from Wales, including Richard Fitz Gilbert de Clare, Fitzgerald, Fitz Henry and Carew, among others, and then even went himself in 1171, calling himself "Lord of Ireland". Norman castles arose at Maynooth, Trim, Carrickfirgus and Dublin, but in the end the Irish absorbed the Normans into Irish culture. As a result, however, the

Irish never again quite trusted the English. Belfast was founded in northern Ireland in 1177 as a castle to command a ford across the Lagan River. (Ref. 40,41)2

2 It starts with an account of Viking attacks of the 9th and 10th centuries and then goes into an heroic saga about 2 Munster kings, Mathgamain and his brother Brian Boru (further described on page 557), from whom the O'Brien kings traced their descent. (Ref. 42)

WALES

The prince of north Wales, Gruffydd ap Cynan, and his sons worked in the first half of the century to rebuild native Welsh power behind the Snowdonian range. Elsewhere Wales had become the home of many of the Norman nobility and they were the Welch-Norman buccaneers sent by the English king to Ireland when an internal dispute there offered an excuse for intervention. Tintern Abbey was founded in the Wye Valley by Cistercian monks in 1131. (Ref. 43)

SCANDINAVIA

Civilization progressed rapidly among these sturdy people. Work was held in honor and great craftsmen developed, particularly in woodworking and shipbuilding. There was wide distribution of the land among a free peasantry. Polygamy was practiced among the wealthy in spite of acknowledgment of Christianity. The great Scandinavian epic poems called the "Edda", with sources from Norway, Iceland and Greenland, appeared at some time between the 8th and this 12 century.3

3 (Ref. 44)

NORWAY

King Sigurd Magnusson, like King Harald before him, took up the fight against Moslem expansion by taking 60 Viking ships to fight in Portugal and Spain and then on to Morocco and the Balearic Islands. He was well received by his Norwegian predecessors (Normans) on Sicily, where Roger II Guiscard was duke. King Sigurd, with the consent of the pope, raised Roger to the rank of king and then proceeded on in 1110 to conquer the fortress Sidon, in Lebanon. The first cardinal to visit Norway was Nicholas, who later became Pope Adrian IV and his visit probably helped to make the Catholic Church the greatest power in Norway at the time. Most of the rest of the century was a period of confusion, marked by wars of succession and by a struggle against the growing power of the clergy. Nevertheless, there was expansion of trade and increasing prosperity. Sverre became king in 1184 and maintained a strong monarchy against both aristocratic and clerical opposition, thanks to support from small landowners. (Ref. 45, 46)4

4 In western Norway two classes of freemen were recognized: the "hauldar", owning inherited land and other men of free descent, farming land not theirs by inheritance. The law of Trondelag recognized these two classes but also a third, lower class of landless freemen. "Mansbot" was an atonement price, the legal value of a man's life and varying according to his class. After a killing, a feud could be averted by paying the "mansbot" to the family, which could be extended to 4th or 5th cousins' Much that has been written about this may be pure fantasy, constructed by later medieval lawyers. Norway had a single king in this century, but his influence did not extend far inland. (Ref. 47)

SWEDEN

King Sverker amalgamated the Sveas and the Goths and was then succeeded by Eric IX Jedvardsson in 1150. Erik restored Christianity and then conquered the heathen Finns, establishing seven-century domination over those people. (Ref. 48, 49)

DENMARK

Cavalry was first used in Denmark in 1134 and this accentuated a feudal tendency as a new class of professional, military nobles appeared. In this period many Danes returned from England where William had started to persecute them and subsequently much Danish building had an English influence. Valdemar (or Waldemar) I, the Great, be came

Danish king in 1157 and gave the country a strong government, as trade increased. Copenhagen was founded as a market outlet by the chief minister, Bishop Absalon. Together the king and this minister wiped out the savage Wends, pirates from the Island of Rugen. Valdemar married two of his daughters to two of Frederick Barbarossa's sons. Absalon although not very scholarly himself, got his clerk, Saxe, to write Denmark's chronicles in Latin. Sweden never had such a chronicle and thus Swedish history is not well documented. (Ref. 50, 51)

FINLAND

It was raiding by the Finns on the Swedish coast which finally provoked the Swedish King Eric IX to retaliate by conquering Finland. He then withdrew most of his troops and left a Bishop Henry to convert the Finns. They promptly killed the missionary, although much later they made redemption by making him a saint. In the meantime, however, they reverted to paganism for another 50 years.

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

Iceland's Mount Hekla volcano erupted in 1104 and again in 1154, devastating farmland for 45 miles around its base. The Scandinavian colonies on Greenland continued throughout this century. (Ref. 52)5

5 Power in Iceland was divided among many chieftains. The early church was not a royal institution, but early bishops were, in fact, chieftains. All chiefs fought for more land and power, but in the meeting of the Allthing once a year the unity of the country was symbolically expressed. This was the century when Icelanders began to compose sagas, first about Norwegian kings and Icelandic bishops, later about the families who were believed to have played prominent parts in the history of the country. Some 300 farms had been established in Greenland by this century. (Ref. 53)

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

When the Cuman invasion ended Russian trade with Constantinople, the exports of tallow, honey, wax and furs were sent via the Baltic to the West and the Baltic ports, already rich with fisheries, became even more important. In these states just south of the Baltic, Christianity came in by means of the German sword, through the Teutonic Knights, although the conversion was not actually official until after 1190. In the meantime, Poland subdued the Pomeranians (1102-1124) and King Boleslav III gained access to the Baltic Sea. He divided his realm into five principalities for his sons, with Cracow as the capital. The great landlords and knights had become well-defined social classes and along with the clergy became ever more powerful. After an eight year reign by Vladislav II (Ladislas), Boleslav IV took over in 1146. He was not a strong ruler and he lost territory to Albert the Bear and Henry the Lion. As far as the Germans were concerned, Poland was only a dukedom and Frederick Barbarossa again invaded Poland in 1157, forcing the submission of "Duke" Boleslav. There followed Mieszko III, who was so despotic that his own nobles drove him out in 1177 and then Casimir II, the Just. (Ref. 54, 55, 56)

RUSSIA

This was the century of the decline and fall of the Kievan realm and according to the historical schema of Toynbee (Ref. 57) it represented the "Time of Troubles" in the Eastern Orthodox Christian Society, Russian Division. Between 1054 and 1224 there were 83 civil wars, 46 invasions of Russia, 16 wars waged by Russian states on others, and 293 princes disputing 64 thrones. (Ref . 49). Kiev, itself, succumbed internally to class warfare and a declining wealth, precipitated by the diversion of trade routes through Mediterranean channels and finally to external force as the Mongols invaded in the next century. The Cumans remained powerful in the south and continually raided until the local people fled north to the forest, emptying the steppe, but increasing the population of the central and northern principalities, including Moscow, which was founded in A.D. 1147, and Novgorod, which built up a far-flung empire far into the arctic. (Ref. 58). Vladimir Monomakh, Prince of Kiev, carried on numerous campaigns against the Cumans and his reign marked the last period of brilliance at Kiev. The Volga Bulgars still held the middle Volga region and prevented Russian expansion eastward. South of the Cumans in the Caucasus there was a large group of Alans and the Kingdom of Georgia. (Ref. 59)

1 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

7 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

13 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

14 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

15 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

16 [126]  MACARTNEY, c.s., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

17 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

18 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

20 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

21 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

22 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

23 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

24 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

25 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

26 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

27 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

28 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

29 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

30 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

31 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

32 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

33 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

34 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

35 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

36 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

37 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

38 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

39 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

40 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

41 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

42 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

43 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

44 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

45 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

46 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

47 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

48 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

49 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

50 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

51 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

52 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

53 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

54 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

55 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

56 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

57 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

58 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

59 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  From A History of the Byzantine Empire, by A.D. Vasiliev, as quoted by McNeill (Ref. 7, page 514n)

2.  Trager (Ref. 15) gives the explanation that "Ghibelline" is an Italian corruption of "Waiblingen" which was the name of the estates on which the Swabian castle "Staufen" was located. This later became Hohenstaufen. "Guelph" is a corruption of the Bavarian family name "Welf"

3.  Quotation from Reference 8 page 124

4.  The pointed arch had been used in Arabic art for 200 years. (Ref. 31)

5.  So-called because of the roaring beast displayed on his standard

Europe: A.D. 1201 to 1300

EUROPE

Although Europe was in great part burning with the Crusade zeal, still the trade and economy was such that one might say that western capitalism was established in this century. The scale of crossbow manufacture, particularly in Barcelona and Genoa, had reached the stage where the supply allowed not only use in the crows nests of fighting ships but also in land battles as well. This further signalled the downfall of horse warfare as suggested by the success of the Catalan Company whose exploits will be told under TURKEY and SOUTHERN EUROPE, in the next chapter. (Ref. 1)1

1 (Ref. 2)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

In 1204 at the close of the 4th Crusade, the Latin Empire of Constantinople controlled the Cyclades under the title of Duchy of the Archipelago, with ruling Italian and Venetian nobles. At the same time, Rhodes was freed from Byzantine control and some areas came under rule of local lords, while others were under Genoa or Nicaea.

By 1282, however, the Seljuq Turks took over the entire island of Rhodes while Venice continued to dominate Crete after the 4th Crusade. When the Hospitallers arrived on Cyprus in 1291, they established sugar cane, which they had brought from Syria. (Ref. 3, 4)

After Constantinople was sacked by the 4th Crusaders, the Byzantine areas, including Greece, were divided into feudal dominions, each ruled by a Latin noble. Most of these on the mainland were French and French became the official language there for a period of 57 years, particularly in the feudal state ruled by the Villeharddouin princes. An unique mixture of French and Hellenistic culture flourished in Morea in the Peloponnese. In 1261 the Byzantine Empire was restored under the Palaeologus Dynasty, but the territory was much reduced and there was little attached glory. Greek art and literature did experience some revival and there were at least two peripheral Greek dynasties - the Greek Empire in Exile at Nicaea in Asia Minor and the Despotate of Epirus on the west shore of the Greek peninsula. The latter had fallen to the Bulgars in a war in 1230 but the Greek-Nicaean empire armies triumphantly re-entered the area in July of 1261.

UPPER BALKANS

The Second Bulgarian Empire emerged after the Crusader sacking of Constantinople, with the Asen Dynasty oscillating in allegiance between the West and the East. Under her greatest king, John Asen II, Bulgaria ruled also Thrace, Macedonia, and for awhile after 1230, also Greek Epirus and Albania. This king was much beloved, even by the Greek population. Finally he broke with Rome and the Bulgarian Church became independent. While Bulgarian territory was at its maximum a Mongol invasion greatly disordered and weakened the state and the leadership of the Balkans moved farther west to the Serbs. Ever since that time, even up until the 20th century, Bulgaria has been striving to regain that once extensive empire which included parts of Yugoslavia, Turkey (old Thrace), Greece (old Macedonia) and Albania. As the Mongols, under Kadan, headed back toward Mongolia in 1241, the Bulgarian King Koloman I paid tribute and accepted Batu as his overlord. (Ref. 5, 6)

The Kingdom of Serbia had been moving toward a high level of civilization in art and music. The kings of the Nemanjic family promulgated enduring laws, founded monasteries and encouraged learning and the visual arts. At the very end of the century, at the peak of development, religious heresies and persecutions began to destroy national unity and made way for an ultimate Turkish victory in the next century. (Ref. 7)

ITALY

In the early part of the century Italy was subjected to repeated German invasions. The Holy Roman Emperor, Otto IV, completed a conquest of southern Italy, in spite of his excommunication by the pope. When Otto was deposed by the German princes in 1211, Frederick II, grandson of both Frederick Barbarossa and the Norman Roger II, was elected king of Germany and he was crowned emperor of the Roman domains in 1220. As he was the monarch of Sicily, he had to divide his time in managing affairs in both Italy and Germany. He often kept court in Sicily and founded the University of Naples and enlarged the medical school at Salerno. Continuing an already established regulation of medicine, Frederick specified that before one could apply for a medical license, he should study logic for three years, medicine and surgery for five years, practice with an experienced physician for one year and then be publicly examined by the masters at Salerno. In Bologna the Dominican friar, Theodoric, pioneered anesthesia, using sponges soaked in opiates applied to the nose. (Ref. 8)

At Frederick II's death in 1250 his empire began to collapse but the great part of Italy was already a mosaic of city-states. Venice was the great trade center of Europe, with pepper, cinnamon, saffron, cloves, ginger, cardamon, medicines and silks coming through there from Constantinople. Genoa, as an enemy of Venice, was also powerful but since part of western Europe had stopped growing grain, Genoa had to use most of its shipping to supply its own people with food. A typical household of ten (with servants) used five and one-half tons of grain per year and a town of 2,000 or 3,000 thus had to have 1,000 to 1,500 tons of grain per annum and this was the produce of 10,000 acres of land. Genoa occasionally cooperated some with the Venetians in bringing in carpets, tapestries and fruits from or through Egypt, but in 1264 the Venetians destroyed the Genoese fleet at Trepani. (Ref. 9, 10, 11, 12)

Attempts to reunify Italy were continued by Frederick II's bastard heir, Manfred, the new King of Sicily, but he found himself at odds with the pope, who offered the Sicilian crown to Edmund, son of Henry III of England. Later, however, the head of the papal state financed the French king's brother, Charles of Anjou, in an attack on Manfred, who was killed in the battle of Benevento in 1266. Charles then tried to develop his own empire in Italy, North Africa and the tip of the southern peninsula of Greece, where there was a remnant of the old Latin Empire. Throughout most of the century the Two Sicilies remained the richest, most advanced and tightly organized state in Europe as it remained under Angevin control. In A.D. 1282, however, Charles and Sicily were conquered by forces from Aragon in Spain1, helped by a local revolt called the Sicilian Vespers, claiming French insolence and cruelty. The end result was that Aragon's Peter III assumed the Sicilian kingship while the Catalan mercenaries went on to Turkey.

Silk production had begun in northern Italy and Milan, a city of 200,000 ruled in this century by the Guelf, Della Torre, was already famous for its metal work. Wool was exported to the East and textile industries were developing rapidly. With respect to this there is an interesting sidelight. Local wool, chiefly from Tuscany, was of poor quality and the best cloth, on which the Tuscan merchants became rich, was bought as raw wool from Spain, Minorca, Africa, or from the Coswolds of England. In this way the shepherds of those far away isles helped to create the fortunes of the Bardi, the Medici and the Frescobaldi, who in turn financed the coming Renaissance. The wool-based wealth of Florence led to the establishment of the great Florentine banking families and the whole apparatus of modern commerce such as trading associations, modern company shares, credit systems and the like. (Ref. 14, 15)2

2 (Ref. 16)

The last half of this century was the period of the famous journeys of the Polo family of Venice. The brothers Nicolo and Maffeo traveled in Asia and China in 1255 and 1256 and made a second journey with Nicolo's son, Marco, beginning in 1271. Marco, after extensive service and traveling for the Mongol Khan in Asia, China, Burma and India, returned to Europe in 1295, only to be imprisoned by the Genoese. On page 753 there is a map showing these travels.

CENTRAL EUROPE

It is clear from the preceding paragraphs that this was the century of the Mongol invasions of Europe. Those nomads from the East were never decisively beaten in Europe but withdrew finally by their own choice. Europeans had ignored the light Asian and the tall slender Arab horses and developed a large, massive, slow breed of their own to carry the heavy armor inherited from Roman times. Thus, they were no match in battle against the invading, nimble horses of Asia. Furthermore the same defect was apparent in the Crusades when the large European horses perished in droves, contributing to the general defeats. (Ref. 17)

GERMANY

After the installation of Otto IV, son of Henry the Lion, as emperor, the empire rapidly lost prestige to France and in effect became a loose confederacy of magnates giving little actual power to the emperor. (Ref. 18) This situation changed somewhat with the ascension of Emperor Frederick II, who, as noted above, was the grandson of Frederick Barbarossa and of King Roger II of Sicily. Frederick had been raised in Palmero as a proud Sicilian, speaking Latin, Greek, Italian, French and Arabic and with a passion for science, astronomy, falconry and ornithology. He felt that Islam was a superior world and he had Moslem mercenaries and a harem. It was he who introduced Arabic numerals and algebra to Christians and he alternately cajoled and fought with the papacy, although he would not allow his own people to deviate from the straight Catholic line and actually helped to promote the Inquisition. Frederick, himself, was a "free-thinker" and some accused him of being more Moslem than Christian. He protected Jews in spite of the pope's orders. Forced to start a Christian Crusade in 1228 he set out against his friend, the Sultan of Egypt (who had just given him a giraffe) and he came back from Egypt with a secret ten year lease on Jerusalem, Bethlehem and Nazareth and tried to take over Rome as his capital. As a result of all this, neither he nor the pope was in a position to help King Bela of Hungary when the Mongols arrived. (Ref. 19)

When Hungary fell to the Mongols, great fear penetrated Germany and it was rumored that the "Tartars" were the lost - tribes of Israel and that Jews were smuggling arms to them, with the result that at several border posts Jewish merchants were indiscriminately slaughtered. Frederick II blamed King Bela for incompetence and held the pope responsible for placing Christians in jeopardy. At Frederick lI's death, the Hohenstaufen line fell and the nobles of Germany further weakened the monarchy and let Germany fall from the leadership of Europe. The imperial administration was in utter ruin by 1268 when the Austrian Habsburg, Rudolph, became emperor. The true "Roman Empire of the German People" never did re-emerge. (Ref. 20, 21) (See "Confederation of the Rhine", map)

In 1230 heathen Prussia was conquered by the Order of Teutonic Knights and in 1237 they also took Kurland, Livland and Estland and began to colonize those districts. In Brandenburg, Berlin was founded in 1240 on the site of an older Slav settlement. Bavaria, at that time, was ruled as several separate fiefs under various members of the Wittelsbach family.

The German people in the 13th century were morally still half pagan and their Christianity was half a cover for territorial robbery in the east. Their manners were crude, the laws chaotic. The Hohenstauf en rule during most of the century was the most brilliant of the medieval civilizations but it was already beginning to decay. Leprosy was on the increase and most cities had hospitals outside the city limits for those patients. The greatest German scholar of the Middle Ages was St. Albert the Great, a Dominican monk, who some believe was on a par with St. Thomas Aquinas. By the end of the century the peasants' lot had improved considerably due to better general economic conditions, more arable land, better markets and trade. It was the city burgher, however, who proved the most dynamic and also the most disruptive element of medieval society. The city became the cradle of a new middle class, a new corporative legal code, a new economic system and a new philosophy of life. Several German city leagues were formed - Rhenish, Swabian and the Hanseatic League. The new economic system was based on money, not on land. (Ref. 22)

AUSTRIA

Another Frederick, the Duke of Austria and the last of the Babenbergs, took advantage of a lull in the Mongols' advance (they were resting across the Danube) to take unoccupied areas of Hungary, although in many areas the Hungarians resisted. When the winter of 1241 came, the Danube froze (an unusual event) and the Mongols crossed over, sacking Gran (now Esztergom) and Buda and then headed for Austria itself, laying waste all lands as far as Wiener Neustadt and their scouts were on the outskirts of Vienna. It was then, in December, 1241 that Ogedai Khan died and the home regime at Karakorum was temporarily run by his wife, Toregene, as regent, until new elections could be held. The invasion of Europe had to be postponed, as the Mongols went back to Mongolia. (Ref. 23) This allowed Frederick to continue his attacks on the Hungarian Magyars but in one of the battles of 1246, he was killed. The Bohemian King Ottocar Premysl then moved in and captured Vienna, Carinthia and Carniola. In 1272 the German princes elected Rudolf of Habsburg as the German king and he promptly reclaimed the Austrian territory from Bohemia and thus both the Habsburgs and Austria made their true entrance on the European stage. It was another 10 years, however, before King Rudolf actually defeated the Bohemians, who had been trying again to seize power. Rudolf then gave both Austria and Styria to his sons. (Ref. 24)

HUNGARY

Hungary's written constitution, "The Golden Seal", dates from 1222. It limited the king's royal powers and was comparable to the English Magna Carta. The royal authority decreased even more with the long reign of a silly king, Andrew II. His brighter son, Bela IV, was trying to recoup the royal influence before the calamity of the Mongol invasion. He had more or less graciously received the Cumans, who were fleeing ahead of the advancing Mongols and he had even taken title as King of the Cumans. The Cuman Kotian and his last 40,000 warriors had sought asylum in Hungary in return for conversion to Christianity. By 1240 the Mongols were ready to move again and within a few weeks southern Russia had been destroyed and the Mongols had reached the Carpathians surrounding Hungary. In the following year the Hungarian campaign began under General Batu. Bela appealed to the pope for aid, but as we noted earlier he was busy defending himself against the Holy Roman Emperor and sent no help. While part of the invading army turned north to take Lithuania and Poland and then wheeled south to enter Hungary from the north, the main Mongol army came straight west through the Carpathian passes while still others came up from the south. Towns were burned, churches pillaged and women raped. The main army came down from the mountains through the snow at 60 miles a day' King Bela fought but his Cuman allies, after some misunderstanding, would not help him and neither would Austria. It followed that with their usual trickery and superior tactics the Mongols soon surrounded Bela's 100,000 men and killed 60,000 of them. This Mongol slaughter and the famine which followed cost Hungary 1/2 of its population. After his defeat King Bela IV fled through the mountains toward Austria but then was taken prisoner by Duke Frederick because of past differences. His freedom cost the Hungarian king all the money he had, the Hungarian crown jewels and three of his western "departments". Only then could Bela and his family travel south to the safety of Croatia. The neighboring Bulgarian King Koloman had also fled to Croatia where he subsequently died of wounds incurred in a brief skirmish with the Mongols as they went through his country. The slaughter in this entire region Europe ended only with the Asiatics' withdrawal at the end of 1241. (Ref. 25)

After the Mongol retreat the country of Hungary was gradually re-peopled in part with Germans, Slovaks, Croats, Vlachs and Russians, although the basic population still remained essentially Magyar. King Bela IV eventually returned with more Cumans and some Romanians and he attempted reconstruction along with the building of forts for defense. Bela's son, Stephen, had married a Cuman princess to cement the Cuman relationship and when Bela died in 1270 the young man reigned as Stephen V for only two years. He was succeeded by Ladislas IV, who rejected western ways and was known as "Ladislas the Cuman". When the barons and bishops passed a law requiring the king to convert his Cumans truly to Christianity, he arrested the papal legate and married two Cuman princesses from the court of Nogai of the Golden Horde in Russia. The Mongol armies returned to Europe in 1285, attacking both Poland and Hungary but the attacks failed due to poor conception and disorganization. Although the countrysides were sacked, the cities held. Ladislas, the last of the Arpad Dynasty, was assassinated in 1290, dying without male issue. (Ref. 26, 27)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

In 1241 when the Mongols came, both Bohemia and Moravia were ruled by Wenceslas I (1230-1253), although subject to the German emperor's control. When the northern Mongol armies went south to join Batu and Subedei after the battle of Leignetz (to be discussed in a later paragraph), they burned and killed to such an extent that later both Moravian and Silesian towns had to be resettled by German immigrants. Certain tax benefits helped to entice them there. (Ref. 28) Subsequently, under Ottocar II (1253-1269), Bohemia had great prosperity with the opening of great silver mines, which made that one of the wealthiest countries of the late Middle Ages. Ottocar even expanded to acquire Austria under his control for a short period. It was fear of this Premysl king that led the German princes to then elect Rudolf of Habsburg as their king. Ottocar ref used to recognize him and the Diet of Regesburg of 1274 therefore declared all of Ottocar's acquisitions void. He was finally defeated and killed in battle with Rudolf on the Marchfield in 1278. The Bohemian throne went to Wenceslas II, a boy of seven, with Otto of arandenburg acting as regent. (Ref. 29)

SWITZERLAND

Although it may not have been clearly defined in previous chapters, the country we now know as Switzerland was originally the home of mixed Celtic, Teutonic and Italic tribes, including the Helvetii, Raeti, Leopontii and Alemanni. Separated by vast mountain ranges, many "cantons" developed in the valleys. The entire area was under control of the Habsburgs until after Rudolf's death in 1291, and the cantons were then caught up in the dynastic strife of the Germans. At that time, three of the forest cantons - Uri, Nidwalden and Schwyz, formed the "Everlasting League" to give mutual aid. Soon other cantons - Lucerne, Zurich and Contance, joined the League and they had the beginnings of the nation of Switzerland.

WESTERN EUROPE

By this time some areas of western Europe had stopped growing grain. France had put its land, in part, into wine growing and elsewhere farmers had turned more to stock-breeding. Another factor was the cheap water transportation of grain from Germany's east along the Baltic to northern and western Europe rather than to the southern areas. There had been a shift from piracy to trade along the Atlantic coast, where Vikings had previously raided. (Ref. 30, 31) The western European population rise continued throughout this century.

SPAIN

In this and the preceding century, Cistercian orders in Galicia in northwest Spain induced peasants to lease church owned waste land for 2% of the capital value, with the leases supposedly to last for three generations. This was to make much trouble later, as we shall see in the chapter on the 17th century. (Ref. 32) Castile, originally a tributary of the kings of Leon, was permanently united to Leon in 1230 and soon controlled more than one-half of the Iberian peninsula. It became a truly monarchial state under Alfonso X (1252-1284), although he soon gave lavish concessions to the nobles and therefore lost some power for the crown. The Cortes appeared as an assembly of nobles allowed to petition the king and, in a sense, to legislate, thus anticipating the English parliament. Sheep became the big crop of that area and by 1300 there were 1,500,000 of these animals in Castile alone. Mental life stirred and six universities were founded, while bull fighting became a common sport. (Ref. 33, 34)

The Kingdom of Navarre remained under French rule from A.D. 1234 to 1316. Even though many Jews had fled southern Spain in the last century, overall the peninsula- still had the largest and most prosperous Jewish population in Europe. Sephardic Judaism included diplomats, tax collectors, physicians, astronomers and translators. Even in the north, however, some troubles were developing in the religious field as the Dominicans began preaching just south of the Pyrenees. On the coast at Barcelona, native sailers, with Jewish money, began an extensive slave trade in Moorish prisoners and that city became a most active Mediterranean port. Ramon Lu II, of this area, was the greatest Spanish intellectual figure of the period - poet, novelist, educator, scientist and traveler.

In the middle east of Spain the Aragon Empire was strengthened by the commercial wealth of Catalonia and Valencia and by 1281 this empire had taken the Balearics and then Sicily, as Peter III defeated Charles of Anjou. Peter's nobles formed the "Union for Liberty", however, and curtailed much of his power. The next king, Alfonso III, had to grant the so-called Magna Charta of Aragon. (Ref. 35)

In Moslem Spain, the Almohades were defeated in 1212 at the battle of Las Navas de Tolosa by the Christians under Alfonso VIII (of Castile) and were soon expelled from most of Spain. Part of the Moslem's troubles derived from the existence of many diverse, often antagonistic factions from many origins, as we have noted previously. By 1278 the Emirate of Granada existed only as a small coastal strip adjacent to Gibralter, while the Kingdom of Castile controlled the remainder of Spain except for Navarre and Aragon. Intermarriages of Spanish and Moors had remained common, at least up until this century, but now the preaching of the Crusades and papal propaganda prepared the Spanish mind for intolerance and later fanaticism. (Ref. 36, 37)

Up until 1291 the Moslems had prevented Christian vessels from going through the strait of Gibralter, but in that year a Genoese sea captain seized control of the strait and thereafter Atlantic and Mediterranean sea routes could be integrated. (Ref. 38)

PORTUGAL

Sancho II, beginning his reign in 1223, was deposed by the pope in 1245 and the throne was taken by his brother, Afonso III. Portugal increased its borders to its modern size and the port of Lisbon became its capital. Under Diniz (1279) one of its best loved and greatest rulers, culture bloomed and Portugese changed from a Galican dialect -to a literary language. The Portugese navy was started and the University of Lisbon was founded in 1290. (Ref. 39, 40)

FRANCE

NOTE: Insert Map: France in A.D. 1259

By the beginning of this century in France, elective monarchy had been replaced by hereditary monarchy. The turning point of the French royalty was the conquest of Normandy in 1204, which meant the destruction of the Angevin or Anglo-Norman Empire on the French side of the English Channel. After 1214 England controlled only Gascony on the continent. Much of Languedoc was obtained by the French king in a campaign against the Albigensian heretics (1209-1229). (Ref. 41) Philip II also finally defeated Otto IV of Germany, thus starting the decline of the Holy Roman Empire and allowing the beginning of strong, present day France. Following Philip came Louis IX, St. Louis, who participated in the Crusades. De Gramont (Ref. 42) says the Crusades were essentially a French affair and partially exhausted the nation's colonial potential. The beginnings of industrialism created an economic revolution with resulting class struggles leading finally to class wars. Peasants carrying religious banners fought against barons and priests alike. Nobility was first conferred by gift in 19270 and generally could be purchased, in this century. (Ref. 43) Nevertheless, this minor economic revolution stimulated the minds and energies of men and was the making of modern Europe.3

3  (Ref. 44)  By the second half of the century powerful Italian firms from Florence, Piacenza, Milan, Rome and Venice were throughout France. These "foreigners" were intelligent, lively, irritating and detested as much as envied. (Ref. 45)

The French language was spoken by the elite abroad before the French nation learned it. Marco Polo wrote the account of his travels in French. Since the time of Hugh Capet (10th century) about half a dozen dialects struggled for preponderance. The Crusade against the Albigensian heretics, for instance, was less a religious struggle than France 's version of a north-south civil war between the langue d'oc (language of the south) and the "langue d'oil" (language of the north). The latter won. (Ref. 46)

The whole of France now used the vertical plane windmill as a source of power. By 1200 Montpellier, on the southern coast, had become the premier medical school of all Europe.

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

The Hanseatic League continued an active existence on the Baltic Sea and their ships were now using a new, true rudder and bowsprit, which allowed better close- hauled sailing. (Ref. 47) Holland, which had been a part of the Frank Kingdom from the 3rd to the 9th centuries, then an area of German feudal fiefs, began to have some unity in this 13th century. The Hague became the capital in 1250 and Amsterdam became a great free port in about 1297. Rotterdam had also began to rise in importance, with increasing trade with England. Hereafter Holland played a large part in the economic world. The Zuider Zee, which was originally a large, shallow lake in a swamp, became swollen with floods in this period and broke through to the North Sea, thereafter to be an arm of the ocean.

In Flanders the textile industry assumed a large scale, semi-capitalistic structure in which thousands of workers produced goods for investors of capital. Modern Belgium came chiefly from this Flanders territory. The people were Flemish, speaking a low German and Walloons, who were a mixture of Germans and French on a Celtic base, speaking a dialect of French. Throughout the Middle Ages they were variously dominated now by the English and now by the French.4

4 (Ref. 48)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

As the century opened King John (Lackland) lost all of the crown's possessions on the continent north of the Loire and got into serious trouble with the pope. To increase his difficulties his nobles insisted on limiting his powers, forcing him to reluctantly sign the Magna Charta, which was to have far reaching and long-lasting effect in the entire English speaking world. That document freed the Church of England from the monarchy, established the principles of Habeas Corpus and trial by jury, increased the power of the purse to Parliament and transformed an absolute monarchy into a limited and constitutional one. When King John died of dysentery in the next year, his nine year old son was crowned as Henry III. As he matured, Henry developed a love of splendor and unfortunately contributed very little to the English nation. His son, Edward I, who became king in 1272, however, was the best of the Plantagenet line. Because he established a Code of Laws, he has been called "the English Justinian" and he also was the foster father of the House of Commons and the first truly English king. He died in a campaign against Scotland.

There were a number of Englishmen of this century whose names live on. There was Stephen Langston, one of the great men of the early century, a builder of rights against royal, baronial and at times ecclesiastical pretensions. And there was Hubert de Burgh, a defender of the monarch but a solid champion of the rights of all Englishmen. It was a period of increased papal demands but these were resisted by Robert Grosseteste, scholar, scientist and saint, who anticipated Wycliff. It was the time of Simon de Montfort, who led the baronial revolt and of Roger Bacon, who described the magnetic needle and reading glasses and predicted such things as the steamship and airplane. He is usually given credit for the invention of gun-powder, although there is no concrete evidence of this and we have noted that the Chinese had it in the 11th century. (Ref. 49)

Cambridge and Oxford universities were founded but all books were in Latin and there were few of these. By the end of the century London was a city of 40,000 people even though England was still 90% rural. There were 8,000,000 sheep in the country, more sheep than people and there was sheep cheese on every table. In spite of this, there were repeated famines throughout the century. Coal was mined at Newcastle for the first time in this period. By the end of the century all Jews had been expelled from England. (Ref. 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55)

SCOTLAND

By this time the Scottish nobility had been largely Normanized. All through the first half of the century there was poverty, war with England and war with Norway over the Hebrides, but Alexander III (A.D. 1249) at last established friendly relations with England and gave Scotland a temporary golden age of prosperity and peace. He had become king at the age of eight, with the actual ruler for the first six years being Walter Camyn, Earl of Menteith. Becoming of age, Alexander tried to buy the Hebrides from King Haakon of Norway but was laughed at and then subjected to an attack on the Firth of Clyde by the Norwegian navy. A great storm destroyed most of that fleet and Haakon had to retreat. Three years later, by the Treaty of Perth, Man and the Western Isles were given to Scotland for a monetary arrangement. (Ref. 56)

At Alexander's death, in the absence of direct male heirs, his granddaughter, Margaret, the Maid of Norway2 became a child queen in 1286, with six guardians to govern in her name. All but one of these were of Norman descent. In 1290 she left Norway for Scotland, only to die on the way, and this paved the way for a great Scottish civil war over the succession with both Robert Bruce and John Balliol contesting. There was chaos for two years until Edward of England put the Norman John Balliol (formerly de Ballieul) on the throne as a vassal puppet for England. When Edward attempted to completely subdue the Scots, as he had previously successfully done with the Welsh, he met fierce resistance led by William Wallace and Robert Bruce, in multiple, bloody battles. Wallace was eventually hung, drawn, beheaded and quartered in the lovely fashion of the English of that day. After humiliating and slaughtering many Scottish people, Edward I even captured his puppet king, John, in 1296, and for 10 years Scotland had no king. Although under British domination, Scotland still remained, in a sense, free and was actually more disposed toward France, a situation which continued intermittently for some 300 years. What had once been forts or fortified villages now became trading burghs, as a mercantile and agricultural economy replaced the ancient pastoral tribalism. Of incidental interest is the fact that leprosy was rampant in Scotland at that time. (Ref. 57, 58)

IRELAND

This was a century of turmoil and destruction for Ireland as the Irish lost their liberty to England as well as suffering repeated famines. The Anglo-Norman sections prospered while the remainder of the country despaired and the cleavage between the two peoples became very marked, a situation which remains in this 20th century. (Ref. 60, 61)

WALES

It was a time of tribal union and bardic poetry in Wales. A national revival was led by Llewelyn, Prince of north Wales, against the English Henry III but there was no great bloodshed until the latter was succeeded by Edward I. He waged war against the Welsh, using the long bow, which the English had available after A.D. 1200. Cavalry was useless in Wales but archers could score with the long shots, loosing five to six arrows in the time required for only one cross-bow shot. After many battles, Wales was finally subdued and made a part of England, in 1281, which is not to say that real peace was obtained. Coal mining records in Wales go back to this 13th century.5

5 (Ref. 62)

SCANDINAVIA

NORWAY

Haakon the Old (1217-1263) ruled ably and generously and brought Iceland, Greenland and the Faeroes temporarily under Norwegian power. This was the era of Snorre Sturlason, who wrote Heimskringla, a history of Norwegian kings which was to become the chief source of early Norwegian history and the prose Edda, about Norse mythology. Haakon V (1299-1319) was the last male of the line of Fairhair. (Ref. 63, 64)

SWEDEN

The Swedish throne was on an elective basis. Earl Birger, a prime minister while his weak brother was actually king, abolished serfdom, established a reign of law, founded Stockholm and started the Folkung Dynasty by putting his son Waldemar on the throne in 1250 and then acting as his regent. He attempted to set up a European type of feudalism, establishing his other sons in quasi-independent duchies. One of these sons, Magnus Ladulos, overthrew Waldemar but continued his father's feudal innovations although family feuding continued. Meanwhile the merchants of Sweden became rich through mining and trade.

Until the middle of the 13th century Sweden had supplied 1/2 of Europe with herring, but then the cities of the Hanseatic League (chiefly German) took over this industry. Fish was always a more important food than meat for millions of people. Cod, haddock, pottock and ling all were preserved primarily by drying, but herring could not be handled this way because it was too oily. It had to be salted. In Scandinavia, such meat as was available was beaten and then exposed to a clear, cool wind, for preservation. (Ref. 65, 66)

DENMARK

Denmark had the largest population of the Scandinavian countries at this time and claimed a part of what is now the Scania province in southern Sweden. The Danes burst into activity at the beginning of this century, winning a brief supremacy in the Baltic trade. Waldemar II the Victorious temporarily conquered northeast Germany and waged three crusades for the church against the heathen Baltic states of Livonia and Estonia, penetrating the Gulf of Finland and making the southern Baltic a Danish "lake". Waldemar is remembered by many because of his marriage to an exiled Bohemian princess, Dagmar, famous in Danish folklore. But the Danes suffered a crippling defeat in the 1220s and the German Baltic towns (later to be called the "Hanse") took over the Baltic and even the North Sea, also shutting out the Flemish by 1275. At a meeting of nobles in 1282 King Eric V was made to sign Denmark's first Royal Charter - the Magna Charta of Den- mark - and the Danehof was established as a national parliament. Eric had to promise to call a national assembly once a year and to cooperate with the nobles. (Ref. 67)

FINLAND

It was a bad century for Finland. There were continued, intermittent beatings by Swedish armies who first conquered and baptized the Tavastians and then forty years later did the same for the Karelians. In the meantime the Principality of Novgorod had seized a large part of Karelia in 1220. (Ref. 68)

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

Iceland remained the most active literary center in the Scandinavian world. The colonies on Greenland also thrived and more will be written about them under NORTH AMERICA, this chapter.

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA (See map in this section of the next chapter)

Lithuanians and Latvians were remnants of the eastern Balts, but all these people had gradually been Slavonized in the 5 or 6 centuries leading up to this 13th. We noted in the discussion above that the Danes conquered and tried to Christianize Livonia and Estonia early in the century. Tallinn, which was a Danish castle, was the Estonian name for the town of Reval, citadel of the Danish king, Waldemar II. Later, German merchants transformed it into a port for the Hanseatic League. The Danes were followed by the German Teutonic Knights along with various crusaders, monks, and Knights of the Sword, offering either conversion to Christianity or decapitation. They forged continually eastward almost completely exterminating the pagan Prussians and thinning out the Livonians. Teutonic orders were established in Riga as early as 1201, causing the disintegration of the Curonians and Semigallians, who were two of some eleven separate, Prussian tribes. The Lithuanians, alone, resisted the Teutonic Knights and absorbed the Knights of the Sword, so that in a sense they protected the Russians. Written history of the Balts begins only at that point, as the Lithuanians consolidated themselves into a powerful state. Various Lithuanian tribes were first united about the middle of the century under Mindaugas. He was baptized a Christian in 1251 but after he and his two sons were assassinated in 1263, the people reverted to paganism. All Balts worshiped a goddess of fate, Laima, closely connected to the sun but they also had multiple demi-gods and goddesses. After they finally became Christianized permanently the Lithuanians became chiefly Roman Catholic while the Latvians became divided between Catholicism and Lutheranism. (Ref. 69)

At the beginning of the century in a period of some German civil wars, the Danish king also seized Holstein, Mechlenburg, Pomerania and the cities of Lubeck, Hamburg and Bremen, but after 1220, Frederick II defeated Denmark and reconquered these lands, thereafter redoubling the efforts to colonize them. An abundance of grain from the Baltic region helped to supply famine areas in the rest of northern Europe and barley malt allowed a large brewing industry to develop in Hamburg and adjacent areas. (Ref. 70) In this entire northern zone along the Baltic it was difficult to keep farm animals alive through the hard winters and there were long periods when no fresh meat or fish could be had, so there was much salting of meat - chiefly pork and fish - and herring was the most important in the salt fish trade. One could buy 20 pounds of meat for 5 cents, but then had to use 2 more for 2 pounds of salt, plus some peppercorns, cloves, etc., for the preservation. In all medieval cooking something had to be used to absorb the salt - bread crumbs, grain, spices, etc. in the form of sauces. (Ref. 71)

There were still some nine separate principalities in Poland under four dukedoms.

In 1241 the northern prong of the invading Mongols defeated both the Poles and the Teutonic Knights. The Mongols had sent only two tumens to take Lithuania and Poland with an aim to draw the northern European armies away from Hungary, but the Polish armies, under Vladimir, the Palatine of Sandomir and Cracow were no match for them and Cracow was abandoned on their approach and burned by the invaders. King Boleslav fled with his family and treasures to Hungary. The Mongol generals, Baidar and Kadan, met at Breslau, the capital of Silesia, where the citizens had already burned their own city and retired into a citadel. A final battle developed at Liegnitz (now known as Legnica) where the invaders met a 25,000 man army assembled by Henry of Silesia, many untrained and ill-equipped, contingents from Oppeln and Moravia, similarly poorly prepared, conscripts from Great Poland and detachments of the Knights Templar from France and the Hospitallers. The Mongols won and after the battle they cut an ear from each dead enemy's body and sent nine large sacks of them to General Batu, as a present. Although some European historians refer to Liegnitz as a Polish victory, this is untrue and due to misunderstandings encountered in translating oriental characters and reports. (Ref. 72)

After the invasion and the Mongol withdrawal the Germans immigrated into Poland, giving a strong admixture of the German language, laws and blood. At the same time Poland welcomed thousands of Jews fleeing from pogroms in Germany. At the end of the century Poland united with Bohemia to form a single country- under King Wenceslas II of Bohemia.

RUSSIA

"The Mongol invasion was perhaps the most traumatic event in Russian history."3 After smashing the central Asian Khwarizm, the first wave of Mongols, led by generals Jebe4 and Subedei, sent a corps to reconnoiter southern Russia in 1221, delivering crushing defeats to Georgians, Alans, Cumans and south Russian princes. (Ref. 73) This was not easily done, however. The main Mongol force crossed the Caucasus mountains in the winter with some difficulty and descended the north slope to find a Cuman army of 50,000 men, led by the sons of Khan Kotian, awaiting them. With the Cumans were Bulgars, Khazars and Alans (descendants of the Scythians). Bribed by the wily Mongols with gold and horses, the Cumans retreated in the night, leaving their allies to be slaughtered by the Asians. The latter then simply followed the Cumans and massacred them just north of the Sea of Azov, in 1222. (Ref. 74, 75) While Subedei was defeating those Cumans, Jebe rode west to the Don River. It is of interest that while on the shores of the Sea of Azov, Subedei came across some Venetians, who discovered that the Mongols rode with fine silk under their light weight armor and carried physicians, diplomats and interpreters with them and had an Armenian bishop and merchants who were already printing cheap Bibles and selling them to the locals. All this impressed the Venetians who then offered themselves as spies in the west. To seal this new alliance, Subedei raized the Genoese trading station at Sudak.

Rejoining Jebe on the Don, Subedei recruited 5,000 Brodniki (nomad fishermen on the lower Don) as mercenaries and then proceeded to the Dniester where his troops patrolled for several months, while his Mandarin scholars made maps of southern Russia and organized all information from their intelligence sources. Their reconnaissance then complete, they started eastward to go home. As they did so, however, spies brought in word that around and behind them the remnants of the Cumans had accumulated a new army, including forces from various Russian principalities. Greatly outnumbered, the Mongols could have easily outrun the combined armies, but they had also promised the Great Khan Genghis that they would destroy the Volga Bulgars enroute home, so they had to delay the oncoming Russians and Cumans by leaving some 1,000 men as a rear-guard on the Dniepner, under the command of Hamabek. In due time these men did their delaying job but were all killed, down to the last man. At the River Kalka the main Mongol army allowed the speeding, spread-out enemies to catch up with them and using their usual guile and splitting tactics, the Asians soon demolished the entire foe. Besides the thousands who went in backward flight, there were 40,000 Russians dead, including 6 princes and 70 nobles, all defeated by less than 18,000 Mongols and 5,000 Brodniki. This was in A.D. 1223. A little later, joined by another son of Genghis named Jochi and 10,000 reinforcements, they did strike the upper Volga and defeated the Kama Bulgars before moving on east into Asia. (Ref. 78)

Fifteen years after that initial reconnaissance, the Mongols returned but there were two main obstacles to be overcome before entering European Russia. The first was still Bulgar, at the junction of the Kama and Volga rivers, which had grown rich with the fur trade. Slavs and Finns had been imported to work for the Bulgars, but the Mongols were not particular and killed all of Bulgar's 50,000 inhabitants. The city has never been rebuilt and the Bulgar state became a Mongol vassal. The second obstacle was a rejuvenated Cuman Kipchak group in the forests at the lower Volga, all of whom were slaughtered by the generals Manku and Budjek. (Ref. 79) Thus, as the Asians came into Russia they systematically eliminated in sequence the Volga Bulgars (1237), the great Principality of Vladimer (1238), the Cumans and Alans (1239) and finally the south Russian principalities. The army then split into two prongs to enter central Europe. (Ref. 80)

To go back for a moment, plans had begun for this attack in 1236, with several corps of Chinese and Persian engineers, 20,000 conscripts and 50,000 experienced soldiers of the Mongol army which included no less than ten princes. At the beginning of the winter of 1237 generals Batu and Subedei had an army of 120,000 men ready to cross the frozen Volga and enter Russia, proper. As they drove into the center of that country there developed a reign of true terror. There was mass murder and destruction, then multitudes of prisoners and booty, with the targets including Moscow, Vladimir, Dimitrov, Tver, Rostov and Yaroslav among others. With the spring thaw, Batu stopped 60 miles short of Novgorod and turned back south to join Subedei. Although thus spared at the moment, Novgorod had to beat off repeated attacks of Germans and Swedes. The hero of these latter victories was Alexander Nevsky, Prince of Novgorod, who defeated the Teutonic Knights and saved the identity of north Russia. The story is that Nevsky lured the invading Germans onto the frozen surface of Lake Peipus, which broke beneath the weight of their horses and armor. (Ref. 81) To continue to elude Mongol devastation, however, Nevsky soon had to begin to pay continued tribute to the Asians and recognize their overlordship. (Ref. 82, 83)

During the summer of 1239 the Mongols rested in the western Ukraine while fresh herds of horses were brought in from Mongolia. In the following winter all surrounding nomad nations were taken and plundered. Prisoners of Cumans, Circassians and Alans almost outnumbered their Mongol captors and most were sold into slavery, chiefly to the new sultan of Egypt to augment his Turkoman army. By 1240 the completion of the Russian invasion was initiated with the destruction of Cherigov and then Kiev. From there it was on to Poland and Hungary as detailed in the paragraphs above on CENTRAL EUROPE and the SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA.

After the Mongols withdrew from Europe upon the death of the Great Khan, life in Russia was reduced to a barbarous level and to add insult to injury, the Mongols left power- ful revenue collecting agents and a pattern of ruthless terror and efficient extortion. (Ref. 84) Batu went back to Sarai on the Volga, 60 miles south of Astrakhan, where his brother, Sinkur, had been left in command. Here Batu established his capital and remained to organize a new empire. Subedei and the other princes went back to Mongolia. Sarai was soon to be a capital which rivalled Karakorum, itself, and Batu's empire subsequently became known as the "Golden Horde". When Batu died in 1258, his brother Berke, a Moslem, took control and started a type of civil war against another Mongolian army headed by Hulegu, in the mid-east. Thus the great Mongol domain began to fragment. Many of Berke's soldiers were Mamluks up from Egypt. At the end of the century Berke and his successor, Mangu-Temur, granted high estates to their noyans (commanders) and reinforced the feudalism that was to paralyze Russia for the next 600 years. (Ref. 85) In the final divisions, the Khanate of the Golden Horde included western and southern Russia; the Khanate of the White Horde occupied the area about the Aral Sea; and the Cheibanid Khanate (from Khan Cheiban) was located north of the White Horde. (Ref. 86)

The Mongols had made peace with the Russian Church, protected her property and personnel and in return the church preached submission to the Asians. The church became immensely rich while the people, as a whole, remained beaten, humbled, stagnant and poor. Kiev never recovered sufficiently to resume leadership and control passed from the Ukraine to "Great Russia" around Moscow and the upper Volga. The first chapter of Russian statehood, characterized by a blend of Norse politics and Byzantine religious and cultural influence, had come to an end. (Ref. 87)

1 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

4 [86] HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

5 [72] GIBBONS, Boyd, "The Bulgarians", National Geographic 158: 91, July, 1980.

6 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

7 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF Life, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

8 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [125]  Lyons, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

10 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

11 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

14 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

16 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

17 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

18 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

19 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

20 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

21 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

22 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

23 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

24 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF Life, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

25 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

26 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

27 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

28 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

29 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

30 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

31 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

32 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

33 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

34 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

35 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

36 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

37 [196] Smith, Rhea Marsh, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

38 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

39 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

40 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

41 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

42 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

43 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

44 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

45 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

46 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

47 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

48 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

49 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

50 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

51 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

52 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

53 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

54 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

55 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

56 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

57 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

58 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

59 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

60 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

61 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

62 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

63 [34] Clark, Sidney, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

64 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

65 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

66 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

67 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

68 [89] HEARN, MAXWELL, "An Ancient Chinese Army rises from Underground Sentinel duty", Smithsonian, Nov. 1979, page 39.

69 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

70 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

71 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

72 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

73 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

74 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

75 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

76 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

77 [87] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, The World of the Past. (Two volumes). (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1927.

78 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

79 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

80 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

81 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

82 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

83 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

84 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

85 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

86 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

87 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

1.  These were the famous mercenary Forces of the Catalan Company, who destroyed an army of chiefly French knights, using crossbows. (Ref. 13)

2.  Alexander had managed to marry his daughter, Margaret, to Eric, son of King Magnus of Norway, and this child was their offspring. (Ref. 59)

3.  Quotation from Times Atlas of World History, (Ref. 76), page 114

4.  Another authority, Lamb (Ref. 77), spells this name "Chepe")

Europe: A.D. 1301 to 1400

EUROPE

Early in this century Europe, as a whole, experienced some extremely heavy rains and hard, severe winters in an otherwise warm period. Gunpowder was in use in Flanders, Germany, Italy and Moslem Spain early in the century and then in France and England in the second half. (Ref. 1, 2) Near the end of the century blast furnaces were developed, first in Germany and/or the Netherlands, but soon used also in France. Water powered bellows promoted these furnaces which then produced cast iron and "steeled" iron for the first time in Europe. Larger, stouter ships were now available which could sail as safely in winter as summer, making possible a still greater commercial web all around the continent. Bills of exchange and credit facilitated this commerce. From this time on European allowance for the private accumulation of relatively large amounts of capital made the fundamental superiority of this region over the rest of the civilized world. (Ref. 3, 4)

The aggressiveness of Christian Knighthood which had sent Germans to the Gulf of Finland, Crusaders to Jerusalem and attackers against the Moslems in southern Spain and Italy, came to a slow-down, as the basic foodstuffs for their support could no longer keep up the pace. The mold-board plow was not efficient in arid parts of Spain and in the cold of northern and eastern Europe. (Ref. 5)

The Black Death (plague) killed perhaps 1/3 of the population of Europe. Pope Clement VI gave a score of 42,866,486 dead, but this may be a mild exaggeration. (Ref. 6) Crop failures and the severe winters had already hit northern Europe and depopulation had begun. Then in 1346 a Mongol prince laid siege to Caffe in the Crimea. His army came down with plague and he withdrew, but the disease had entered the city and from there it spread by ship throughout the Mediterranean and ere long to northern and western Europe. The initial shock of A.D. 1346 was so severe that it spread not only by flea bite, but also from person to person by inhalation of droplets from coughing patients. Such lung infections were 100% fatal and the overall mortality rate probably was 60 to 70% of those infected. (Ref. 7) In this same period, western Europe and Germany had economic depression, prolonged and devastating wars (England and France) and political fragmentation (Germany). After recurrent plague epidemics of the 1360s and 1370s there were widespread manpower shortages in central and western Europe. In contrast, there was a rise and consolidation of powerful states in eastern Europe and there were far flung results from the mass production of paper. (Ref. 8)

Cookery for the average European remained, as in the past, prosaic at best. Alleged feasts at courts consisted chiefly of gorging on meats and wine and were rare events not available to the common man. There was a great change in costumes. Men's clothes were shortened and their tunics became form-fitting, never to return to robes, while women's bodices became more close-fitting and cut with large décolleté. (Ref. 9)

SOUTHERN EUROPE (See map on page 660)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The islands close to the eastern shore were involved in some of the Crusade adventures and in this century Rhodes was taken by the Knights Hospitalers. Most of the other islands were dominated by Venice. Cyprus was worst hit by the Black Death in 1347. (Ref. 10, 11, 12)

GREECE

After the murder of their leader, Roger de Flor (see TURKEY, page 659), the Catalan Company raided through the Balkans and down into Greece, setting up their own dynasty in Athens in 1311. As the Serbian Empire grew, most of northern Greece became part of the Serbian Principalities, while the Despotate of the Morea (Peloponnesus) passed from the Latin French, who had controlled it in the last century, first to some Aragonese and then to some free-booters from Navarre. Most of the Aegean islands were controlled by Venice. Although corrupt and frail, the Byzantine state was competent enough administratively to stand as somewhat of a bulwark against the spread of Islam and by the end of the century was making some inroads back into control of part of Greece.

The Turks of the Ottoman Empire, however, settled the question in 1389 by overwhelming the Serbian chivalry at the battle of Kossovo and as the Serbian Empire shriveled, most of Greece went to the Ottoman sultanate. A few Latin states remained in the west and Venice held on to the southern tip of Morea. (Ref. 13, 14)

UPPER BALKANS

The mercenary Catalan Company laid waste to Thrace and Macedonia between 1305 and 1311 but otherwise the early 14th century saw the peak of progress for all the Slavic peoples in this region. Serbia, under Stephen Dushan, Czar of the Serbs and Greeks, had a parliament of nobles and coded laws and a magnificent period of art. (Ref. 15) Militarily the Serbs conquered Bosnia, Albania, Macedonia and Thessally and put an end to Bulgar power until Dushan's death, when the empire fell apart. Then Bosnia (west central Yugoslavia), which came under Hungarian rule after 1328, became independent in 1353 and had a short period of glory. Croatia, on the coast, and Slavonia were both under Hungarian rule. The Latin-speaking Wallachians and Moldavians, inhabiting modern Romania, were first mentioned at the beginning of this century. Although they later claimed to be descendants of Roman colonists of the 2nd century, this is improbable.

Almost certainly the Vlachs came from the western Balkans and only migrated into Romania as the nomads abandoned it in the late 13th and early 14th centuries. Wallachia was under Hungarian suzerainty until 1369, then independent until 1389 when it became an Ottoman tributary. Moldavia became independent in 1365 but fell under Lithuanian control in 1399. Bulgaria, under John Alexander, had its last great age. (Ref. 16, 17)

The expansion of the Ottomans during the reigns of- Orklan and Murad I (1316-1389) was actually due to the action of semi-independent Turkish marcher lords, but with the a ascension of Bayezid I in 1389, the conquest speeded up, with the absorption of Bulgaria and the reduction of Serbia to vassal status. Some of the Serbian Christians even helped the Turks in their conquest and more of ten than not Greek, Serb and Bulgarian peasants welcomed the conquerors as liberators from the oppression of Christian, rural aristocrats. The final test of strength between the heirs of the Serbian Nemanjic family leadership and the Ottomans came at Kosovo Polje in 1389, with the former meeting complete defeat. One of the effects of the Ottoman expansion was the conversion to the Moslem faith of bright young Christian boys who were taken to Moslem schools and their family memories purged, to the end that they were forged into a corps of fearless and devoted followers of the Turkish regime. Some were used as pages and administrative aides while others were put in regiments of the guards, forming the famous Janissaries, pledged to fight the enemies of the sultan and Allah. (Ref. 18, 19, 20)

ITALY

Italy remained a conglomeration of contending city-states. The general economy was poor at the beginning of the century, with the Black Death killing 60,000 in Florence and 100,000 in Venice, great famines from 1315 to 1317, a decrease in manufacturing and trade and banking failures, particularly that of the Peruzzi and the Bardi houses in Florence. Naples was subject to France, under the House of Anjou and the rising Spanish power, Aragon, seized Sardinia in 1313, while Genoa took Corsica. Venice continued as a great power but had a serious uprising against its oligarchy in 1310. This "Tiepolo's Rebellion" was crushed, but it led to the permanent creation of an emergency committee called the "Council of Ten". Venice and Genoa kept up their battle on the seas throughout the century, with Venice the ultimate winner. (Ref. 21, 22, 23)

It was in this century that mercenary armies became standard in Italy. Armed adventurers, often from north of the Alps, got together under various leaders and either blackmailed local authorities or plundered the countryside. One band of 10,000 armed men and twice as many camp followers fought its way across central Italy, acting in effect, as a migratory city. For protection against such mobs, citizens of the cities taxed themselves to hire mercenary soldiers and the latter reimbursed the citizens, in a sense, as they spent their pay in the community. Thus was armed violence commercialized in Italy. (Ref. 24)

Overall, Italy did not stay "down" for long. In spite of the turmoil mentioned above, Italians were the primary managers of the commercial economy of Europe, with trade centers in Venice, Genoa, Florence, Sienna and Milan. This involved wholesale buying and selling, organizing projects in backwoods regions and extending credit. So extensive was their European financial dealings that the bankruptcy of the English King Edward III in 1339 triggered a general financial crisis in Italy. (Ref. 25) The Rinascita, or rebirth of the Classic Spirit, began in 1378 in Florence, financed by the money of the Medici family. This was the beginning of the humanist movement of emphasis on philosophy rather than religion, as the educated Florentines ignored some of the dogmas of the church and devoted themselves to the enjoyment of beauty in women, man and art. This state of bliss was marred some in 1345 when the industrial workers attempted to overthrow the ruling business oligarchy. There was much business in Florence as merchants there handled between 5,000 and 10,000 tons of Sicilian grain every year. (Ref. 26)1

1 All Europe had a general recession, which was followed by the Black Death. At the end of the century Jewish bankers, long kept at arms length, made their entry into Florence and settled there as money lenders in the next century  In Florence secular education was organized, with up to 10,000 children (out of a total population of 100,000) attending school. Over 1,000 of those went on to high school, training specially for merchant apprentices. A boy stayed there until age 15, studying arithmetic and accounting. The merchants were an educated group. (Ref. 27)

Although the European slave trade had almost died out, the decrease in population occasioned by the Black Death and famine resulted in Florence authorizing the import of slaves, providing they were infidels. By the end of the century almost every household had at least one, usually female, of Circassian, Tartar, Greek or Russian origin. All of this led the way for the Renaissance, which consumed all Italy in the next century. Toynbee (Ref. 28) says that this was a period of withdrawal and isolation from the rest of Europe, with new economic, political and cultural ideas developing. It was the age of Petrarch and Boccaccio and Dante, all of Florence. By the end of the century, in addition to Florence, there were Italian states of Venice, the Papal States, Naples and perhaps the most powerful of all - Milan, under Visconti lords. (Ref. 29, 30, 31, 32)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

The Hanseatic League, originally established primarily by traders of the Netherlands and Flanders, now included some 52 towns, most of them German, including Bremen, Cologne, Danzig, Dortmund, Hamburg and Hanover. (Ref. 33) At this time Germany was essentially a federation of provinces, each ruled by secular or ecclesiastical princes acknowledging a limited fealty to the head of the Holy Roman Empire. Ludwig Wittelsbach of Bavaria made himself emperor and then battled with pope John XXII over the imperial succession and finally crowned his own pope. (Ref . 8). William of Occam, a Franciscan theologian and philosopher, took refuge with this Emperor Ludwig IV, after he had been excommunicated in England. He was important as a forerunner of Martin Luther, in attacking papal claims to temporal authority and appealing to the authority of the Bible. Bavaria was briefly united under the Wittelsbach emperor but at his death the imperial crown went to Charles IV of Bohemia. In this century, the Brandenburg rulers became members of the Electoral College which chose the German king and emperor, but Wittelbachs, Habsburgs and Luxembourgs all contested for the crown while papal intervention contributed to monarchial weakness. (Ref. 34)2

2 This meant 150 to 200 ruling people out of 20,000 in the town and another 20,000 in the district. (Ref. 35)

Although it was a period of degeneration in some areas of Germany, there were also new ideas appearing that foreshadowed a more modern state. One of these was a growing territorialism, with the formation of Standestaaten, or states based on estates, without feudal arrangement and with the gradual establishment of non-noble, civil service, pointing the way toward more centralized communities. The second concept was that of bourgeoisie. In 1300 only 811 towns north of the Alps had a flourishing trade but by 1450 there were 3,000 such towns. Leagues of these were formed for mutual protection and the acme of this was the Hanseatic League, which reached its high point in this century. Salted herring made the merchants of this Hanse wealthy. Although the fundamental basis was economic, the League used war, if necessary to protect its interests. The merchant families formed a new class of patricians and guilds appeared for artisans and workmen. The still famous Loewenbrau brewery was started in Munich in 1383. Blast furnaces, which allowed iron to be cast, resulted in the transformation of European iron technology, a feature which, in turn, revolutionized warfare by decreasing the useful ness of castles and the value of chivalry. (Ref. 36) A final factor of importance in this era was the Teutonic Knight. Even by 1300 Germans had pushed beyond the Elbe, seizing the Baltic littoral and settling in Poland and Hungary. (Ref. 37, 38, 39)

Cruel persecution of Jews reached a peak, with wholesale murders in Swabia, Bavaria and the Rhine as well as in Switzerland and Austria. Famine, followed commonly by the Black Death, reached almost every German village. Many felt that the epidemic was a judgment of God and they joined a fanatic religious movement, the "Flagellants", who turned on the Jews in many areas, accusing them of causing the plague by poisoning of the wells. Jewish persecution may have accelerated the eastward shift of the Jewish population in Europe and helped to populate Poland with Jewish merchants. Economically, wage and price patterns were disrupted, class conflicts were exacerbated and an increased personal mysticism appeared within the Christian religion. (260,140).

AUSTRIA

Although subject to the Holy Roman Emperor, the Habsburgs controlled the duchy of Austria and were gradually extending their holdings. By the time of Rudolf IV (1356-65), the family had consolidated their position and Austria was a major power. The University of Vienna was founded in 1365 (Ref. 40)

HUNGARY

Hungary began the century with close to 1,000,000 people, consisting in a minority of Magyars ruling a majority of Slavs. The Arpad Dynasty became extinct in 1301, and Charles Robert of Anjou was brought in to rule and with French and Italian ideas and wines, Hungary became a western state. Industrial immigrants began to arrive from Germany, Flanders and Italy. It was a century of some glory and essentially peace for Hungary and adjacent states. One-third of all the gold production in the world, in the amount of 3,000 pounds each year, came from Hungary. Charles Robert set up a systematic fiscal policy with that gold as a base. Charles' son, Louis, although still an Angevin, became one of the greatest kings and was called "the Great", chiefly because of territory gained and his added assumption of the Polish throne in 1370. Some estimates give up to 3,000,000 people in Hungary by that time. The government was typical of European feudalism with nobles supplying military support for the monarch. Allied with Genoa, Louis had a long struggle with Venice which ended in the Peace of 1381 in which Venice ceded Dalmatia and paid tribute. Serbia, Wallachia and Moldavia all recognized the suzerainty of Louis and he even had a victory over the Turks in northern Bulgaria in 1366. At Louis' death his daughter Maria became queen and married Sigismund of Luxemburgs who became guardian of the kingdom. This situation was soon challenged by Charles of Durazzo and Naples, who had a large following in southern Hungary and Croatia and he became king in 1385 only to be assassinated about a year later. This resulted in a Croatian revolt and it was 1387 before Sigismund regained control and this time assumed the throne, himself. He was absent from the country most of the time, however, and there was a marked decline in royal power. In 1396 there was a disastrous loss in battle with the Turks, Dalmatia was taken again by Venice and there were Hussite invasions from Bohemia as a result of Sigismund's attempt to gain the Bohemian throne. (Ref. 41, 42)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Like Austria, Bohemia was a part of the German Holy Roman Empire, but with its own king. After the death of Wenceslas III (1306), the ancient Przemyslid line ended and a foreigner, John of Luxemburg, son of Emperor Henry VIII, was brought in to form a new dynasty, making Bohemia a part of the West. Limited in power by written law and subject to actions of a national diet, he actually showed little concern for Bohemian affairs. In spite of this Bohemia became a power in international politics. John supported the Teutonic Knights against Lithuania and for a time ruled western Lombardy, as well as the Tyrol. He died in the battle of Crecy, fighting on the side of the French. His son became King Charles I and soon Emperor Charles IV of the Holy Roman Empire. He was the greatest of the Bohemian kings, maintaining peace with the Germans, organizing good government, rebuilding and beautifying Prague and founding the University of Prague as the first university in central Europe. By the Golden Bull, initiated in the empire in 1356 transforming it from a monarchy into an aristocratic federation with seven electors to vote on the emperor and other matters, the King of Bohemia was given first place among those electors. Charles was a bright young man in every way except as a military leader and was the last of the great medieval kings. His one black mark was his subsidizing of the massacre of Jews and giving of their property to his supporters. His son and successor, Wenceslas IV, was a useless alcoholic and the remainder of the century was one of political chaos and degeneration. At the end of the century John Huss was pushing for the use of the vernacular in church liturgy and a religious movement known as Hussites began to form. Slavic nationalism rose in full force and added another disconcerting element. (Ref. 43, 44)

SWITZERLAND

The Swiss were the best soldiers in Europe and were frequently hired out as mercenaries and they repulsed all attempts of the Austrian dukes to enforce feudal rights. In 1315, after defeating the Habsburg dukes by rolling rocks down the hills on to the knights, at the battle of Morgarten, three cantons made the further step of forming the Swiss Confederacy, on their way to establishing the most stable and sensible democracy in history. Soon the original three cantons had been joined by five others. The Confederacy, however, remained a part of the Holy Roman Empire, although the southern communes emancipated themselves from the domination of the House of Habsurg by defeating Leopold II of Swabia, in 1388. Blamed for spreading the Black Death, Jews were persecuted at Lake Geneva and Basel. (Ref. 45)

WESTERN EUROPE

Famines, the Black Death (1346-53) and social and economic strife reordered the manorial system throughout western Europe, with the previous servile tenant becoming either a free-holder or wage worker. Laborers organized and revolts erupted. (Ref. 46) After 1350, for a hundred years there was a sharp drop in population and concomitantly a rise in the standard of living for the survivors of the epidemics and famines, as they inherited property and had more land for use and could concentrate on only the good, productive land. (Ref. 47)

SPAIN

Racially and geographically Spain was lacking in unity. Its population was a mixture of many stocks - Iberian, Celtic, Carthaginian and Roman, Teutonic and Arabic, Moorish and Jewish - and its mountains had prevented it from acquiring homogeneity.

In the Christian areas they had only religion in common. The one saving grace of 14th century Spain was wool, the chief source of royal revenue. By 1400 this country was exporting wool all over Europe and especially to Tuscany, while English exports there had dropped. (Ref. 48, 49)

Bands of mercenaries employed by every side took place in dynastic wars over most of the country. Although the successors of Alfonso X were not very capable, Alfonso XI (1340) did defeat an attack of Spanish and Moroccon Moslems and ended the African menace. This battle of Rio Salado (1340) saw perhaps the first use of cannon in Europe. (Ref. 50) Throughout the Hundred Years War, Castile supported France but tried to avoid actual hostility with England. Pedro the Cruel came to power in mid-century and, helped by the Franciscan monks, promoted a terrible persecution of Jews. Some of the latter converted to Christianity while others fled or were killed. Otherwise Pedro's reign was little more than a dynastic struggle with his half-brother, Enrigue (Henry) Trastamara.

The French, outraged by Pedro's treatment of his French wife, sent Du Guesclin to Spain to support Enrigue, while the English supported Pedro until they, too, became estranged by the kings' viscous character. Ultimately Enrigue defeated and killed Pedro and subsequently reigned as Enrigue II Trastamara. In Spanish history this was the "Trastamara usurpation" of 1369. Peace was made with both Aragon and Portugal by 1374. (Ref. 51) Enrigue's son, John I, and grandson, Enrigue III followed him on the throne before the end of the century.

In Aragon territories, James II held Sardinia and Corsica, while giving Sicily to his brother Frederick. There was continued turmoil among the nobility, however, with Alfonso IV ruling from 1327 to 1336 and then giving way to Pedro IV who ruled from 1336 to 1387. He was virtually a prisoner of the nobility for much of that reign and was eventually succeeded by a nephew, John I of Aragon. Pedro's daughter, Eleanor, married another John, son of Enrigue of Castile, so that these two communities became reconciled. Granada remained under Moslem rule, tolerant and prosperous. The physician Ibn-a Khatib described the contagious aspect of the Black Death, in contrast to the general concept of the times, which was that it was due to divine vengeance.

PORTUGAL

The great king Diniz was succeeded in 1325 by his son, Afonso IV. The latter had a troubled reign, including civil war with the opposition led by his son, Pedro (Peter) I. Under Ferdinand I further war with Castile occurred as Castile's Juan (John) claimed the throne because of his marriage to a Portuguese princess,- Beatrix, but the Castilians were beaten at the battle of Aljubarrota on August 14, 1385, which became Portuguese Independence Day. Under the Avis Dynasty, with John I the Great, Portugal entered the greatest period of its history. John married John Gaunt's daughter, Philippa, thus making the subsequent Avis family part English. (Ref. 52, 53)

FRANCE

The States-General met for the first time in 1302. Everywhere the new monarchies were finding a powerful aristocratic reaction and it was a particularly bad century for France. In addition to the revolt of the nobles there were labor-employer troubles and then England's attempt to conquer France, which began the Hundred Years' War in 1331. This came close to initial success with victories for England at Crecy in 1346 when Edward III's 4,000 knights and 10,000 English and Welsh longbowmen defeated Philip VI's 38,000 assorted heavily armored men and again at Poitiers in 1356, when the Black Prince of Wales took France's Jean II (John) prisoner. (Ref. 54, 55) Cannon were first used at Calais, in 1347. (Ref. 56) Unrest in Paris in that same year was led by Etienne Marcel and eventually led to violence. French expansion eastward was checked by the expanding Duchy of Burgundy. As can be noted on the accompanying small maps, by 1360 England controlled all of the southwestern portion of modern day France. By 1380, however, Charles V had retaken most of that territory. The devastation of the crops was responsible for more deaths in that war than the battles themselves. When Genoa, reeling from a final defeat by Venice in 1396, accepted French protection, the stage seemed set for a full-scale French intervention in Italy, but this was not yet to be as Charles VI, inheriting the throne, became insane and the French government was paralyzed. (Ref. 57, 58)

France had other problems in this century. Four general famines occurred and there was a crisis in north European salt production, partly because of the Hundred Years' War and partly because of economic conditions. The chief source of salt then became the beach pans of Bouigneuf Bay in southern Brittany, but this was of poor quality. Other problems were religious in nature. Early in the century Philip IV, wanting the Knights Templars' property, forced Pope Clement to allow the Grand Inquisitor, Guillaume of Paris, to prosecute the Templars as heretics. De Molay was burned at the stake in this activity and thus became a martyr. Since the Knights, originally an ascetic Catholic order, had over the years become very wealthy and were serving as the bankers of civilization, their prosecution could not help but interfere with the country 's economic as well as religious activities. France expelled all Jews in 1394. (Ref. 59, 60, 61)

NOTE: Insert FRANCE IN MID-14TH CENTURY (1328/1360)

Credits can go to some Frenchmen of this century, however. Jean Buridan wrote on theoretical physics and astronomy, anticipating Galiter, Descartes and Newton. Henri de Mondeville and Guy de Chauliac were great French surgeons and Nicole Oresme developed a system of co-ordinates and employed graphs to show the growth of functions, preparing the way for Copernicus. (Ref. 62, 63)

NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

The Dutch had succeeded in reopening the trade route around the Danish peninsula and had somewhat overcome the dominance of the Germanic Hanse in the Baltic trade. (Ref. 64) Growing realism and individualism in the arts was the most striking feature in the Netherlands, whose culture was strongly and proudly Germanic. (Ref. 65)

Farther south in Flanders1 as early as 1302 there was a general uprising against French influence and the burgher oligarchy. In spite of this and a great famine lasting from 1315 to 1317 which greatly affected Flemish cities, Flanders enjoyed a great economic development and along with Brabant had become the largest industrial complex in northern Europe, chiefly exporting woolens. As labor-employer troubles developed, however, a communistic type of organization appeared. As the English began to dominate the commercial activities in Flanders, a political crisis developed and the communes made the Count of Flanders, Louis of Nevers, prisoner (1325). Philip marched in, massacred the burghers on the field of Cassel and established French administration again. When England's Edward III replied with an embargo on wool export from England in 1336 the weavers of Ghent, under the wealthy James van Artevelde, became virtual masters of the country and made a commercial treaty with England. When Edward then declared himself King of France the Flemings recognized him as their sovereign and made a political alliance with him, all of this becoming a part of the start of the Hundred Years War. In 1369 the daughter of the Count of Flanders married the Duke of Burgundy with a two-fold result. First, there occurred a concentration of Flemish, French and Burgundian artists in the Burgundian cities and secondly after 1384 control of Flanders passed to Burgundy. (Ref. 66, 67, 68)

1.  Flanders is an area which today makes up most of western Belgium but includes also a portion of France. Most of the people speak a Germanic tongue, Flemish, and are known as Flemings

BRITISH ISLES

In Great Britain, as a whole, the Black Death dropped the population from 3.7 million in 1348 to 2.2 million in 1377 and it dropped another 100,000 in the next 50 years.

ENGLAND

The basic cause of the Hundred Years War between England and France was the dynastic quarrel which started with the conquest of England by William of Normandy in the 11th century and which created a state lying on 40th sides of the channel. In this 14th century the English kings still held the Duchy of Guienne in southwest France and they resented paying homage to French kings. Edward I had spent most of his life fighting the Scots and finally was defeated by them, while Edward II was a weak ruler who was finally forced to abdicate in favor of his fifteen year old son, Edward III, while the latter's mother and paramour, Roger Mortimer, actually ruled the nation. Meanwhile Edward II had died in a dungeon, supposedly by means of a red hot poker inserted through a pipe into his rectum, so that there were no external signs of violence. Coming of age, Edward III became upset over the way the French were treating the Duchy of Guienne as well as their activities in the Lowlands and he declared himself the King of France and sent armies through the Low Countries to France, to prove his claim. This king was the most spectacular of the Plantagenets, a conqueror, brave, but extravagant, ostentatious and shallow. His son, another Edward, was the famous Black Prince of warrior fame, who first won and then lost a great part of France for England during the Hundred Years War. Rather than being acclaimed a hero, he seemed to antagonize the people. He never reigned as king because he died before his father and it was his son, Richard II, who became a child king with John of Gaunt, his uncle, serving as regent. (Ref. 69, 70)3

3 (Ref. 71)

In spite of the intermittent warfare2, business had a great emergence, with new tycoons developing in the wool industry. After 1350 so much of the locally grown wool was made into cloth in England that the weavers of Flanders and Italy had to get and use poorer wool from Spain and Ireland. This was also a period of semi-renaissance, with a more general desire for education and a sudden surge of interest in university training. Oxford enlarged and new colleges were started, including Exeter, Oriel and Queens. Balliol had been built in the previous century. (Ref. 72, 73)

But England also had its troubles in this century. Early on, heavy rains wrecked harvests and destroyed the vineyards. Then the Black Death (bubonic plague) rolled into England in 1347 and returned again in 1361 and 1368, killing from 1/4 to 112 of the entire population. Because of the decimation of the laboring class, labor trouble subsequently developed. Some ref used to work because of low wages and became bandits. One great revolt of the workers, the Wat Tyler rebellion, was finally put down in 1381 by young King Richard II, after some concessions were made. In 1399 Henry Bolingbroke of Lancaster, son of John of Gaunt, beat Richard in battle, imprisoned him and took over the realm as Henry IV, ending the Plantagenet Dynasty. It should be mentioned that war with the Scots was another ever present threat to England throughout this century and frequently a reality. (Ref. 74, 75, 76)

Of some interest is the further development of the English language at this time. In 1362 Edward III ruled that English, rather than French, should be used for public trials and that was the first decisive defeat for the French language on the islands. Then English replaced Norman French in the schools and became the accepted language of the nation. Richard Rolle, who died of the plague in 1349, was the father of English prose, as he amalgamated Old English, Norman, French and Latin in a written language that had previously only been spoken. Geoffrey Chaucer lived and wrote in this type of English between 1340 and 1400. John Wycliff was partly responsible for the first complete, vernacular English Bible and this at a time when the established church felt that Bible reading by the masses was heresy. The poor priests who followed Wycliff (also Wyclif and Wiclif) were called Lollards and soon it was said that every fourth man in England was a Lollard, in that they adhered to his doctrines, which emphasized the purely spiritual function of the church, with direct access of the individual to God. Advocating a property-less church, Wycliff was opposed to the auricular confession and was in favor of the reduction of the importance of the sacraments. (Ref. 77, 78)

SCOTLAND

As the century opened Scotland remained without a king and suffered continual internal strife and external warfare with England. In early 1306, after a bloody confrontation with John Comyn the Red, Robert Bruce, a descendant of de Brus, was crowned King of Scotland. Immediately King Edward I of England started mobilization of forces to send north against him. Not ready for war, Robert I promptly disappeared into the western islands where, over the next many months, he gathered bands of Islemen, Irish and Gaels to initiate guerrilla warfare. Edward died in 1307 but the battles went on, with Robert making surprisingly successful raids on English strongholds, taking advantage of the weakness of Edward II. A great battle was finally fought at Bannock-burn, just south of Stirling, in 1314, with Robert I and 30,000 Scots defeating 100,000 English. An independent Scottish kingdom resulted with Robert I Bruce the unchallenged monarch. Bruce's daughter, Margaret, married Walter "the steward" and became the founder of the house of Stuart. (Ref. 79, 80, 81, 82)

Upon Robert's death, possibly from leprosy, his son David II succeeded him in 1329, nominally ruling for 42 years, although his regents had to fight constantly against usurpers and attacks from England. Edward III gave the Scots one of their worst defeats at Halidon Hill, forcing the boy king David Bruce to be taken to France for protection, while Edward Balliol (also Baliol), with English support, took over the throne. When Edward III turned to fight France, David II returned to his own country and Balliol was thrown out. In 1346, however, at the battle of Neville's Cross, David was captured by the English and spent 11 years in the Tower of London. He was finally released after an agreement wherein Scotland was to pay 100,000 marks in 10 yearly installments. Only 1/4 of this was actually ever paid. During these same years, Scotland suffered with England from the terrible scourge of the Black Death, chiefly of the pneumonic form. (Ref. 83, 84, 85)

The Steward (Stuart) line was established on the Scottish throne in 1371 by Robert II Steward, nephew of David 11 and descendant of Walter Fitz-Alan (high steward of Scotland in 1136) and with France as an ally his nobles fought England again, all as part of the Hundred Years War. Robert Ill succeeded to the throne in 1390. There was great poverty in Scotland, except among those nobles who had the military power and dominated the Parliament and the King. The villages had a measure of self-government within the framework of feudalism and monarchy. Industry was primitive, commerce precarious and the cities small and few. All Scotland had about 600,000 people. (Ref. 86, 87)

IRELAND

Edward Bruce, brother of Robert Bruce of Scotland, landed in Ireland in 1316 and with the support of some native leaders, had himself crowned king, although he lasted only two years. By 1350 the Normans controlled most of Ireland, although during this and the next century they adopted Irish customs. The Irish Parliament, made up almost entirely of English Normans, passed in 1366 the infamous Statute of Kilkenny, which for- bade inter-marriage between English and Irish "to prevent Gaelicization" This government of Ireland, emasculated by the English, soon became very corrupt. That statute, followed by the Black Death epidemic of 1348 and 1349 started the-decline of English influence in Ireland, as the viceroys and governors were unable to maintain order. (Ref. 88, 89)

WALES

Remained restlessly under English rule.

SCANDINAVIA

Fishing replaced agriculture as the chief economic activity of both Scandinavia proper and Iceland. Near the end of the century, Margaret ruled as queen and regent over all three of the true Teutonic Scandinavian countries - Norway, Sweden and Denmark - in a wonderful reign lasting into the next century.

NORWAY

Magnus II, who was also King of Sweden, ruled Norway as king from 1319 until he turned the Norwegian crown over to his son Haakon Vl in 1343. Margaret, daughter of Denmark's Valdemar IV, was married at ten years of age to King Haakon VI and ten years later she had a son, Olaf, who became king of Denmark when Valdemar died and then king of Norway when Haakon died. When Olaf expired in 1387, Margaret was elected as Queen, thus introducing the system of election already in practice in Denmark and Sweden.

SWEDEN

Magnus II became the Swedish king in 1319 at the age of three years, with his mother as regent and effective ruler. Through his mother Magnus also succeeded to the Norwegian crown and during a troubled period in Denmark actually gained Scania, Halland, and Bleking temporarily for Sweden. Even after he assumed the reign for himself, there was a definite weakening of the royal power and a rise of the aristocracy. The first meeting of the Riksdag, which included nobles and burghers, was in 1359. By 1363 Magnus was deposed and succeeded by Albert of Mecklenburg, who was always a tool of the nobility. They eventually dethroned him in 1388, calling in Margaret, already Queen of Norway and regent of Denmark, thus uniting all three countries. Officially she formed the Union of Kalmar in 1387 under the name of her grand-nephew and adopted son, Eric of Pomerania, but she retained the effective power.4

4 (Ref. 90)

DENMARK

The successful reign of Eric Menved ended in 1320 by capitulation and Christopher II was elected, with limitations laid down by the nobility and clergy. In 1340 Christopher was driven from the throne by Gerhard, Count of Holstein. This was indicative of the dominance of the German Hansa towns in Danish politics at that time. From 1332 to 1340 Denmark was in a state of anarchy, with no king and actually ruled by German Counts from adjacent territories. The Scanian provinces across the sound placed themselves under the Swedish king, Magnus Smek, as a separate province. But then came Valdemar IV, the youngest son of Christopher, to take the throne as one of the greatest Danish kings. The Church was subordinated to the royal power and the nobles and towns were made to perform their military obligations as Valdemar reconquered the territories lost by his father, in wars with Sweden, Holstein and Schleswig. In 1361 he even took on the Hansa. Copenhagen was sacked but the Danes defeated the Hansa fleets in 1362 at Helsingborg.

Valdemar had been raised at the Imperial German court as a European man of fashion; his wife was a Schlesvig princess. Although not liked much by the Danes, he ruled efficiently. During his reign he sold Estonia to German nobles, then conquered the Goths of Gotland, an island in the Baltic which was actually a part of Sweden although controlled by the Hanseatic League. The second war with the Hansa occurred from 1368 to 1370 and this time the League was supported by Sweden, Norway, Holstein, Mecklenburg and even by some of the Danish nobles. Badly defeated, Valdemar accepted the Peace of Stralsund which again made the Hansa supreme in the Baltic. Valdemar's grandson, Olaf, ruled from 1376, under the regency of his mother, Margaret, until his death in 1387 when Margaret became queen, ruling also in Norway and Sweden. (See map, page 726)

FINLAND

After 30 years of being the battle field for war between Sweden and Russia, in 1323 a boundary treaty was drawn up and solemnized and Finland became a true province of Sweden, remaining so for the next 500 years.

EASTERN EUROPE

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

Northern Estonia was sold by Denmark to German nobles of the Teutonic Knights, who were already pretty well distributed throughout that area. About two centuries of eastward migration of Germans, with the founding of such cities as Wismar, Rostock, Stralsund, Greifswald, Cammin and Kolberg had resulted in the formation of the Hanseatic League in 1358. The bulk of the peasantry in the Baltic States retained their Finno-Ugrian character and there was not any actual military conquest except in Prussia. (Ref. 91) In this and the next century the northern seas swarmed with herring and the Hanseatic League (with some strong competition from the Dutch) tended to dominate the commerce. Herring has to be salted within 24 hours of the catch and so this was of ten done at sea with salt imported from the south. The same chemical allowed cabbage to be preserved through the winter and the Baltic lands had a frontier boom, sending timber and grain to the Low Countries. As in most of Europe, however, the Black Death came on the scene in 1350. (Ref. 92, 93, 94)

Early in the century Poland withdrew from a previous short-term Bohemian association and in spite of pressure by the German Knights on the west and north and by Lithuania on the east, Vladislav united Poland into a coherent kingdom with a capital at Cracow. Casimir III, called the Great, continued as a fine administrator, indulging in some territorial exchanges and founding the University of Cracow. In both this and the next century, Poland's internal strife was perpetually between kings attempting unification and nobles trying to establish more of an oligarchy type of government. Externally Poland pushed alternately against the Teutonic Knights northward, trying to get to the Baltic, and southeast toward the Black Sea. As a result of a dynastic agreement in 1370, Louis of Hungary became the Polish king and reigned until his death about 1382. The Poles then accepted Louis' younger daughter, Jadwiga, and married her to Jagiello of Lithuania, at which time they separated from Hungary. Beginning in this century the Poles used their rivers for transportation of great rafts carrying wood to the Baltic Sea. Like other European medieval cities, Prague was a walled, self-contained unit, but occasionally it was necessary to move the walls to allow for growth. (Ref. 95)

NOTE: Insert Map 74. Lithuania and Poland 13th-14th Centuries

Lithuania was the largest territorial state of 14th century Europe and Gedymin (1316- 1341) and Olgierd (1345-1377) of the Gedimimas family were the real founders of that nation. Blocked by the Germans on the Baltic, they took advantage of the weakness of the Russian principalities to extend control to the east and south by acquiring Polotsk, Minsk and the middle Dnieper region, with Vilno as the capital of the state. Several times Olgierd advanced to the very outskirts of Moscow and he extended his domains to the Black Sea, where he defeated the resident Tatars, re-establishing an extensive realm that had been occupied in prehistoric times by the Baltic Galindas. The Lithuanians were people that had originated in the upper Dnieper basin and mixed with Lappons, who had been pushed south by the Baltic Finns. At the end of the century Lithuania was ruled by Jagiello, a pagan. When he married the Polish princess Jadwiga, as noted above, she converted him to Christianity and he then took the name Valdislav II. This marriage united Poland and Lithuania into a giant Slavic kingdom in 1385. The Polish-Lithuanian link was always loose, however, for several reasons not the least of which was that Poland was Catholic and Lithuania was chiefly Orthodox. In addition, they tended to pull in opposite directions, with the Poles chiefly concerned with the inroad of the Germans while the Lithuanians expanded along the Black Sea, hoping to exploit the decline of the Golden Horde. The latter were still tough enough, nevertheless, to defeat the Lithuanians in 1399 and close off their Black Sea outlet. (Ref. 96, 97, 98, 99) (See map, page 726, also)

RUSSIA (See map in RUSSIA section in 19th century)

Russia did not exist as a nation at this time. The western-most territory was dependent to Lithuania; the north had a variety of independent city-states, including from north to south the Principates of Novgorod, Moscow and Ryazan. The east, including all the territory north of the Caspian, some east of the Caspian, all north of the Black Sea in a diagonal line running northeast - all this was the Khanate of the Golden Horde with its Mongol-Turk marauder occupants. It was noted in the last chapter that in all probability the plague was brought to the Euro-Asian steppes from the southeast of Asia, then by the Mongols to the Crimea, from whence it spread to all of Europe. In 1347 the city of Caffa (now Feodosiya) was under siege by the Tartars when they suddenly began dying off with plague. The living Mongols catapulted their dead companions into the city and as the Christian defenders started home, nearly all died at sea. It was the survivors that started the epidemic in Italy that soon spread to the entire continent. (Ref. 100, 101, 102)

Novgorod was an important city of the Hanseatic League with a population in this century of about 400,000, a high rate of literacy and a thriving economy. In the Ukraine the old Scythian population, mixed with Slav and some Mongol blood, reverted to a nomadic life and became the Christian Cossacks, forming somewhat of a buffer against the Tartars. The general population shift, however, was northward. In 1318 the Yarlik (charter) given by the Golden Horde to a north Russian subaltern, passed on to Prince Yuri of Moscow and then to Ivan of Moscow, who also brought the Church Metropolitan to that city. The Russians of the era were very pious, monasteries were numerous and the Patriarch Alexis was virtually the ruler of the Russian people from 1354 to 1370 as the church was the life and culture of all. In mid-century Ivan II of Moscow refused to pay tax to the Mongols and the latter retaliated by raiding and massacring some 24,000 people and burning the city of Moscow. After this, however, the Mongol hold on Russia gradually weakened and in the great battle of Kulikovo, Dmitri Donskoi (meaning "of the Don"), then ruler of Moscovy, defeated the Tartar army in 1380 for the first time. Lithuanian armies, which were supposed to help the Mongols, did not arrive on time and probably related to this defeat is the fact that in the same year the Golden Horde was conquered by the White Horde from the east, which then migrated into its territories, although in the West all were still known by the former name. The Mongol-Turks were still not completely destroyed, however, and lived to attack Moscow again. (Ref. 103, 104)

1 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

2 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

5 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

6 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

7 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

10 [86] HANSEN, James, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

11 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

14 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

20 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

21 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

22 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

23 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

24 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

25 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

26 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

27 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

28 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

29 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

30 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

31 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

32 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

33 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

34 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

35 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

36 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

37 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

38 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

39 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

40 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

41 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

42 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

43 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

44 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

45 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

48 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

49 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

50 [281] Gore, Rick, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

51 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

52 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

53 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

54 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

55 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

56 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

57 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

58 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

59 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

60 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

61 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

62 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

63 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

64 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

65 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

66 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

67 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

68 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

69 [40] COSTAIN, THOMAS B., The Three Edwards. (Doubleday & Co., Inc., Garden City, New York, 1958).

70 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

71 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

72 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

73 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

74 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

75 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

76 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

77 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

78 [229] Wells, h.c., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

79 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

80 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

81 [91] Herm, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

82 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

83 [91] Herm, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

84 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

85 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

86 [91] Herm, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

87 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

88 [40] COSTAIN, THOMAS B., The Three Edwards. (Doubleday & Co., Inc., Garden City, New York, 1958).

89 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

90 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

91 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

92 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

93 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

94 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

95 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

96 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

97 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

98 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

99 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

100 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

101 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

102 [125] LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

103 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

104 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

2.  Rather than a continuous affair, the Hundred Years War was actually a series of intermittent wars

Europe: A.D. 1401 to 1500

EUROPE

At 1401 there was no dominant state in Europe. Germany and Italy were fragmented and the eastern empires of Casimir IV of Poland and Corvinus of Hungary developed late in the century and even then were ephemeral. The Iberian Peninsula had civil war and France had the Burgundians and Armagnacs feuding. Prolonged climate deterioration began about 1450, starting the "Little Ice Age", which lasted up to the first of the 19th century. (Ref. 1, 2) In spite of all this, after about 1450 Europe began to recover from the prolonged disasters and deficiencies of the previous 100 years. (Ref. 3)

Slavery had almost ceased in Europe until Portugal revived the custom in the latter half of the century, with the blacks from Africa. (Ref. 4) Movable type printing gradually came into use so that by 1500 some 236 towns in Europe had their own print shops (11). As Braudel (Ref. 5) states, the printing press expanded and invigorated everything. For centuries there had been two different European navies - the Mediterranean and the northern - but with increased trade and intermingling, the clinker construction and centerline rudder of the northern ships began to appear in the Mediterranean, while the southern lanteen rig went north and Europe began to emerge more as a single civilization. Vehicles with a moveable front axle, first used in gun carriages, were only employed after about 1470. As populations increased and artillery made their old walls useless, 15th century towns began to face serious problems. New, wide ramparts filled with earth (and thus hardly movable) had to be constructed and then large open spaces in front of these fortifications were necessary, eliminating gardens and trees. (Ref. 6)

Methods of exchange of goods had changed considerably by this century. Essentially only towns (or very large villages) now had markets. The western town controlled everything and the market, held usually once or twice a week, was one of its chief mechanisms. The surrounding countryside needed time to produce and collect goods and then divert some individuals, usually women, to sell the produce. On the seas, ships had increased enormously in size and were no longer individually owned, as shares were sold. The money market moved towards Holland and later London. (Ref. 7)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Venice continued her domination of most of the Mediterranean and added the island of Cyprus to her possessions in this century. (Ref. 8) The exception was Rhodes, which remained under control of the Knights Hospitallers.

GREECE

Early in the century Greece was divided between Ottomans, Venice, some Latin States and a small area still belonging to Byzantium. By late century all had been pushed out by the Ottoman Turks except for a few coastal islands which were still controlled by Venice. In the next century or two many Greek men actually functioned as Ottoman generals and officials. (Ref. 9)

UPPER BALKANS

Early on the bulk of the Balkans were under Turkish domination with the exceptions of Romania, which was a part of Hungary, and the Principality of Moldavia. Albania was taken by the Ottomans in 1430 and by 1436 the entire peninsula was Turkish. Their attempted invasion of Hungary began in 1439. Merchant Sicilians (Ragusans) were the chief westerners to penetrate this Balkan Turkish territory. (Ref. 10)

ITALY (See maps on pages 704 and 711)

Italy remained as a group of states, including the Venetian Republic, Florence, the Papal States, Genoa and Corsica, Sicily under Spanish Aragon control, the Kingdom of Naples1, and finally the German Empire which was dominant in the very north. Of all these, Venice was probably the most active, annexing much of the north Italian plain, giving her not only agricultural land of her own, but a direct route to Germany and guaranteeing her grain supply. (Ref. 11) Spices coming through Venice were in ever greater demand because they could disguise rancidity in food, reduce saltiness and give some character to otherwise insipid, dried edibles. At one time pepper was as negotiable as silver for currency in Europe. Venice imported 2,500 tons of pepper and ginger and almost as much again of other spices. The Venetian control of this trade actually was a great stimulus to the Portuguese to open up a sea route to India and was a factor in Spain's discovery of America. (Ref. 12, 13) This city was also the incoming port for cotton in the form of yarn or bales, receiving loads twice a year from Syria in 1,000 ton ships2. Venice was one of the first city-states to have a completely mercenary land army, although they had long used the same practice at sea. (Ref. 14, 15)

In contrast, it was in Florence that the Golden Age of the Renaissance started, in the last half of the century. Although plague continued to cause extensive loss of life in Italy as a whole, with a continued fall of the population of most Italian cities and with a decline in industrial and agricultural production and woolen cloth, still Florence seemed to prosper. The Florentine wool trade was a combination of activities in both town and country. In fact Gino Barbieri recently commented3: "The Italian renaissance is really all about wool'" Controlled by the Medici family, Florence bought Pisa, gaining direct access to the sea and it then invited learned Greeks to the community (1439). This initiated a period of great art and secondarily a considerable looseness in living and morals. The house of a merchant in Tuscany about 1400 might have had 12 to 14 rooms with a tile roof and glass windows, possibly a fireplace and wall hangings of French serge or linen or carpet. Floor carpeting, however, was rare. The dining room would have a long table with only one communal drinking glass and no forks (except for serving) and few spoons. Guests would bring their own knives. Benches were far more common than chairs. As everything was made of wood, fires were common and catastrophic, as in all of Europe.

As a result of the transfer of the church from a religious organization to, for all intents and purposes, a secular political power, the Italian middle and upper classes became the most skeptical of all European peoples. Although they paid lip service to the Catholic faith, their ideas and writings became more humanistic. (Ref. 19, 20) The papal schisms of this century undoubtedly had something to do with this shift of loyalties Water was beginning to be a troublesome factor in a great city such as Rome and one of the few accomplishments of Pope Martin V after the first papal schism was to restore one of the demolished great Roman aqueducts. (Ref. 21)

NOTE: Insert Map 45. Renaissance Italy

Among the great artists of the era were Botticelli, Leonardo Da Vinci, Raphael and Michelangelo. Leonardo was one of the greatest geniuses of all time, a brilliant, multi- faceted, secretive man, born as an illegitimate son to a notary, basically left-handed, but apparently somewhat ambidextrous and who of ten wrote in mirror image. Known primarily as an artist and sculptor, he was perhaps even more interested in science, including human anatomy, comparative anatomy, botany, geology, physiology, mechanical and hydraulic engineering, astronomy and military engineering. In addition he was a philosopher, of ten writing in paraphrase in a method very reminiscent of the New Testament and he even did some work in music, mathematics and, of course, architecture. He has been called an homosexual, but in the large, beautiful text of his work, called simply "Leonardo da Vinci" (Ref. 22), the only reference by any of the biographers to his personal, emotional life was the statement by Giorgio Nicodemi: "There is no trace in his life of women, who may have smiled at him or been his companions.”4 Leonardo was a contemporary of Columbus and Copernicus and helped to give deeper insight into the works of Michelangelo and Raphael. At one time or another he lived and worked in most of the city-states of Italy which were of ten at war with one another, although he was basically a Florentine. (Ref. 23, 24)

Science could make but moderate advances in this period and medicine made more progress than most, but even the most advanced anatomists and physicians of this age had barely reached, by 1500, the knowledge possessed by Hippocrates, Galen and Soranus between 450 B.C. and A.D. 200. Syphilis became rampant in Italy in 1493 and 1494 and the argument still goes on to whether or not this was brought from America. Celsus' old book De Medicina was one of the first medical texts ever printed (Florence, 1478). In addition, in 1487 Mondino de Luzzi's treatise on dissection techniques, called Anathomia was published at Padua and used as a standard text through forty editions, until the time of Vesalius. The treatise was actually written at the University of Bologna in 1316. (Ref. 25, 26)

Some new navigable canals and irrigation systems were built during this period. The first Great War between the Turks and Venice (1463-1479) developed over interference with trade and the Turkish threat to Albanian and Greek coastal possessions of Venice. In 1480 Naples, too, was sacked by Turks and at the end of the century almost of Italy, except Naples, came under French control as Charles VIII invaded in 1494. For the first time, artillery became a major element in European warfare in this campaign. It became apparent then that the community financed, local mercenary armies of the city-states of Italy could not stop intervention from outside the peninsula. Florence and the Papal States yielded readily to the French and even a fortress of the border of the Kingdom of Naples fell in 8 hours of bombardment by the new French guns, as its wall were reduced to rubble. (Ref. 27)

In addition to these military and political troubles, in 1498 the Portuguese rounded the Cape of Good Hope, establishing a waterway to the East, bypassing the Mediterranean and diverting world trade away from this ancient trade route. But there was one redeeming feature that saved Italy at that time. The rich of Europe forsake gold and silver fabrics for silk and since Italy was one of the few silk manufacturing centers of the continent, this brought a last wave of prosperity to the peninsula, to last about 100 years. Sicily was already growing sugar cane, but in spite of the intervention of Genoese capitalism, the sugar works were money losing ventures. (Ref. 28)

CENTRAL EUROPE

Gold and silver mines flourished again in central Europe from 1470 on for about 70 years. Mining camps were worked by free men in the Alps, the Carpathaians and the Erz Gebirge on the border between Czechoslovakia and Germany. (Ref. 29)

GERMANY (See map in section on PRUSSIA, in 18th century)

15th century Germany will be described in some detail so that the reader may understand the political and social groundwork on which the Reformation was to burst in full bloom in the next century. The people were the healthiest, strongest, cleanest and most vital and exuberant in Europe. They were actually too vigorous and prosperous to tolerate any longer the manacle of feudalism or the exactions of Rome. The German Church was rich but much of its money continually drained into Rome and a revolutionary spirit of hatred for the Church and the clergy had taken hold of the masses in various parts of the country. In the last half of the century all classes in Germany prospered and with the exception of knights and the lower nobility, although there were sporadic agrarian revolts. The German financiers became prominent, particularly at Augsburg, Bavaria and in particular we must mention the Fuggers family. These and other south German bankers had gained greatly from the mining boom in Germany and Bohemia. (Ref. 30) This era of the Fuggers established a center of wealth that Europe had not seen since the millionaires of Imperial Rome. The Fuggers soon moved the center of their operations to Antwerp and this closeness to northern Germany allowed that portion of the country to become divorced from the Italian economy and thus strong enough to protect Luther in the next century. Southern Germany, tied to the Italian economy, remained Catholic. The relative abundance of gold in the last years of the century in Europe paradoxically "launched" the silver mines of Germany. As one of these precious metals becomes more commonplace, the other becomes more valuable. (Ref. 31) (See map on page 711)

By 1460 a hundred small cities had won charters of practical freedom from their lay or church superiors. Cologne, with 20,000 people, was the largest town in Germany, functioning as a trade center at the intersection of two Rhine waterways and important overland trade routes. There were still ten times more rural than urban dwellers in the country, although there were about 3,000 towns of all sizes, each acting as a relay point 5 to 8 hours apart on trade routes. (Ref. 32) In each principality the three estates - nobles, clergy and commons - met occasionally in a territorial diet that exercised some restraint on the purse strings. Then there was an over-all Reichstag and a Diet of Electors to choose a king, who was then made emperor by the pope. Early in the century, Sigismund of Bohemia (and then also king of Hungary) was the Holy Roman Emperor, but then the Habsburgs of Austria came to power with Albert II in 1438 and after that all the emperors were Habsburgs and thus from outside of Germany, itself . It was not great wonder, then, that Frederick III, in league with the popes, aggravated tension between the popes and the German people and further set the stage for the Reformation. During his reign, the areas of Schleswig-Holstein, Bohemia, Austria and Hungary detached themselves from the German dominion.

With Gutenberg's European5 invention of the movable type printing press in 1454, there was a great increase in books for all the people. This was one of the things which helped to terminate the Middle Ages. There were 20 German translations of the Bible before Luther and a scholar, Johannes Reuchlin, put the study of the Old Testament on a scientific basis, so that it played a big part in the coming Reformation. Reuchlin was a humanist; Albrecht Durer was an artist of the period; Johann Muller was a peak figure in mathematics and astronomy, devoting an entire book to trigonometry, describing Halley's comet, making longitude and latitude calculations and establishing himself as a stimulating teacher. Sculptors worked in bronze and wood. Lucas Cranach was another portrait painter of the calibre of Durer and Nicholas (Krebs) of Cusa (1401-1464) was one of the great philosophers of Germany. Some of his ideas live on in the philosophical system of Leibniz. Regular postal service was established by the end of this century. German universities had increased to 16.

After 1400 the eastward political drive was carried on, not by the empire, but by two quasi-independent states, Austria and Brandenburg-Prussia, or more properly by the two dynasties - Habsburgs and Hohenzollerns. The Emperor Sigismund gave the march of Brandenburg to Frederick of the Hohenzollern6 family in 1417. Through conquests, purchases and marriages, this territory continued to grow. (Ref. 33) In Bavaria, Duke Albert IV again united the area in the last half of the century and introduced the law of primogeniture, thus allowing Bavaria to enter the Reformation period strengthened and strongly Catholic. The Habsburg Maximilian I (1493-1519) was the first and only Renaissance king of Germany. Through his wife's inheritance (Mary was heiress to Charles the Bold of Burgundy) he acquired the Netherlands. He was well educated, patronized the arts and sciences and aspired to a writer. He was adored by the middle classes, even though the princes were less than enthusiastic. Germany was still not a state, but under Maximilian it might have been called a nation. Eventually, however, both the emperor and the territorial lords began to hire mercenary armies and thus initiated a military plague. After 1497, Jews were expelled from many German cities.

AUSTRIA

Upon reading the paragraphs above it is apparent that it is difficult to separate the history of Austria from Germany at this period, when the Habsburgs were also emperors of all Germany. When Frederick III was crowned Holy Roman Emperor in 1452 he soon made Austria an archduchy. In 1474 the Habsburgs acquired the whole of Vorarlberg (on the border of Switzerland) and then in 1477 the Netherlands by marriage, as noted in the paragraph above. The inhabitants of Austria are, of course, basically Germanic, and the remarks about the German people above, can be easily translated to the Austrian populace. The only really negative feature of the century occurred in 1485, when King Matthias of Hungary occupied Vienna and stayed there for 5 years, actually assimilating Lower Austria and Syria into a temporary Hungarian Empire.

HUNGARY

Hungary, along with the Balkans and Poland, sent cattle on the hoof to Germany and Venice. Sigismund (actually Bohemian) was King of Hungary as the century opened and soon became Holy Roman Emperor. It was under his reign that a peasant revolt broke out over tithe money in the Transylvania region (now a part of Romania). This resulted in an institution called "The Union of the Three Nations" under which the nobles of Transylvania, along with the Saxons and the Szekels, formed a league for mutual defense against all except the king. Sigismund was followed by a young Polish king, Vladislav V, who was called Ulaszlo by the Hungarians.

At that time, Janos Hunyadi, son of a lesser noble of Vlach origin, who had been rapidly promoted in the army, defeated the Turks in Transylvania in 1442 and then, with King Vladislav V, undertook a Balkan campaign where eventually they were disastrously defeated and the king was killed. The heir was yet a baby so his uncle, Emperor Frederick, left Hunyadi in charge of Hungary, as regent. In 1456 the regent fought and defeated the Turks beyond Belgrade and had no further trouble with them for many years. The young king died soon after Hunyadi's death and there ensued a scramble for the throne. Finally, the nobles elected Hunyadi's son, Matyas (Matthias or Mathew). He was a true Renaissance prince, who fought 4 wars with the German Emperor Frederick III, finally gaining Lower Austria and Styria for his domains. This first Austro-Hungarian Empire was thus Hungarian. When Matyas died with no heir, the Hungarians took Vladislas Jagiella, another Bohemian king, as their own. Lower Austria was then given back to the current emperor, Maximilian. (Ref. 35)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

The phenomenon of earning wages by hiring out as a laborer was early seen in the mines of Bohemia. The considerable investment required for equipment for deep mines could be made only by merchants, who then paid men to do the work. (Ref. 36) As a source of energy, horizontal water wheels were still used in Bohemia at this time. (Ref. 37) We have seen in the paragraphs immediately above that there was a close association at this period, of Bohemia with Hungary.

As early as 1410 Germans and Czechs had clashed at the University of Prague over the papal schism and the German teachers and students had left and gone to Saxony, where they eventually founded the University of Leipsig. Under the reign of Wenceslaus IV, John Huss, a priest of Prague, began to preach the doctrines of Wycliff, challenging image worship, auricular confession, many ornate rites, indulgences and the existence of purgatory. The Church banished him and eventually burned him at the stake as an heretic, along with his friend and supporter, Jerome. The news of Huss' death caused the Bohemian Revolution of 1415 to 1436, in which the people denounced the death and declared that they would fight to defend the doctrines of Christ against the man-made decrees of the Church. They formulated the "Four Articles of Prague", as follows:

(1) Mass should be given in wine as well as wafer. (2) Simony should be punished. (3) The word of God should be preached rather than doctrines. (4) There should be an end to the extensive wealth of the clergy.

The Bohemian Revolution actually became the Hussite Wars, which, in turn, became socialistic in character. The Germans in Bohemia wanted to remain faithful to the Roman Church and the Hussites made them their victims, with battles, massacres and persecutions. All elements of the later Luther Reformation appeared first in this Hussite Movement. Wenceslaus IV died in 1419 and Bohemia had no king for 17 years, during which time the Hussites were dominant. Eventually they began to argue among themselves, however, and broke up into various factions. The more radical wing formed the "Moravian Brethren" sect and in eastern Bohemia and Moravia the Moravian Brotherhood Church was formed in 1457. By 1500 there were 100,000 members, renouncing the authority of the Roman Church and dedicating themselves to the New Testament. This church still exists today. In the meantime there was peace in 1436 with compromises on the part of the Empire and the Church. This peace was apparently stimulated as the more conservative elements of the Hussites were shocked as some of the radicals formed communist groups. When the conservatives allied themselves with the orthodox Catholics again, the revolt was put down and Sigismund of Hungary, the son of Charles IV and a Bohemian, became king and then Holy Roman Emperor. Then came Albert II, an Habsburg and then Ladislas V of Hungary (Ladislas I in Bohemia), although actually George of Podebrad ruled for him. On the death of Ladislas, George was elected king (1458), but in 1471 the crown reverted to the kings of Hungary, beginning with Matthias Corvinus. In 1485, at the treaty of Kutna Hora, the Catholics and the Hussites, then called Ultraquists, pledged 30 years of peace.

SWITZERLAND

The first half of the century was one of almost constant turmoil between the various cantons themselves and with the Holy Roman Empire. The Canton of Uri began expansion westward to get control of the passes into Italy, but the Swiss were driven out by the Duke of Savoy in 1413. From 1436 to 1450 there was civil war between Zurich and some of her neighbors over the succession to the domains of the Count of Toggenburg. Zurich allied itself with the German Emperor, who, in turn, called in the French, but they were all defeated by the soldiers of Schwyz and the French withdrew. The emperor made peace at Constance in 1446 and the cantons made their own peace by 1450. The general effect was to strengthen the Confederacy, although the country was still allied to the empire. The Swiss cantons were suppliers of meat to Germany and northern Italy. Geneva re-instituted the great fair concept that had declined in Champagne in the previous century. (Ref. 38, 39)

But the Swiss still had wars to fight. From 1474 to 1477 there was the Great War against Charles the Bold of Burgundy, who had eyes on Alsace. The Swiss had great victories at Granson and Morat in 1476 and Nancy in 1477, squashing Charles' plans. It was after this that Swiss pikemen were in great demand in Europe as mercenaries. There was war with Milan in 1478 and even war again with the emperor in 1499 over some territories in the east. The Swiss had French financial help and by September, in the Treaty of Basel, the confederation became independent in fact, if not yet formally. (Ref. 40)

NOTE: Insert Map 46. Activities of the Medici and Fuggers in Western and Central

Europe c.1500

WESTERN EUROPE

Beginning in mid-century, western Europe started another population boom, this time to last for two centuries. It has been said that the founding fathers of the modern state were three western European leaders of this century - Henry VII of England, Louis XI of France and Ferdinand II of Spain.

SPAIN

The marriage of Juan I, of Castile and Eleanor of Aragon allowed these two provinces to become united, although at first they kept the monarchies separate. Ferdinand I of Castile became King of Aragon in 1410 but the union did not really become complete and final until the marriage of Ferdinand II and Isabella, in 1474. In the meantime, by 1450 there were 10,000,000 people in Spain, a mixture of Celts, Phoenicians, Carthaginians, Romans, Visigoths, Vandals, Arabs, Berbers and Jews. A state bank had opened in 1401 and marine insurance had been established in 1435. The Church was an inseparable ally of the state and took small account of the pope in Italy. The king was head of the church and the people were devout. Moslems and Jews still made up 10% of the people. The Spanish Inquisition became cruel and money-mad under the Dominican leader, Torquemada and Spain was made into a unified State-church. For a short period, there followed a remarkable display of energy. Granada finally surrendered to the Christians in 1491.

The Genoese, Cristoforo Colombo, a giant of a man at six feet, when most virile men of that age were about five feet four, thought he could reach the spice islands of the east by sea by sailing westward, but the task of convincing Queen Isabella was not easy. Several factors were concerned in her final decision. Juan Perez, the Queen's confessor, pleaded for the trip; Granada had fallen, ending 700 years of warfare with the Moors; another Genoese, John Cabot, had already convinced Henry VII of England that the trip would be made sooner or later. (Ref. 41) Finally Luis de Santingel loaned Isabella the money for the glory of God and the Queen desperately needed to replenish her treasury, already depleted by those last campaigns against the Moors. The chance of a share of the spice trade from the Indies (since the Ottomans now had Constantinople and Athens, cutting off the old trade route) was the final argument. (Ref. 42) (Columbus' trips will be further detailed under Section VIII, AMERICA, this chapter). In 1492 in addition to Columbus' commission, the Spanish crowns issued the Edict of the Exile of the Jews, which led to massive emigrations and eventually slaughter. This wave of terror shook Spain to its foundations as perhaps 200,000 Jews were expelled. These people had been the real middle class of Castile - tax gatherers and state administrators, as well as high tax payers. The chief rabbi of Burgos was also the bishop there in 1415. In Seville the Bible had been read in Arabic for many generations. But strange tales about Jews drifted down from the rest of Europe and influenced the Spanish monarchs. The irony of the expulsion was that King Ferdinand, like most Spanish noblemen, had Jewish blood through his mother, Juana Enriquez7. At this same time slavery was commonplace in Spain. Rich families had as many as 50 - some Greeks, Russians, Albanians or Turks, bought at famous slave markets of Caffa on the Black Sea - but most were Negroes from Africa. (Ref. 43)

There were 2,700,000 sheep in Spain by 1467 and wool was the chief agricultural product, along with mutton, milk and cheese. (Ref. 45) At the end of the century Spain had an epidemic of typhus, brought there in 1490 by soldiers who had been fighting in Cyprus. (Ref. 46) In addition, incidental to the celebrations upon the return of Columbus from his first voyage in 1493, a terrible epidemic of syphilis broke out. It was severe, rapid in progress and of ten fatal and within 4 or 5 years the disease "toured" Europe. (Ref. 47)

PORTUGAL

On the political front, Portugal finally made peace with Castile in 1411 and then started their expansion on the African mainland. Their luck was bad as the plague hit and then they suffered an overwhelming defeat at Tangiers in 1437. Alfonso V, who ruled from 1437 to 1481, was one-half Spanish. The nobles revolted against him at one time, but he did promote the Ordenacoes Affonsinas, the first Code of Portuguese Law, in 1146. It was an amalgam of Roman, Visigothic and customary law.

It was not only gold hunger but shortages of grain, fish and slaves to work the sugar plantations of Madiera that stimulated the Portuguese merchant marine of this century. They built fortresses on the Gold Coast of Africa in the 1480s and by the end of the century were bringing 700 kilograms of gold and 10,000 slaves to Lisbon every year. (Ref. 48)

In their initiation of the slave trade, the Portuguese had the blessings of the Catholic Church in that Pope Nicholas V had authorized them to "attack, subject and reduce to perpetual slavery the Saracens, pagans and other enemies of Christ southward from Capes Bajador and Non, including all the coast of Guinea."8 Of course, the black kings and merchants of the African coast were happy to trade slaves for European cloth, hardware, spirits or firearms.

NOTE: Insert Map 55. The Iberian Peninsula Towards The End of the 15th Century (1476)

Near the end of the century Joao Il had to suppress another revolt by the nobles. When Portugal and Spain began to squabble over their overseas possessions in the new world, the Treaty of Tordesillas made a dividing line which was only more or less subsequently observed. In 1497, the same year that Portugal either expelled the Jews or forcibly converted them, Vasco da Gama, using an Arab navigator, Arab maps and astronomy tables of the Jew, Abraham Zacuto, sailed around the southern tip of Africa to India and thus began the commercial supremacy of Portugal. Unfortunately Vasco lost more than half of his crew to scurvy on the journey. Navigational improvements were pioneered through Prince Dom Enrique (Henry), the Navigator, son of Joao II and he brought mathematicians and astronomers, who made instruments and trigonometric tables to measure latitude. These improvements also resulted in the discovery and peopling of the Azores as well as the African coast. (Ref. 49)

FRANCE

The Hundred Years War continued on into this century. Henry V of England, joined by the ambitious Duke of Burgundy, invaded France in 1415, hoping to seize the French throne. He failed in this but be did manage to take a portion of the country, including Paris, for a time, following the battle of Agincourt, when the English, with 6,000 archers, 1,000 men-at-arms and a few thousand foot soldiers defeated 25,000 French, still wearing heavy armor. France was actually in ruins, with poverty, amorality, filth, cruelty, treachery and corruption endemic. This deterioration had been going on since the last half of the preceding century. In this recession, market buildings fell into ruins and even the great Halles market place in Paris declined. (Ref. 50) Nevertheless, the French King Charles VII set up a new government south of the Loire and after the stimulation of the epic of Joan D'Arc (originally Jeanne Darc), in 1429, the tide turned. Joan, a religious mystic, who led the defeated French troops, was burned at the stake by the British as a witch, but to Catholic France she was a guiding light. In 1435 the Duke of Burgundy switched sides, transferring his support to France and with the help of cannon the expulsion of the English soon followed. First Normandy was reconquered (1440), then Gascony and some adjacent areas in the 1440s, Burgundy in 1477, Anjou in 1481 and Brittany in 1491. It was the fall of Bordeaux in 1453 that, in effect, ended the Hundred Years war.

Thus the kingdom of France emerged on the European map between 1450 and 1490, centralized and capable of sustaining a professional standing army of about 25,000 men constantly, with about 50,000 more reserves available if needed. In addition- they had heavy artillery pieces which could demolish castle walls in a matter of hours, thanks to a century of rapid improvements in cannon design and manufacture. In this rebuilding Charles VII was helped immeasurably by the financier, Jacques Coeur, one of the copper kings. It should be noted, however, that in 1479 Louis XI disbanded his French infantry forces and made a contract with Swiss mercenary pikemen. The Swiss propped up the aristocratic-bureaucratic regime for the next 300 years. (Ref. 51, 52, 53)

NOTE: Insert Map 51. England and France in 1429

NOTE: Insert Map France in A.D. 1453

Under the strange King Louis XI in the last of the century, the government of France became the most powerful in Latin Christendom but the people themselves became poorer. It was Louis' son, Charles VIII, who invaded Italy and held a part of it for a short period. Lyons became the most famous "fair" center, located on the great trade route through the Rhone Valley and it prospered accordingly, developing its own stock exchange in 1462. Toulouse followed with one in 1469. (Ref. 54)

In the south of France, as in Spain, tens of thousands of sheep were moved annually from the mountains of Provence to winter pasture at Arles. Also in Provence, communal herds of pigs were driven across country to fatten on the acorns of Vauduse and Albion.

The development of all this over a period of many, many years had helped the food situation throughout France and there were only six general famines between 1200 and 1500, a marked improvement from earlier centuries. (Ref. 55) The modern French language appeared fully complete in the works of Francois Villon in this century and Jean Froissart was another great writer of the period. (Ref. 56, 57, 58) But it is easy to overestimate the extent of true civilization in Europe in past centuries. The whole continent, from the Urals to Gibralter was the domain of wolves and bears. In 1420 wolf packs entered Paris and they were there again in 1438, attacking people. (Ref. 59)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

This area remained more or less unscathed by the Hundred Years War. In the first half of the century, present day Holland and Belgium were a part of Burgundy and ruled by the Burgundy dukes, essentially as a separate entity. After the duke, Charles the Bold, was killed in 1477, his daughter Mary saved almost all of the Netherlands and Flanders by marrying the Habsburg head and getting his help against France. In the process Burgundy became part of the territories of the Holy Roman emperors Maximilian I and later Charles V. Trade with England became very important to both areas. The Dutch now seized control of the herring industry in the North Sea, the English having granted them the right to seine in their waters and the rise of Amsterdam was made possible by this herring industry. But about 1500 the herring disappeared, whether because of a change in the currents, depredations of larger fish or disease, is not known9. The results were far flung and many. The scarcity of fish drove up the price and fishing fleets were dispersed even to the distant waters of Newfoundland, by Breton fishermen. (Ref. 60)

In contrast to some parts of Europe, however, meat was commonly eaten in the Netherlands, even in times of famine. Windmills were particularly useful in this country for driving bucket chains, which drained water from the soil and poured it into canals, thus helping in the reclamation of land. The permanent westerly winds from the Atlantic to the Baltic made these mills more efficient than those of some countries. (Ref. 62)

Bruges in Belgium was one of the four great trading posts of the Hansa, along with Tyskebrugge in Bergen (timber and fish), Peterhof in Novgorod (furs), Steelyard in London (wool and cloth). The first north European stock exchange developed in Bruges in 1409.

At the end of the century, however, Bruges' harbor silted up and the cloth center shifted to Antwerp on the Scheldt and that city developed its own exchange in 1460. (Ref. 63, 64) Coal was used throughout the Low Countries and was exported, but almost all of their salt came from the mouth of the Loire. (Ref. 65)

As in Bohemia, various "heretical" groups made their appearances in the Lowlands at this time, but more of this later. Many great artists developed, including Herbert and Jan Van Eyck and Roger de la Pasture, also known as Rogier Van der Weyden. Important to note, too, is the birth in this century of Erasmus, skeptic, satirist and humanist who was another forerunner of the Reformation and about whom we shall have much more in the discussion of ENGLAND, in the next century. (Ref. 66)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

Among the great powers rising on the Atlantic seaboard, England came last. From about 1350 to 1450 the English had had a drastic population reduction from the Black Death, prolonged economic stagnation and sporadic outbursts of the Hundred Years War against France. As noted above, Henry V took most of France for a short period and his death may have saved that continental country, but he almost ruined England because the treasury sank into irremedial debt. Henry VI went mad and there followed the famous War of the Roses, lasting from 1454 to 1485, in which the nobles of the House of York battled those of the House of Lancaster for the throne. It was a suicide of the Anglo-Norman aristocracy and England was left impoverished, destitute and desolate, as the

Lancastrians were scattered or destroyed and many of their nobles decapitated10. The victorious Yorkists entered London with King Edward IV, who had already resolved to have as little to do with Parliament as possible. In 1475 he made a token invasion of France through Calais, the one remaining English foothold on the continent, but he soon stopped to parley with Louis XI and a settlement was struck whereby Edward obtained a lump sum of 75,000 crowns and a yearly payment of 50,000. This was almost enough to keep him independent of Parliament and let him live the life of ease, which he so desired.

Some would say that his debauchery and promiscuity caused his early death in 1483, but actually he may well have died of appendicitis. His son Edward V, the apparent heir, was immediately imprisoned and his uncle took over the crown as Richard III, claiming that the boy Edward was a bastard and not entitled to succeed. But Richard, himself, ended up without an heir and the rival claimant to the throne became Henry Tudor, Earl of Richmond, a Welshman, who had been forced to flee to Brittany many years before. Now both Yorkists and Lancasters left England to join him as he prepared an expedition at the mouth of the Seine. In late summer of 1485, Richmond, with his English supporters and a body of French troops landed at Milford Haven, near the southwestern tip of Wales. The Welsh were more than happy to have the prospect of having one of their own on the throne of England and many Welsh gentry joined his forces so that he had about 5,000 men as he moved through Shrewsbury and Stafford. In the last of what should be called the "nobility wars", on Bosworth Field, Richard III was slain and Henry Tudor (Tydder) became Henry VII, a wise, sad, careful monarch, who reformed the administration, centralized the government and finally left the state respected, orderly, solvent, united and at peace. Henry's claim to the throne was through his mother, from John of Gaunt, founder of the House of Lancaster. He married Elizabeth, a princess of the House of York and thus united the two rival houses. When his first son, Arthur, who had married Catharine of Aragon, died, Henry arranged for his second son Henry (later Henry VIII) to marry the widow, thus strengthening the alliance with Spain. (Ref. 69, 70)

During this 15th century England experienced a so-called "agrarian revolution", which was a transition from grain to sheep raising. This, in itself, caused a social and economic catastrophe, with the small farmer eliminated, the flatlands depopulated and the food supply decreased so that heavy imports were necessary. The country did experience a mild renaissance in the last quarter of the century, however, as she began to build her own merchant ships and to export coal from Northumberland. By 1500 she was ruling the North Sea trade. Giovanni Cabato, sailing under an English charter and the Anglicized name, John Cabot, discovered Newfoundland and explored the American coastline from Labrador to Delaware, just a few years after Columbus' initial trip to the new world.

The people of England were a vigorous stock - coarse, profane and perhaps a touch cruel. Probably only 40% could read. As if the Black Death were not enough, in 1485 a new disease, characterized by severe sweating, appeared in England and was called sudor anglicus or the "sweating sickness". Death could occur within days, particularly in strong men. Paradoxically old women and children were spared. After appearing at intervals into the next century in England and in some outbreaks in northern Europe a little later, the disease, whatever it was, vanished forever. (Ref. 71, 72, 73)

Two men who were to play most important parts in the history of England were born near the end of this century. Thomas Wolsey was the son of an Ipswich butcher, who had been in some trouble with the law. Thomas enrolled in Oxford University at the age of II (instead of the usual 14 years) and 40 years later was to become the most powerful man in western Europe. Thomas More's father was a London barrister and his grandfather had been a butler. He too attended Oxford, beginning at the then usual age of 14. He was a good student, excelling in Latin and Greek and eventually ended up in the study of law. We shall hear much more of both these men in the next century. (Ref. 74)

In the last chapter we mentioned the early protestations against the organized church by John Wycliffe. As his followers waned, the church came back into power. Some Lollards persisted, however, and finally presented a statement of principles to Parliament opposing clerical celibacy, transubstantiation, image worship, necessity of confession to priests, ceremonies of exorcism, worship of saints, etc. Some of these men were executed for heresy, probably under the statue "de Heretico Comburendo" which had been passed at the beginning of the century. In this period under discussion, the king's government was carried on chiefly by priests. The Lord Chancellor was almost always a priest and about half the Privy Council (similar to a modern cabinet) were bishops. This link between the Church and the government service was one of the reasons for the corruption in the Church that was apparent by the end of this century. Nearly every priest was corrupt and this was generally accepted as normal. The priesthood appealed to practical men rather than to spiritual individuals, who usually preferred the monasteries. The word "religious" was used exclusively to refer to monks and nuns. The priests were called the "secular clergy", but it was they who alone could grant licences, dispensations, absolution after confession and perform the miracle of transforming bread and wine into the Body and Blood of Christ at Mass. By this 15th century priests no longer took a vow of celibacy, although most novice monks and nuns did. (Ref. 75)

At the very end of the century Henry VII put down an insurrection in Cornwall, where the people had risen to protest taxes imposed for defense against Scottish invasion forces. (Ref. 76) Some remarks about the legal system in England are in order. There was a good deal of antagonism between the barristers and the priests of the civil service. The latter had usually studied canon law and also the old Roman civil law, codified by Justinian in the 6th century. Although parts of the Roman law had survived in most of western Europe and even in Scotland, the English common law had developed along different lines. By this 15th century torture was freely used in political cases brought before the Privy Council, where the civilians, mostly priests, conducted the trials. (Ref. 77) Of incidental interest is the fact that construction of Westminister Abbey was under way as the century ended. (Ref. 78)

SCOTLAND

The infant heir, James I, while going to France for safety, was taken prisoner en route by the English and on the almost immediate death thereafter of Robert II, the regent, Albany, actually ruled Scotland in an uneasy peace that allowed some recovery of prosperity amid good harvests. The Scottish church achieved opulence and the ecclesiastical income equaled all other incomes combined.

The ordinary Scottish man living in the last half of the century had a rough life, but in a warm, human society. The crown laid down all sorts of rules - such as no drinking in taverns after nine o'clock, no staying with friends when traveling (i.e. must stay in taverns), every man with a plow and 8 oxen was to plant a designated amount of wheat, peas and beans, commoner women could not wear clothes of silk, scarlet gowns or trimming of martin fur and must have their heads covered. The peasant with his kin usually worked 30 acres with a wooden plow and oxen and lived in a turf house, such acreage "leased" to him for five years. At the end of the century, James IV did give his serfs the land in fee, however, and encouraged his barons to do likewise. The great burghs, started by the merchants, were becoming cities, with vermin, wandering dogs and free-running swine, fish stalls, general squalor and plenty of beggars. Each man kept horse and weapons ready to be available for war within 12 hours of the first beacon flare. John Major, an educated historian of the times, described two nations in Scotland - the wild Scots of the mountains and the householding Scots of the south, both-quarrelsome and contentious, with the "lairds" thinking of nothing else but fighting. The two "peoples" had different tongues and hated each other. The land was rich in fish, wildfowl, deer and immense quantities of salmon and herring were exported to France, Flanders and England. (Ref. 79)

The last two-thirds of the century was a bloody era with the ransomed James I, James II and III all meeting violent deaths and the nobles did their share of killing each other.

"For eight years Douglases and Hepburns, Stewarts, Ruthvens and Crawfords, Kennedys and Ogilivies fought with or against each other on both sides of the Forth."11 James IV married Margaret Tudor, sister of the future King Henry VIII of England and became the best loved of the Stewarts. A Renaissance prince, it was he who made his Parliament pass the first compulsory education act in 1496. Scotland acquired the Orkneys and the Shetlands from Denmark in 1472. After 1487 the bishops and abbots were nominated by the king, a feature which led to a deterioration of the already corrupt clergy.

IRELAND

Ireland continued to be dominated by England although by 1500 English influence had waned to be confined to a small border area while the remainder of the country drifted back to a squalid freedom. (Ref. 81)

WALES

For centuries the Welsh had seethed just under the point of open rebellion against the English and in 1405, with the help of French troops Owen Glendower actually opened fighting. It was 1415 before this rebellion was finally ended and Glendower pardoned. (Ref. 82) Even so, it was not until 1485, when the Welsh Henry Tydder (Tudor) became Henry VII of England, that the Welsh began to live peaceably with their English neighbors. (Please see page 720)

Scandinavia

NORWAY, SWEDEN, AND DENMARK

At the death of Queen Margaret in 1412, her grandnephew Eric, in whose name she had actually ruled, allowed the Union of Calmar, which had loosely bound the three nations, to become in essence a Danish Empire. He introduced the “Sound Dues”, charging all ships going to and from the Baltic through the Danish sound and built castles (including the famous Kronborg castle at Helsingor – English “Elsinore”) along both sides of the narrow strait to protect the area. The dues produced enormous sums of money for Denmark in the next several years, but they also produced immense political troubles. All of the Scandinavian countries were protective of their coastal waters. The city of Bergen in Norway was completely under the control of the Hanseatic League, but when some of their fishermen caught some English poaching in the area, they bound the English and threw them overboard to drown.

In Sweden a peasant uprising, initiated by Englebrecht Engelbrechtson against the king, was backed by the nobles. The revolt spread to Norway, with strong feelings developed against the somewhat autocratic Eric. When the nobles’ pressure reached its height, Eric abdicated and went to Gotland. The aristocracy of all three countries then chose his nephew, Christopher of Bavaria, as his successor. He died in 1448 without a son and Count Christian of Oldenburg, distantly related to the old Danish royal line, was chosen and accepted by Norway and Denmark. But Sweden named Karl Knutsson as its king. (English texts list him as Charles VIII.) Christian promptly attacked the Swedes but lost at the battle of Brunke Hill, in 1471. As a dowry for his daughter Margaret, who married King James III of Scotland, Christian gave the Norwegian Islands of Shetland and Orkney to Scotland. He administered the state well, but like his predecessors, his court was filled with Germans and he was financially dependent on the Hansa cities. Christian arranged a union of Schleswig and Holstein under the Danish crown in 1460 and founded the University of Copenhagen in 1479. On his death, his son Hans was elected successor in both Norway and Denmark. By that time the Swedish nobles were ready to get rid of their King Sten Sture, but couldn’t quite get this promoted before Hans lost his patience and marched on Stockholm with an army, only to be repulsed by Sten Sture the Younger. The clergy supported the King of Denmark, but the nobles pretty well controlled Sweden, with its rising commerce and industry. The University of Uppsala was founded in 1477 and printing was introduced soon afterward. In 1500 King Hans and his cousin, Duke Frederick of Holstein, attacked the Frisians on the fertile marchland at the base of the Jutland peninsula, but they were badly defeated and King Hans was not only humiliated, but then found that some of his subjects, particularly the Swedish peasants, were now ready to throw him over. (Ref. 83, 84, 85, 86)

It is of some interest that what might be called the first Swedish Riksdag, or Parliament, resulted when Engelbrektson, mentioned above, called a meeting of the Estates (nobles, clergy, burghers and peasants) which then elected him Regent, in 1435. He was murdered in a year and the regime collapsed, in part due to the attitude of the Swedish bishops.

FINLAND

Finland remained a province of Sweden, although the Finns, themselves, were little affected by neighboring civilizations. (Ref. 87)

OVERSEAS SCANDIVAVIAN CENTERS

An example of the extensive use of various materials for money, in Europe, can be found in a market price list from Iceland, where one dried fish would purchase a horse-shoe, three would buy a pair of women's shoes and one hundred a barrel of wine. (Ref. 88)

EASTERN EUROPE

At the beginning of the century the political boundaries were not greatly different than after the Peace of Stralsund.

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

Some 200 years of struggle in this area between German, Slav and Balt culminated in the battle of Tannenberg of 1411, where the Teutonic Knights were vanquished by the Polish-Lithuanian army. Lithuania, as a Grand Duchy, was part of the Polish State. Prussia, although partially still under control of the Knights, continued to decline until the Peace of Torun of 1466, under which Pomerelia, Danzig, etc. went under Polish rule. (Ref. 89) In East Prussia, where the Teutonic Knights still held power, the bonds of serfdom were increased and in 1494 Prussian land owners were given the right to have runaway fugitive serfs handed back to them.

NOTE: Insert Map 44. The Hanseatic League and the Political Situation in Northern Europe after the Peace of Stralsund in 1370

Casimir IV, previously Grand Duke of Lithuania, was one of the great rulers of Poland with its Lithuanian Duchy. When his son Vladislav assumed the throne he became king of Bohemia also. As noted previously, the union of Poland and Lithuania had its problems, basically arising from the fact that eastern Lithuania was orthodox in faith and Russian in language. The Polish ascendance thus brought aggravation of issues arising from the religious and ethnic differences. Mazour says: "The religious disagreement held the conflicting interest of Poland and Russia even further apart and made deep imprints upon the course of political development in eastern Europe for centuries to come."12 Casimir IV curtailed the independence of the Church somewhat, by making the bishops appointed by the king. Poland and Lithuania were greatly dependent upon river transport, using immense rafts of tree trunks with a central cabin for the sailors. Great wharfs were built at Torun (Thorn), Kovno and Brest-Litovsk. Jewish merchants were very important in the trade of 15th century Poland. (Ref. 90)1

1 In this way 300 to 500 tons a year were produced. (Ref. 92)

RUSSIA (See map in section on RUSSIA in 19th century C.E.)

It should be noted that the entire region, which we have just discussed as Lithuania, as well as part of Poland, is today part of the U.S.S.R., so that in a sense we could have transferred the last paragraphs to this heading of "RUSSIA", but we have preferred to keep the old historical regions separated. The Times Atlas of World History (Ref. 93) calls the Lithuanian-Polish area "West Russia" and the Moscovy area "East Russia"

Five years before Constantinople fell to the Turks, the Russian Church had declared her independence from Byzantium . This church was the sole patron of letters and arts in Russia. Occasionally the Mongol Khan still mustered attacks and Basil II was captured in 1445 in a serious Russian defeat. Still, the Muscovite rulers managed to hold on to the title of Grand Prince and gradually suzerainty over Novgorod was established and tribute exacted. Although at the beginning of the century the people of Novgorod were still using small Tartar coins, scraps of martens' skins and bits of stamped leather for exchange, by 1425 they began to mint very coarse, silver money. The population of that area continued to increase and commerce developed to the point that almost compelled the unification of the country.

Ivan III the Great, of Moscow, began unification by conquering neighboring Novgorod and then extended his rule to part of Finland, the Arctic and the Urals. He then took some of Lithuania and played the Mongol groups in the east against each other so that in warfare they gradually melted away. Ivan assumed the title of Caesar or Czar, and claimed inheritance to all the religious and political authority of the now defunct Byzantium. Toynbee (Ref. 94) calls this the founding of the Universal State of the Russian branch of the Orthodox Christian Society. The type of Christianity was the eastern, "orthodox", court-ruled form, which had reached Russia long before, through Bulgarian missionaries. The divine right philosophy of absolute power began to be put into practical form. The Assumption Cathedral in the fortress Kremlin, the largest in Russia, was built in 1479 by Ridolfo Fioravanti of Bologna, Italy. Ivan the Great commissioned the first stone palace of the Kremlin, the Palace of Facets, in 1487 and his actual living quarters, Terem Palace, was built in 1499. It was a dark and dreary place, with only candles for light. The first Code of Laws for Russia was compiled by Sudebnik in 1497. (Ref. 95, 96, 97, 98)

Russia's most noteworthy international position in the last 40 years of this 1 5th century was its isolation, cut off from almost all contact with the outside world by the hostility of adjacent Swedes, Livonians, Poles and Turks. It had no access to the sea in any direction, a feature which remained one of its great concerns for centuries to come. Even the Black Sea remained unattainable. The Ottoman Mehemmed II established a bridgehead by capturing Caffa from the Genoese and brought the Khanate of the Crimea under his control, this being the most significant successor of the Golden Horde. A land route to the Crimea was finally established via Constantinople in 1484. By mid-century, in addition to the Crimean Khanate just mentioned, the original Golden Horde had broken up into the Khanate of Kazan in the north, the Khanate of Astrakhan in the southeast on the northwest shore of the Caspian and a Khanate retaining the old Golden Horde name in the southwest. (Ref. 99)

NOTE: Insert Map: 15TH Century Poland, Lithuania and Russia

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

8 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

9 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

10 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

14 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

15 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

16 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

17 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

18 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

19 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

20 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

21 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

22 [121]  LEONARDO DA VINCI. (Reynal & Co. New York, 1956).

23 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

24 [121]  LEONARDO DA VINCI. (Reynal & Co. New York, 1956).

25 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

26 [125]  Lyons, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

27 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

28 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

29 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

30 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

31 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

32 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

33 [184] RODES, JOHN E., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

34 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

35 [124]  Low, d.m. (Editor). Abridgement of The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, by EDWARD GIBBON. (Harcourt, Brace & Co., New York 1960).

36 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

37 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

38 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

39 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

40 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

41 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

42 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

43 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

44 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

45 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

46 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

47 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

48 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

49 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

50 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

51 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

52 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

53 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

54 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

55 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

56 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

57 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

58 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

59 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

60 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

61 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

62 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

63 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

64 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

65 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

66 [250] GILLINGHAM, JOHN, The Wars of the Roses. (Louisiana State University, 1981).

67 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

68 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

69 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

70 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

71 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

72 [125]  Lyons, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

73 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

74 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

75 [50] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

76 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

77 [169] POLLITZER, WILLIAM S., "Blood Groups and Anthropology", Critical Reviews in Clinical Laboratory Sciences Vol. I: 193, 1970.

78 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

79 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

80 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

81 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

82 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

83 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

84[237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

85 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

86 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

87 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

88 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

89 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

90 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

91 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

92 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

93 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

94 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

95 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

96 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

97 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

98 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

99 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  After 1435 Naples was also ruled by the Aragon king until November, 1500 when, in a secret treaty of Granada, Louis XII and Ferdinand divided this kingdom between them. (Ref. 16)

2.  Genoese carracks at this same period were already up to 1,500 tons. (Ref. 17)

3.  As quoted by Braudel (Ref. 18), page 312

4.  From Reference 121, page 39

5.  It will be recalled that movable type was available in China as far back as the 11th century, even though it was not extensively used until the 14th. See pages 564 and 685

6.  The name comes from the ancestral castle atop Mt. Zollern in Swabia, but the family descended from the Teutonic Knights, who superimposed their Germanic origins over the original Prussian Balts, who eventually became extinct as a separate people. (Ref. 34)

7.  The author of the first European novel, La Celestina, was the Jew Fernando de Rojas, cousin of King Ferdinand. (Ref. 44)

8.  Quotation from H.A. Wyndham, The Atlantic and Slavery, published in London, 1935, page 221, as noted in Reference 211

9.  Trager (Ref. 61) says that it was a decrease of copepod crustaceans on which the herring feed. (Original source not given)

10.  John Gillingham (Ref. 67), lecturer in history at the London School of Economics, presents a considerable different view, denying the destruction, describing the battles as more the wars of gentlemen taking care not to offend the electorate and hardly affecting the social and economic development of England. Jasper Ridley (Ref. 68) would agree that the battles were fought by the royal and noble families and their retainers in a few counties only, but does remark that there was widespread breakdown in law and order in neighboring areas during these conflicts

11.  This quotation was taken from page 140 of Prebble (Ref. 80)

12.  Quotation taken from page 38, Mazour (Ref. 91)

Europe: A.D. 1501 to 1600

EUROPE (The time of the Reformation and beginning of world exploration)

At the beginning of this century Europe had a population of about 69,000,000 and it was increasing rapidly. Commerce and financial transactions remained essentially linked to the great fairs held regularly at centers between northern Italy and Flanders and there was a continuous inflation year after year. In a little over 100 years in France, prices rose a total of 627.6% (i.e. from 1471 to 1598). (Ref. 1) In the second half of the century, private trading with traveling merchants became a common feature, probably because the public markets were becoming inadequate and too closely controlled. Advertising was already flourishing and land was bought and sold frequently. The commission system, whereby all merchants worked on commission for other merchants, who did the same for them, became quite common by the end of the century. (Ref. 2)

Braudel (Ref. 3) makes the interesting observation that the first 2/3 of the century was an age of accelerated social promotion, with the highest bourgeoisie group climbing from the trade background to join the limited ruling classes, all over Europe. As a section of the old nobility disappeared, it was replaced by these wealthy new-comers. At the end of the century this trend was reversed - "the door to social advancement was in effect slammed shut, the ladder pulled up." In general, successful merchant families only survived as such for 2 or 3 generations. After that they abandoned trade to live quietly on country estates or when possible slipped into the nobility class.

Roads in Europe were chiefly tracks a yard wide, suitable for horsemen, although sometimes there were adjacent footpaths for pedestrians and herds. When wheeled carriages appeared in large numbers in this century they posed real problems, making severe town surgery necessary in most places. The new thoroughfares, however, in the long run helped both hygienically and commercially. The inhabitants of towns of ten spent only part of their lives there because they had to participate in the harvests, even in such busy places as Flanders. Algerian pirates had no trouble taking Gibraltar in 1540 because, as they knew, all the inhabitants were outside the walls, helping with the grape harvest. (Ref. 4)

In spite of almost constant warfare and religious strife, or perhaps because of the latter, men of education in science, theology, art and medicine seemed to rove from one European country to another. Because many were born in one nation, educated in another and worked finally in a third or fourth location it would be difficult to describe all of them under the sectional divisions of this manuscript. Some of these remarkable men are therefore listed in this paragraph and one might just classify them as "Europeans". Vesalius, born in Belgium, but a student in France and Italy, wrote one of the greatest medical works of all time on the human anatomy. It was published in Basel, Switzerland in 1543 and included many illustrations drawn by the great artist, Titian. In fact it may be said that the year 1543 marks the beginning of the "Scientific Revolution" because of three features:

The anatomical drawings of Andreas Vesalius
the translation of Greek mathematics and physics of Archimedes
Copernicus' treatise - "The Revolution of the Heavenly Orbs." (Ref. 5)

Roaming central Europe there was Paracelsus, part quack, part magician, part crazy, but posting some remarkable cures and establishing himself as the father of chemotherapy, as he used chemical drugs in place of vegetable remedies. Georg Agricola was a minerologist and mining engineer of this era. Geography was enhanced as Magellan's crew completed circumnavigation of the globe in 1518. The microscope was invented in 1590, the thermometer in 1592 and the pendulum clock by Huygens, late in the century. Simon Stevinus wrote an epochal treatise on "The Decimal" in 1585, Fracastoro of Verona wrote on syphilis, Ambroise Pare changed many of the concepts of military surgery and modern botany can be said to begin with Leonhard Fuchs of Bavaria. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)

In spite of the advances in medical knowledge, general health in Europe was poor. Of every five children born, two died in infancy and one more died before maturity. The Royal College of Surgeons was established in England in 1505, stimulating medicine there.

By 1600 western physicians knew that scurvy could be prevented by green herbs or citrus fruits, but they were unable to convince the various admiralties. The potato, which was much smaller than that of today, was introduced to Europe through Spain from America about 1534, but it was not well accepted in some areas, some even thinking that the vegetable caused leprosy. After sugar cane had been taken from Africa to South America, the importation of colonial sugar from Brazil and the Caribbean became very significant in international trade. The Portuguese dumping of molasses at Antwerp soon doomed the honey-bee, because the price was so much lower than honey. (Ref. 10, 11) But grain, flour, and bread were the food of Europe. Obtaining bread was the major preoccupation of all and whenever the price went up, violence was threatened. (Ref. 12)

To understand the political intrigues of a very complicated Europe in this century one must realize that there were eight different, powerful factions present, which may be enumerated as follows:

Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor and King of Spain
The nobles of Germany
The Protestants of Germany and later of France
Francis I, King of France
The nobles of France
The Pope
Henry VIII, King of England
The Turks

There was almost constant warfare and strife throughout the continent, and these eight factions lined up in various ways at various times and on various sides, to battle each other. For example, Francis I remained Catholic, but at times helped Protestant nobles in Germany and Charles V at other times, but he also made alliances with the Turks against the emperor and with the Moors against Italy. The pope alternately warred against Charles V and then was on his side. Henry VIII backed the French part of the time and Charles and the Germans at other times. (Ref. 13) It is hoped that in the following paragraphs some of these complications may be partially unraveled.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

The Mediterranean was no longer able to feed itself and it had to buy Baltic grain so that there was a resulting movement of Spanish silver (from America) to north Europe. The Mediterranean world was now always close to famine and this tended to dictate the course of world events, including the politics and wars. (Ref. 14)

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

In this century the Turks ran the Venetians out of Cyprus but the latter held on to their other possessions. In 1522 Suleiman the Magnificent appeared off Rhodes with 700 warships containing an army of 200,000. Although the Knights Hospitallers, with about 500 knights and 6,000 soldiers, held out for 6 months, they finally had to withdraw. A few years later the Holy Roman Emperor Charles V gave the Knights the islands of Malta and Gozo for their headquarters and they henceforth were known as the "Knights of Malta". Suleiman attacked them also on Malta in 1565 with 373 warships and 40,000 men. Terrible warfare continued for nearly 5 months and about 2/3 of the attackers were killed and only about 600 of the 9,000 defenders were left alive and unwounded, but they held. Turkish sea-power was crippled by this defeat. The Knights regrouped, started work on a new capital city and a great hospital. (Ref. 15, 16)

GREECE AND UPPER BALKANS

All of the Balkan area, including Greece, was under nominal control of the Ottoman Turks, but in some areas there was considerable local autonomy. At the end of the century (1593) when the Turks were again at war with Austria, Sigismund Bathory, Prince of Transylvania (central Romania) sided with the Austrians. The emperor, however, took Transylvania from Bathory and then Moldavia from Michael, to dominate this area for the remainder of the century. In the more southern areas a feudal aristocracy maintained estates and fiefs through many generations. (Ref. 17, 18) Although some Greek families and merchants living in Constantinople and coastal cities, such as Smyrna, were very prosperous, Greece itself sank into obscurity and poverty. (Ref. 19)

The eastern Balkans were a great source of cattle for Central Europe and Italy, sending some 200,000 head each year. (Ref. 20) Even so, as in Eastern Europe, large areas moved back into a "second" serfdom - producing raw materials only - not finished goods. Idria, in the Julian Alps of Yugoslavia, became an important source of mercury, which was shipped clear to America for use in the silver mining process. The Austrian state took over these mines as a monopoly, in 1580. (Ref. 21)

ITALY

France and Spain had begun to fight over possession of Italy at the end of the last century, when French armies under Charles VIII invaded, using new batteries of light, mobile, bronze, field artillery, firing iron cannon balls. "Modern warfare" might be said to have begun in great battles at Ravenna in 1512 and Marignano in 1515. (Ref. 22) "The peninsula then became a theater of war where foreign powers competed for control of the Italians' superior wealth and skill."1 For awhile the stronger city-states held out, as for example in 1508, when the Venetians stood against the League of Cambrai, which included Pope Julius II, Emperor Maximilian and the kings of France and Spain. Even Rome did not escape the terror of foreign invasion. In 1527 Emperor Charles sent the Duke of Bourbon south against the papal forces and the Venetians, with Spanish troops and German mercenaries. When the Duke reached the gates of Rome, he asked permission to march through, was ref used and so fought his way into the city. Although Bourbon was killed, his men slaughtered every man, woman and child they encountered on the streets. The pope and his cardinals fled, while looting went on for 12 days, stopped only by the promise of large monetary settlements from the Catholic hierarchy. In general, the Italian cities hated each other, yet managed to support each other against invaders. (Ref. 23)

The primacy of Italian cities further declined as the Mediterranean became the scene of struggles between the two power-houses of the time - the Spanish Habsburgs and the Ottoman Turks. Milan became ruled by a Spanish governor; Naples, Sicily and Sardinia by Spanish viceroys. Genoa retained its western colony of Corsica, but only after a long revolt late in the century (1551-1569), with the insurgents receiving help from the Turks. Otherwise Genoa, too, was tied economically to Spain. This link with wealthy Spain and the richness of the town of Genoa, itself, did not alleviate the wretchedness of the lower class. The homeless poor of Genoa sold themselves as galley slaves every winter. (Ref. 25) One redeeming feature was an attempt at rejuvenation of the old "Champagne" fairs, which had first moved to Geneva, then to Lyons and finally now to Piacenza, near Genoa. It cannot be denied that it was mainly Genoese who financed the credit operations allowing Spain and others to develop the great trade operations with the New World, at least up until 1568. After that the Piacenza fairs centralized the Genoese business transactions and international payments. (Ref. 26)

Venice was threatened by land and sea, but struggled to stay independent, although it had frequent famines with people begging and often dying in the public square. The entire population was also temporarily incapacitated in 1588 by what was later called "grippe". Even the Grand Council was completely empty. The disease then spread to Milan, France, Spain and even the Americas. (Ref. 27) The famine, felt throughout the Mediterranean, was partially relieved in 1591 when wealthy merchants organized a spectacular diversion of northern ships, loaded with wheat and rye, into the Mediterranean. Portuguese merchants of Antwerp were among those making allegedly 300% profit on these ships, but that did not matter to starving Italians. (Ref. 28)

Naples was one of the largest cities of Europe and an extravagant place, with the Neapolitan nobles striving to keep favor at the court of the Spanish viceroy. (Ref. 29) In general, southern Italy was Spain's and northwest Italy belonged to France. The other great powers, England and Germany, by remote measures changed sides from year to year and there was much confusion. In the end, Italy was devastated and financially exhausted. To add insult to injury, both syphilis2 and typhus appeared in Europe during the long series of Italian wars, lasting from 1494 to 1559. In Italy syphilis was called the "French Disease"; the Spanish called it "Naples Disease". Gonorrhea was also rampant. Typhus swept the peninsula in 1505 and again in 1528 while the first great influenza epidemic struck in 1510 and plague was in Rome in 1522. (Ref. 30, 31, 32)

The papacy had its own history in this century. Caesar Borgia, son of Pope Alexander VI and a former cardinal, attempting to save Italy for the papacy in 1502 in his capacity as the Duke of the Romagna, joined the French in an attack on Naples to free it from the Spanish. The new pope, Julius II (1503-1513), frustrated his schemes, however, and he then turned to the Spanish side. Julius II, one of the greater popes, was a warrior and somewhat morose. He was followed by happy Leo X, who believed that joy should be unconfined, but who failed to realize the seriousness of the developing theological situation. Rome reached new heights of liberty and sexuality. Martin Luther came, saw Rome, was shocked and went home to Germany to initiate the reformation. (Ref. 34)

In contrast to the turmoil on the political and religious scenes, however, the first half of this century also marked the apogee of the Renaissance, with intellectual and artistic supremacy. Michelangelo and Raphael continued their works and Titian added his classical art. Leonardo da Vinci lived well into this century, now residing chiefly in Milan and supported by the French King Louis XII, who controlled Milan most of this period. Subsequently he was subsidized by Francis I. It was also the time of Aretino, Santi, Cellini and last but not least Machiavelli, the amoral, political philosopher, who undoubtedly influenced the monarchies of the world for years to come. Wealth and urban development was concentrated chiefly in the Mediterranean and in Italy in particular, with the only cities of more than 100,000 in the western world being Naples, with 300,000, Venice, Milan, Constantinople and Paris. Rice was now grown throughout the peninsula, actually as an emergency foodstuff and the hard work involved began to make a sharp demarcation between the proletariat laborers and the capitalist owner. (Ref. 35) Communications were difficult, as evidenced by the fact that a message took 27 days to go from Venice to London, 46 days to Lisbon, 37 days to Constantinople, 80 days to Damascus, 65 days to Alexandria and even some 22 days just to go to Palermo, Sicily. Even so, Tuscany, Venice and Genoa moved tens of thousands of tons of grain from the Baltic and the Black Sea, through international merchants and letter of exchange in Nurenberg and Antwerp. (Ref. 36) Venice had commerce with the Hanseatic League through Flanders and Genoese merchants had similar connections as well as contact all over the Mediterranean and particularly at Seville, as we have seen. Florence bankers of the Medici family still controlled the capital in most northern European capitals. However, when Cosimo de Medici created a guard of 2,000 horsemen in Florence in 1531, the cost of the horses ruined him. (Ref. 37, 38, 39)

People, in general, were not what we might call "cultured" in the 16th century. Silver forks were used at table in Venice about 1581, but the custom did not last long and they were not used elsewhere, except in France. At this time the potato, corn, beans and squash spread to northern Italy. (Ref. 40, 41)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY AND AUSTRIA

Germany consisted of a number of autonomous states and in the beginning of the century, at least, Austria was just another German-speaking sub-kingdom, all a part of the Holy Roman Empire. As noted previously, the "Electors" of the various German states chose an emperor, who was nominally over all, although his actual power over any particular state was probably little or none. Maximilian I (Habsburg) of Austria opened the century as that emperor and made his capital at Innsbruck. He married into the House of Burgundy and had his son marry Juana of Castile and Aragon, as well as arranging that his grandchildren marry into the royal families of Bohemia and Hungary. Thus, at the end of his reign, the Habsburgs were well entrenched in all of central and western Europe and their home base of Austria was a power to be reckoned with. Maximilians' grandson followed him as king of Austria as Ferdinand I, a ruler who had constant troubles with the Turks on the eastern border. In 1529 the Ottomans were actually under the walls of Vienna, where they were supplied by camel trains. But there were also peasant revolts in both Germany and Austria in 1525 and latent social war continued for more than another century. Peasants everywhere shared more or less constant poverty and low living standards, yet managed to snatch a precarious existence from the soil. (Ref. 42)

Ferdinand's brother, Charles of Ghent, raised in Flanders, inherited the throne of Spain, where he was known as Charles (or Carlos) I. In 1520 he was chosen as the Holy Roman Emperor as Charles V and by 1550 the Habsburg Empire was at its height, including all of Spain, the Balearic Islands, Italy (excepting the papal states and Venice), Sardinia, Sicily, the Netherlands, all of Germany, Austria, Hungary (that part not held by the Turks), Bohemia and parts of Serbia. On the European continent proper, only Portugal and France and the small areas of Italy previously mentioned, were out of the empire. In addition there were vast overseas holdings in the Americas.

The Fuggers, with headquarters at Augsburg, furnished the money for Charles V and their operations stretched from Danzig to Lisbon and from Budapest to Rome, to Moscow and even to Chile, where their interests extended to silver, copper and mercury mining. Jakob Fugger had learned double-entry bookkeeping in Venice while it was unknown in Germany at that time. The Augsburg merchants also owned silver mines in Bohemia and the Alps and their city rivalled Antwerp as a trade center, particularly for central and eastern European communities. In this connection we must also mention the Welsers of Augsburg, whose financial dealings also penetrated Europe, the Mediterranean and even the New World. But the state always kept a hand in. Augustus I of Saxony owned 2,822 Kuxen (shares) in the mines of his state. These various mines brought together for the first time huge concentrations of labor. In 1550, in the mines of the Tyrol there were 12,000 workers. 500 to 600 men were used solely to keep pumping water that threatened the tunnels. In the last half of the century, however, mining in central Europe declined, apparently because of falling profits, destruction of forestland with resulting high cost of fuel and increased wage demands. (Ref. 43, 44, 45, 46, 47)

NOTE: Insert Map 57. Europe in 1556. The Habsburg Dominions

One of the very colorful and productive personalities of this period was Theophrastus Bombastus von Hohenheim, commonly called Paracelsus (d. 1541) He obtained a doctor's degree at Ferrara in Italy but then barnstormed Germany, denouncing the medical classics and their followers and actually adding something to pharmacology, although he still thought disease was caused by influences of the stars and planets. The "sweating sickness", leprosy and epidemic chorea, which had been prominent diseases of the preceding century, were beginning to disappear, but syphilis was common and gonorrhea rampant. These two venereal diseases were directly responsible for the suppression of communal baths, which had been popular in Germany. Also becoming more common were typhus, diphtheria, small-pox, measles and scurvy (among northern sailors). Ergotism reached endemic levels, bringing insanity and death to thousands who ate bread made from the infected rye. (Ref. 48, 49) Meat was plentiful, with herds of up to 20,000 half-wild cattle coming into Germany at Buttsedt, near Weimar. Others arrived from Switzerland. Wild horses - that is, horses that had returned to a wild state, although not usually eaten - were well distributed all over Europe and particularly in northwest Germany, Alsace and the Vosges. There was an extensive copper mining industry at Mansfeld in Saxony. Because of the poor agriculture in the mountain regions of Swabia about Lake Constance, the peasants there had become linen-workers. (Ref. 50)

The various German municipalities and states remained more or less independent under their own dukes or princes. The Margrave of Brandenburg ruled extensive territories between the Netherlands and Poland. The apparent precocity of some of these medievals can be a source of continued amazement to us in the 20th century. The Margrave's brother, Albert of Brandenburg, was in 1515, at the age of 25, Archbishop of Mageburg and Bishop of Halberstadt and trying to become Archbishop of Mainz, which would automatically make him one of the seven Electors of the empire, like his brother. To help him buy dispensations to obtain this Archbishopric, which was to cost 10,000 ducats, the pope issued an indulgence to anyone who contributed money for the building of a new cathedral in Rome - such indulgence to shorten the stay in purgatory for the contributor and all his relations. Secretly, half the money was to go, not to the cathedral, but to the Fuggers, who would loan Albert the fee for his Archbishopric. The duty of raising the money in Germany was entrusted to Johann Tetzel, about whom we shall hear more later. (Ref. 51)

There was an increasing close connection between Brandenburg and East Prussia and in 1539 the Elector of Brandenburg (a Hohenzollern) was awarded the rights of co-vassalage over East Prussia, together with Albert of Hohenzollern, who had now become the Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights. Bavaria was already ruled by the Wittelsbach family. (Ref. 52)

The great story of this century in Germany, however, is that of the Reformation. Although we have seen the previews of the revolt against the Catholic Church in Wiclif and Huss, the true Reformation began here with Martin Luther. The stage was set when Pope Leo X issued the most famous of all indulgences - the one mentioned above regarding money to finish the new St Peters Church and secretly to indirectly finance an Archbishopric for Albert of Brandenburg. The Dominican, Tetzel, was sent out into Germany to peddle Absolution of all sins, past and present, release of relatives from Purgatory and various other indulgences for various sums of money. When Tetzel approached Saxony, the local ruler, Frederick the Wise, asked Martin Luther, Catholic priest and professor at the University of Wittenberg, for approval of Tetzel 's procedures. Luther refused approval; Tetzel denounced Luther; Luther countered with the posting of 95 theses condemning various practices of the pope and the Reformation had started. This was in 1517.

Martin Luther was a complex man, brought up under the sternest discipline and plagued all his life with the devil, demons and witches. His reformed theology was chiefly against the popes and their corrupt hierarchy. He argued for the Bible against papal decree. He thought that not good works, but faith in Christ alone, brought salvation from Hell and that this was preordained and only a few could make it. The pope issued Bulls against Luther and Luther wrote books against the pope - in German, so the people could read them. His theology went back to Augustine, taking the New Testament very literally. But he also revered the Old Testament, which he translated into German. His God was more like the old Yahweh of the Hebrews. He felt that priests should marry and eventually did so, himself. As he got older he got more and more intolerant, vehement and militant, damned all knowledge and reason and would have everyone return to the old, simple, agrarian life. In the end he declared Zwingli and other Protestants who had appeared on the scene, as heretics. He defended the divine rights of kings and glorified war as the work of God. He exalted the state as the sole source of order and gave a premonition of Imperial Germany to come. At the time, however, German unity was hampered, not furthered, but we are getting ahead of our chronological story.

A year after Charles V became emperor in 1521, the Diet of Worms was called to decide what to do with Luther. The resulting "Edict of Worms" made Luther an outcast and ordered his works burned. He went into seclusion for a year, but the revolution continued anyway in a peaceful way for awhile. In 1524, however, the Peasants' War developed as 30,000 impoverished people in southern Germany started a social revolt against nobles and priests. Religion was only part of the cause, but out of this, flames burst out over half of Germany. Luther finally tried to stop the revolt, but it continued anyway for another year in Austria. There was a terrific loss of property and life and the reformation, itself, was almost lost in this war, because in spite of Luther, the nobles associated this class revolt with the reformation movement. The revolt was finally extinguished by slaughters and massacres, but by 1527 the Lutheran "heresy" had become orthodox in half of Germany. Economic factors (there was now no money going to Italy) and the pressure of the Turks, which kept the emperor and his troops busy, allowed the Reformation to succeed. In 1531 the two religious forces, one represented by the Catholic League and the other by the Protestant Schmalkaldic League, had many conferences but made little progress in conciliation. From this time on the princes and nobles, rather than the theologicans, were the Protestant leaders, for the issues concerned property and power far more than dogma and ritual. (Ref. 53)

The true German religious war, as contrasted to the Peasants' War, began in 1546, a few months after Luther's death. The Protestant Saxon army was badly beaten at Lochau.

By 1547 a kind of settlement was reached but in 1552 all Germany was at war again. Charles V abdicated, giving Germany to his brother Ferdinand and Spain and the Netherlands to his son Philip. Charles, himself, died in 1558 in a monastery where he had been living in royal splendor. The greatness of the Holy Roman Empire died with Charles.

The religious Peace of Augsburg, negotiated by Ferdinand, marks the end of the Reformation period. The adopted formula of 1555 recognized the legality of the status quo - in both religious and territorial sovereignty. Ecclesiastical officials had the right to convert to Protestantism, but they could not secularize their property. The only real victory of the Lutherans in this peace treaty was a legal recognition of their existence. Four factors colored the second half of this 16th century in Germany, as recorded by Rodes (Ref. 54):

The Counter-Reformation: This really began with Pope Paul III. The final Council of Trent convened in 1562, controlled by the Jesuits and it reaffirmed all the basic Catholic doctrine. There were no concessions to the Protestants and the Council did not reconcile the two faiths. Actually the Catholic Church was immensely strengthened as it then established the "Catholic Index"
Disunity of the Protestants: "Disunity among the  Protestants became particularly evident in the distrust and even hatred between the established Lutheran faith and the new Reformed Sect of Calvinism that began to spread across Germany in the 1550s."3 Calvin's predestination and his doctrine of attributing sovereignty to the religious community rather than to the state, divided the groups. There were many decapitations of Protestants by Protestants, as well as by Catholics. Lutheranism began to assume primarily a defensive attitude, while Calvinism, militant and aggressive, kept the expansive spirit alive and completed the conversion of Holland and Scotland while also retaining England in the Protestant camp
Foreign Influences on German Affairs: Most important was the division of the Habsburg inheritance. King Philip II (Spain) was the wealthiest and most powerful ruler of Europe and his troops frequently interfered in Germany in behalf of Catholicism. In addition, German princes continued their various alliances with foreign powers. The German aristocracy rushed to adopt foreign customs and culture, particularly French
Lack of Political Leadership: In Germany, only one ruler stood out in this period, Duke Maximilian I in the Duchy of Bavaria and he did not come into power until 1597.

HUNGARY

It was a bad century for Hungary, beginning with a great revolt of the peasants, under George Dozsa. This uprising against the aristocracy was finally put down in a sea of blood by John Zapolya. Immediately the Werbocz Code was proclaimed, which made the serfdom of the peasants perpetual. A strike by Hungarian miners in 1525 and 1526 started that industry on a downward slide. (Ref. 56)

The Turks, under Suleiman, defeated and killed the Hungarian king in 1526 and overran the nation with an army of 150,000 men. There followed a period of division of the country with a narrow western area remaining as Royal Hungary under the Austrian Habsburg, Ferdinand, and the remainder of the country choosing John Zapola4 to reign as a puppet king under Suleiman in one portion, while the far eastern area was directly under Turkish rule. Later the sultan took the central portion under his rule also, leaving only Transylvania to John Sigismund, Zapolya's heir. Under the Turks, Hungary was devastated and the ultimate result was to give psychological impetus to the eventual union of Hungary to Bohemia and Austria under the Habsburg Dynasty, which was to last for 400 years. (Ref. 57, 58, 59)

The Reformation came into Hungary through German immigrants. By 1550 it seemed that all Hungary would become Protestant, but rivalry between Lutheranism and Calvinism tore the movement in two and Catholicism again became supreme.

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

In 1526 Emperor Charles V's brother-in-law, King Ladislas of Bohemia (and also of Hungary), was defeated by the Turks at Mohacz and he drowned in the Danube while trying to escape. He was succeeded by Charles' brother, Ferdinand. In general Bohemia had weak kings in this century, with the nobles refusing financial support to the throne. The aristocracy as a whole, however, extended its power and peasantry sank back into serfdom. On the religious scene we must recall that through the Hussite movement, Bohemiawas actually Protestant even before the time of Luther and by 1560 2/3 of the population was definitely so. In the following year, however, the Habsburg Ferdinand introduced the Jesuits and the tide turned back to the Catholic Creed. The accession of Archduke Ferdinand (later emperor) began the long Austrian and Habsburg domination of Bohemia.

SWITZERLAND

As the century opened Switzerland gained some territory from Italy south of the Alps and fought against France, but the Swiss were finally defeated at Marignana, in 1515. The country was still having difficulty "pulling itself together". The Swiss were great fighters, as evidenced by their extensive use over all of Europe as mercenary forces, but they still did not always pull together as one nation. In 1533 Geneva, which had previously been a part of Savoy, became independent and in 1536 Swiss armies took Vaud from Savoy. (Ref. 61) The Alps continued to be for the most part untamed and horses that had returned to the wild state were distributed throughout the mountains.

This country was host to two great religious reformers, one the native Zwingli of Zurich and the other John Calvin, born French, but active in theology in Switzerland by 1534. Zwingli had a humanist education, became a Catholic priest in 1506 and by 1508 was attacking the principles of indulgences, clerical celibacy and the Mass. By 1517 he called for a religion based entirely on the Bible, and in 1521 he proclaimed openly for the Reformation, which was already well under way in Germany. Zwingli differed from Luther only in believing that the Mass was entirely symbolic. Eventually he became the head of both the new church and the city-state of Zurich. The local contests with surrounding Catholics became actual battles and Zwingli was killed in one of them. Five Catholic Cantons had banded together against Zurich and the Reformation movement and the resulting conflict greatly weakened the Swiss Confederation for the remaining part of the century. Anabaptism arose among members of Zwingli's circle, crystallizing as a distinct variety of Protestantism in 1525, when Conrad Grebel and George Blaurock re-baptized their group and called themselves "Brethren". After 20 years of persecution, the sect received its permanent doctrine from Menno Simons. Their three fundamental principles were:

adult Baptism
separation from the world
literal observance of Christ's Commandments

NOTE: Insert Map 48. The Swiss Confederation 1526

Upon attaining an essentially independent status in 1533, Geneva had allied itself with the Cantons of Fribourg and Bern and had accepted the Reformation preached by Guillaume Farel. Calvin came there to preach in the middle of the century, after Zwingli's death, and wrote the book The Principles of the Christian Religion, which was modeled after Luther and followed the ideas of Paul and St. Augustine. He put these thoughts into an eccliastical doctrine and established the Reformed and Presbyterian Churches, which won the allegiance of hundreds of millions of men in Switzerland, France, Scotland, England and North America. His theology was dismal - this life is a vale of misery and tears and it would be better to die immediately at birth. He agreed with Zwingli on the Mass; he set rigid moral laws; and made the church supreme again over the state. He was hated by Luther over the single point of- doctrine about the interpretation of the Mass. In later years, Calvin became more and more intolerant and had Michael Servitus burned at the stake for being too liberal and humanistic. (Ref. 62)

WESTERN EUROPE

McNeill (Ref. 63) says that Europeans of the Atlantic seaboard developed command of all oceans of the world within a half century because of three factors: (1) A deep-rooted pugnacity and recklessness. (2) Complex military technology, particularly naval. (3) A population inured to a variety of diseases long endemic in the old world. From 1560 or 1580 population in the western world, especially in France, Spain and Italy, again became too dense and eventually poverty ensued. (Ref. 64) Western Europe, in general, tended to be somewhat antagonistic to the Genoese, who were the chief "capitalists" with the most money, ready "to buy everything up". (Ref. 65) This may be analogous to more recent situations there regarding Americans. (Ref. 66)

SPAIN

In a little more than a half century Spanish institutions and civilization were impressed upon an area larger than the whole of Europe. The Spanish army was the most successful of Europe, with even nobles in its ranks, carrying handguns. Their real pride, however, was the cavalry and after 1525 they dominated Europe until the middle of the next century. Long before that, Spain was spending 70% of its revenue on weapons. For the infantry one man in twelve was conscripted, but he too became a professional. (Ref. 67)

Isabelle, the great queen, died in 1504 and Ferdinand, whose natural Machevellian tendencies had been tempered by Isabelle, died in 1516. In that short time, however, he was totally involved in European politics, goading Henry VIII into war with France and even talking Henry into sending 7,000 men to San Sebastian in 1512 to drive the French from Navarre and conquer Guienne. The attack was premature and a dismal failure. Later, in 1518, the French advanced again, capturing the Spanish garrison at Pamplona, a battle in which the Spanish officer Ignatius de Loyola received a severe leg wound. During his convalescence he reformed his life and founded the Society of Jesus, as we have previously noted. (Ref. 68) Ferdinand's grandson, Charles of Ghent, became Carlos (Charles) I of Spain and Sicily and because the young man's other grandfather had been Maximilian of Austria, he also became king of the Netherlands. As noted above he later became Holy Roman Emperor as Charles V and thus ruled Germany and Austria also. At first Charles could speak no Spanish and he tried to bring an entire Flemish court with him to Spain. Almost immediately after arrival he had to leave to go to Germany and he left Cardinal Adrian of Utrecht to act as regent. In his absence the nobles rose up against him in the Revolt of the Communeros, but this was soon transformed into a class war of commoners against nobles, so that the latter eventually had to support the king to save themselves.

By the time Charles returned with German troops, the rebellion had already pretty well burned itself out and Spain became an absolute monarchy.

Charles abdicated all titles in 1556 while in Brussels and his son Philip II took over as king of Spain. It was Philip who sent the great Spanish Armada against England in 1588 to avenge the death of Mary of Scots and to restore Catholicism to England, but as we shall see shortly, he failed in this endeavor. This preoccupation with northern Europe was new to Spain, basically a Mediterranean country, and it happened only as a result of the dynastic accidents and manipulations of the Habsburgs. Philip II ruled more of the earth's surface than anyone since the beginning of history, but all of the silver from Peru and Mexico had not kept the Spanish court from sinking ever deeper into debt, a lot of the money disappearing into the conflicts in the Netherlands. The Spanish court repudiated its debts to the Fuggers on 5 separate occasions between 1557 and 1627 and those bankers progressively withdrew from financing governments. In 1580 the Spanish cavalry, under the Duke of Alva, quickly conquered Portugal and from then on for the rest of the century Spain and Portugal were united under a common Iberian crown, which ruled three empires - the silver empire of Spanish America, the spice empire of the Indian Ocean and the sugar empire of the south Atlantic. From 1,000 to 2,000 Spaniards left Spain for America each year during this century. (Ref. 69, 70, 71, 72)

We must add some details about Philip's war with England. Actually he feared this, but was egged on by the pope and some of his advisors, so that eventually he was enticed into gathering a great fleet of ships from all over Iberia and Italy, for the purpose of holding the English fleet at bay while the Duke of Parma led Spanish troops, which were then in Belgium, across the channel to restore Catholicism to England. Provisioning the great fleet was a problem never adequately solved, partly because of Spain's worsening financial situation. A raid along the southern coast by Sir Francis Drake, which among other insults resulted in the destruction of about 1,700 tons of hoops and pipe staves, which had been destined to be made into casks to carry 25,000 to 30,000 tons of water, wine, salt meat, salt fish and biscuits, did not help matters. The substitute, green barrel staves, which the Spaniards then had to use, made leaky and quickly fouled casks.

In late May of 1588, under a somewhat inexperienced and reluctant Captain-General Medina Sidonia, the Spanish armada finally set off from Lisbon. In the first line were 10 Portuguese and 10 Castillian galleons, reinforced by 4 great, armed West India merchant- men. Then there were 4 galleasses of Naples manned by 300 soldiers and sailors, 300 rowers and 50 guns apiece. The second line had 4 squadrons of 10 large merchantmen, each heavily armed, and attached to them were 34 light, fast ships and 23 awkward hulks acting as freighters and supply ships, making a total of 130 vessels. Included in the personnel were 180 friars and priests. The armada carried 2,431 cannon (of which 934 were iron, instead of bronze), 7,000 arquebuses, 1,000 muskets and 123,790 bullets and shot. (Ref. 73)

The fleet was at first becalmed for several days just off the Portuguese coast, then scattered by a storm, with the loss of 2 galleasses and 28 other major ships, while still others were badly battered. In addition, there was already much fever, scurvy and dysentery aboard and the green-stave casks were already producing spoiled food and water.

Nevertheless, the battle was eventually joined at the mouth of the English channel on July 31, 15885, with the longer range cannon of the British ships holding the Spanish out of their gun range and preventing grappling and boarding as the southerners were wont to do. After various engagements in the next several days the Spanish lost several ships, some aground and some sunk and/or exploded when the English launched a "fire-ship" attack. By August 8th the Spanish were almost out of ammunition and food and on August 12th the remaining ships turned tail and escaped into the North Sea. The English did not follow, although the Spanish command expected them to do so at any moment.

The damaged remnants of the great armada sailed up around the north end of the British Isles, carrying a load of sick and starving sailors. Some 17 ships are said to have sought refuge on the Irish coast and perished there. Thousands must have drowned- and those that survived a landing were battered to death by the Irish or turned over to English soldiers. Finally in September, 1588 some 44 vessels straggled into the harbor at Santander, Spain, a fleet shattered by battle, weather, sickness and starvation. On the flagship San Martin alone, besides those killed in battle, there were 180 dead of scurvy, typhus or influenza, aggravated by hunger and thirst. More died daily in port while the unprepared countryside people tried to gather food and clothes and arrange hospital facilities. (Ref. 74)

In spite of that armada fiasco, Spanish merchant ships still brought American treasure back to Spain, actually in greater quantities between 1588 and 1603 than in any other 15 year period. The defeat had not significantly altered the command of the seas commercially. Seville was actually prosperous as never before and 7% of the population was slave. Black Africans, white Moriscos and Moors from Granada and North Africa and Indians from America all could be seen in the bustling streets. (Ref. 75) The battles of the armada were the first of their kind with the massive ships and their long range cannon, but as far as actual numbers of vessels and men were concerned, this has been over-emphasized in many histories. (Ref. 76)

In this century the Inquisition continued with the ecclesiastical attack on witchcraft at its height. The Inquisition was a cause as well as an effect of intense Catholicism in Spain and it held the Reformation to a minor skirmish in that country. After the Jews were run out, the Moors came under the Inquisition scrutiny and 3,000,000 of them left Spain and returned to North Africa. In this exodus of Jews and Moors, Spain lost an incalculable treasure and it has never made up for it intellectually and other ways. Thereafter, knowing only one religion, people submitted completely to their clergy and surrendered the right to think except within the limits of the traditional faith. Spain chose to remain medieval, with little intellectual activity. (Ref. 77) One bright light was to be found in the Navarrese, Miguel Serveto, who discovered that blood was pumped to the lungs by the arteries. But, as mentioned in a paragraph above, he was then burned alive in Geneva for some alleged religious eccentricities in letters he wrote to Calvin. The imprint of the Catholic king's world-wide empire can be noted in the general acceptance all over Europe at that time of the black, solemn, short capes and high collars with a small ruff. (Ref. 78, 79)

The potato6 was brought to Spain from Peru about 1565. The peninsula continued to raise tremendous numbers of sheep, exporting wool to Holland, Germany and Italy.

Very important in this industry was the Mesta, a guild of sheep owners, which arranged the movement of the herds of sheep from summer pastures in the north to winter quarters in the south, preventing landowners from fencing across the routes, ensuring the marking of the sheep, fixing the resting places and helping with the- marketing. By 1526 there were 3,400,000 sheep moving each year some 200 to 300 miles up and down Spain, averaging 5 miles a day. The crown protected the Mesta and this centralization prevented the birth of anything like a free-enterprise system and blocked progress in Spain. It is even probable that the Mesta more or less forced the Spanish kings to expel both the Moors and the Jews, because the latter groups were more concerned with farming crops than with livestock. In spite of sheep and potatoes, the years 1599 and 1600 were years of famine and plague, which decimated Andalusia and Castile. (Ref. 80, 81) The government finances did not help the overall situation. By 1600 40% of the government's income went for servicing old debts. (Ref. 82) International capitalism had successfully captured the opportunity which the discovery of America had given Spain. There was a three-tier pyramid: the base consisted of peasants, shepherds, silk-producers, artisans and peddlers; above them were the capitalists of Castile, who controlled those local people; and finally, running everything from above, were the agents of the Fuggers and soon of the Genoese. (Ref. 83)

PORTUGAL

This was a golden age for Portugal, as the Age of Imperialism began with the development of an extensive empire. In addition to Brazil, the Portuguese had established a colony with a governor in India and had set up commercial relations with China. In 1509 they won a decisive battle with the Moslems for control of the Arabian Sea, off the Indian port of Diu. They had heavy ships with cannon and the Moslems were short of metal and under armed. As a result of all this, Portugal had virtually taken over the spice trade from the Venetians. In 1523 alone, some 100 tons of ginger and 2,000 tons of pepper had gone into Germany from Lisbon. By the middle of the century the Portuguese had a string of more than 50 forts and factories from Sofola on the east African coast to Nagasaki, Japan. (Ref. 84, 85) Strangely enough the Portuguese merchantmen carried no artillery, even though French privateers on the Atlantic possessed it. The Portuguese carracks were the giants of the seas, however, with a displacement of up to 2,000 tons7 and carrying up to 800 persons. (Ref. 86)

At home, the Avis Dynasty continued with Manoel I the Great ruling until 1521, then Joao III, followed by Sebastian I (1557-78). The latter undertook a new religious war against the Moors and was killed in the process, ending the dynasty. The Avis had been good rulers and their empire had had good administrators so that Lisbon had become a center of wealth, luxury and a depository for Asiatic goods. The only cloud on the horizon had resulted from Manoel's borrowing from Genoese bankers to equip his Asian-bound ships. Interest on these debts and agents' dishonesty cut heavily into the trade profits and the kings did not do as well as others around them. (Ref. 87)

As the century progressed black slavery, imperial war, corruption at home and other features began to lay the groundwork for decline. An earthquake, which killed 30,000 people in Lisbon in 1531 did not help matters. Following the lead of Spain, Portugal expelled her Jews and soon the Inquisition entered with consequences similar to those in Spain. In the dynastic struggle which followed the end of the Avis Dynasty, the Spanish, under the Duke of Alva, invaded Portugal and defeated a Portuguese contingent in the battle of Alcantara in 1580, near Lisbon, thus allowing the Spanish king, Philip II, to also become the Portuguese monarch, at least in theory. English, Dutch and French forces then began to attack the Portuguese overseas colonies. (Ref. 88, 89, 90)

FRANCE

Louis XII died in 1515 without heirs and the Valois, Francois I, became king and entered in the intrigues of a complicated Europe. Within 8 months he had invaded Italy and defeated a seasoned Swiss mercenary army of the pope near Milan. Venice, still antagonistic to Emperor Maximilian, supported Francois' armies. (Ref. 91) These "Italian Wars" were actually the start of nearly 60 years of warfare of France with Spain, ending in the Peace of Cateau-Cambresis, in 1559. Since Spain was ruled by Charles V, after 1540 Francois entered negotiations that were designed as a three-pronged attack against the Habsburgs, whom he felt to be his greatest antagonist. The triad attack included: (1) Subsidies to German Protestants so that they could attack Charles V from the north. (2) Alliance with the Turks to attack Austria from the east. (3) Launching a campaign with the French army from the west.

The Holy Roman Empire did decline but this was certainly not in any way the result of Francois' manipulations. Actually the French king was held as a prisoner in Madrid by Charles for about a year (1525) and his children were held as hostages much longer. (Ref. 92) It is also true that Francois was so busy with women that he had very little time for administration. He lived lavishly to the extent that he impoverished his people. His sister Marguerite and his mother Louise d'Angouleme of Savoy were very influential in his government and the former was very tolerant religiously, protecting many Protestants as the Reformation began to arrive in France. In 1536 Francois I did occupy the Duchy of Savoy, but by the Peace of Cateau-Cambresis Duke Emmanuel Philibert re-obtained the Duchy, excepting that portion which had been taken by the Swiss. (Ref. 93)

The Reformation was somewhat delayed in this country because of a "concordant" with the pope, allowing the king to appoint and control church officials in the nation. This removed the dominance of Rome, which was such a great factor in Germany's revolt.

Nevertheless, by the second half of the century this did become a political issue that led to the Wars of Religion, France's gravest civil conflict since the Hundred Years War.

Wedged between conflicts were the short reigns of Francois II, first husband of Mary Stuart of Scotland and niece of the Guises, to be mentioned below, and Charles IX. Francois II died of tuberculous meningitis in 1560 a year after he was crowned, while his brother Charles IX died of pulmonary tuberculosis at age 24 years, in 1574. (Ref. 94) From 1559 to 1598 there were8 distinct wars, interrupted by treaties, aggravated by massacres - a muddled, chaotic period, which showed that the French are never crueler than when fighting one another. Huguenot Protestants, taking Calvin's doctrines, became more and more powerful so that by 1561 there were 2,000 Calvinistic churches. This was in the reign of the "boy king", Henri II, son of Francois II and ruling from 1549 to 1559. He was a weak monarch, greatly influenced by Anne de Montmorency, his mistress Diane de Poitiers8 and by Francois and Charles de Guise. Even so, in this period some things were accomplished for France. Calais was finally re-taken from the English and exports of grain, wines, fabrics and woolens gave France a positive trade balance with all its neighbors except one - Italy. Most of the money flowed out through Lyons to Italy for costly silks and velvets, spices, marble and Italian artists' services. (Ref. 95)

Three separate factions began to develop in France: The Valois royalists of Catholic faith, who for awhile tried to be tolerant of the new Protestantism; the strong Catholic faction led by Henry Guise of royal blood from Anjou and Lorraine; and finally the faction of Henri de Navarre of the House of Bourbon and of mixed inheritance from Spanish, Basque, French and Austrian ancestry. Henry Guise had a dual purpose in life - to kill all Huguenots and make himself king of France. Henri de Navarre, a nominal Protestant, also was a claimant to the throne. The destinies of these factions were interwoven with the Spanish-English-Dutch conflict at the end of the century, which we have indirectly mentioned when discussing the Spanish Armada. Henri III, a Valois who had been elected king of Poland, returned to France as king in 1574, on the death of Charles XI. He vacillated on the religious issue and let himself in great part be dominated by his mother Catherine de Medici and his cousin the tricky Duke of Guise, champion of the anti-royalist conspiracy known as the "Holy League", serving the religious interests of the papacy. (Ref. 96, 97, 98, 99, 100)

The antagonisms of the factions just mentioned culminated in 1585 in the last of the 8 wars and carrying the name "The War of the Three Henris". Confusion reigned supreme as Henri III fled to Blois, hoping to get support from the States-General and finding none, he arranged the murder of Henry of Guise and his brother, a cardinal. In retaliation a new revolt of the Catholic party broke out and Henri fled to the camp of Henri of Navarre among the Huguenots, where he was murdered by the monk, Jacques Clement. This left only the Bourbon, Henri of Navarre, but the Catholic group refused to recognize his succession to king and named another. But Henri besieged Paris, defeating the Duke of Mayenne and the Spanish Duke of Parma and finally, supported by somewhat moderate Catholics who wished a strong national monarchy, he was crowned Henri IV, King of France.

NOTE: Insert Map 62. France During the Huguenot Wars 1562-92

He returned to the Catholic faith, but in 1598 issued the Edict of Nantes, which gave the Huguenots equal political rights, although not complete religious freedom. This ended the French religious-civil conflicts, often called "The Huguenot Wars". (Ref. 101, 102)

The large amount of space we have just devoted to the national political scene in France is not to be interpreted in a way to detract from the continued independence of certain towns. Local citizenship was of ten zealously guarded. In Marseilles it was necessary to have 10 years residence, possess property and to have married a local girl before citizenship could be granted. (Ref. 103) All through the feudal period in Europe, there was little or no sense of "country" or of patriotism, because each man's fidelity was given only to his immediate superior in the feudal chain. Even the word patrie, meaning "patriotism", was not used by French writers until this 16th century. (Ref. 104) It is of interest that amid all the national strife, we find an early example of workers revolt against management in the big printing strikes in Lyons in 1539 and 1572. There were about 100 printing presses with about 1,000 workers who thought that new technology in updated presses would result in a decrease in the number of workers. So they beat up blacklegs, distributed leaflets and took their master to court and formed their own society. In both strikes the workers gained little, but their actions certainly foreshadowed modern activities. (Ref. 105)

Only in this century did Paris become France's largest city, with 400,000 people and it was a trade center attracting job hunters and adventurers. The all important wood for construction and burning arrived in Paris in boatloads and giant floats, some 250 feet long and maneuvering these under the arches of bridges took great skill. Charcoal came from the forest of Othe via Sens. A great carrageway was constructed for the king from Paris to Orleans. (Ref. 106) The French aptitude for high fashion was shown late in the century when the effeminate Henri III allegedly wore 6,000 yards of lace at the 1577 Estates General at Blois. By the end of the century the great market, Halles, had been reconstructed and restored to old levels of commercial activity, making a "renaissance" of a type. This must not be taken to mean that everywhere there was prosperity, however. In 1587 some 17,000 poverty-stricken people presented themselves under the walls of Paris. (Ref. 107) In some periods Parisian food supply was very inadequate and some reports state that the dying people were eating dead dogs, garbage, rats, and even children9. There were eleven general famines in France in this century. (Ref. 108, 109, 110)

Ambroise Pare, surgeon to four kings, has been called the "Father of Modern Surgery". In military medicine he gave up the use of the cautery and used soothing dressings. Trained only by apprenticeship to a barber and then a wound dresser, he revolutionized the treatment of wounds. He wrote the treatise "A Universal Surgery" in 1561 and published his famous Ten Books of Surgery in 1564. (Ref. 112, 113) The political decline of the Valois royal family may have been due to syphilis, which had been brought back by French soldiers after a military fray against Naples, in 1494. The French army also brought typhus back from Naples during another excursion there in 1526. In another vein, it is interesting that when Henri Valois was besieging Paris, just prior to his becoming King Henri IV in 1590, Parisians used carrier pigeons to keep in touch with the outside world, a custom in use at times since the ancient Greeks. (Ref. 114)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

Throughout most of this century the Lowlands were a part of the Habsburg dominion. In the first half, Antwerp, by virtue of its crucial location, seemed to be the leading city commercially, with trade routes to Bergen, Stockholm, Reval, Danzig and all points south down even to Seville and Algiers. This was based greatly on a luxury trade, however, and with a shift of the European staple market and the rapid increase of seaborne trade, Amsterdam became the center of commerce. The sacking of Antwerp in 1576 by disgruntled Spanish soldiers, who had gone unpaid by the bankrupt King Philip II, certainly was a factor in this transition. (Ref. 115) Soldier and sailors, in those days, demanded gold for wages, not paper. Already in 1567, when the Duke of Alva arrived in the Netherlands with his army, the troops' pay and expenses were invariably settled in gold and gold alone. (Ref. 116)

The Dutch Baltic fleet brought food supplies, chiefly grains from the Baltic, to Amsterdam and by 1500 that fleet had already equaled that of the Hanseatic League. Their business was free of guild restrictions and the Italian bankers, the Fuggers, and English merchants centered their commercial activities there. The area thus provided a great source of revenue to king and emperor, Charles V, who responded by giving the Dutch reasonably good government except in the matter of religious liberty. (Ref. 117) The Netherlands, along with Italy, remained the focus of European industrial activity until very late in the century. Contrary to what one found in a princely court, as in France, the wealthy of Holland were deliberately modest in both dress and decorum, so they could not be identified on a city street. (Ref. 118)

NOTE: Insert Map 61. The Netherlands War of Independence

Erasmus, a bastard born in Rotterdam, but later a "citizen of the world", traveling, and living at times in England, France, Italy and Switzerland, was one of the original humanists. He became a priest and soon had a number of benefices all over western Europe, which supported him while he wrote, chiefly in Latin and usually adroitly criticizing the Church, including the concept of transubstantiation, as in his Praise of Folly. Somewhat anticipating Luther, the book was condemned only after Lutherism developed. After 1519 Lutheranism and Anabaptism came in from Germany. The latter particularly gained ground in Holland under the leadership of John of Leyden, with the idea of a return to the simple teaching of Jesus and belief in the early return of Christ to earth. These concepts were mingled with communistic theories of equality, mutual aid and even "free love". Various Anabaptist uprisings and rebellions were put down brutally by the emperor's soldiers and finally the Spanish Inquisition machinery was imported to liquidate the group. The Spanish kept 50 pieces of artillery in the Netherlands, these maintained at a monthly cost of over 40,000 ducats. To move these units required almost 5,000 horses and nearly 6,000 wagons. (Ref. 119) After publicly burning Luther's books, the Papal Nuncio, Aleander, had Erasmus expelled from the theological faculty at the University of Louvain, claiming that he had paved the way for Luther by his Greek New Testament and his jibes at the Church. (Ref. 120)

In the middle of the century the Huguenots came in from France and Charles abdicated in 1555, giving the Netherlands to his son, Philip. The latter fought Protestantism in a bitter conflict that eventually broke the Netherlands in two. In these conflicts, known as the 80 Years War or simply as the Dutch Wars, starting in 1568, Philip's Spanish General Alva came opposite William the Silent, of Orange, a great Dutch leader. The Dutch began to win at the siege of Alkmaar in 1573 and in 1576 the "Pacification of Ghent" directed the withdrawal of all Spanish soldiers from the country as part of Philip's political bankruptcy settlement. However, after the Spanish king had made peace with the Turks and annexed. Portugal he felt that his finances would be- adequate and he renewed the war with the Dutch in 1583, only to eventually lose again. (Ref. 121) In the next century the Dutch were officially free. although Belgium remained under Catholic rule.

Professor William McNeill (Ref. 122) has emphasized the-very important contributions to the European military made by Maurice of Nassau, Prince of Orange (1567-1625), Captain-General of Holland and Zeeland after 1585. Maurice stressed three things:

The spade.He felt that the spade was mightier than the musket, in that by systematically digging ditches and erecting earthen ramparts, a besieging army could protect itself while continuing the siege
Systematic close order drill, including repetitive drill on loading and firing of weapons "by the numbers". McNeill believes that this, in itself, promotes psychological and sociological effects that solidifies an army into a close, social, professional, responsive group
Division of army into smaller tactical units on down to platoons, where a single voice could control the movements of all the men

The chief architect of the new Belgium, once separated from Holland, was Alexander Farnese, Duke of Parma, a military genius who had led the Spanish forces in their attempted subjugation of the Lowlands and their frustrated attempts at crossing the English Channel under the hoped for protection of the Spanish Armada. The Dutch had prevented any potential landing barges from leaving the Belgium waterways, while the English navy chased away those ships of the Spanish fleet which remained afloat. Farnese, a grandson of Pope Paul III, was unable to conquer the northern provinces of Holland, but retained Belgium for the Spanish crown and the pope, in spite of the attempt by William the Silent to reconcile various southern social groups under a national program to be carried out by the Estates-General. (Ref. 123, 124)

At the end of the century Dutch sea power had increased to where it could challenge Spain and Portugal and they were raiding the overseas colonies of those powers. The defeat of the Spanish Armada and Spanish involvement in the French civil wars allowed the Dutch to drive the Spanish from the north and they were whittling away at the Portuguese monopoly on the spice trade. Both Holland and Belgium benefitted from a 16th century agricultural revolution, with efficient, commercialized farming systems developing progressively through the next three centuries. The Dutch used- the increased capital they obtained through trade to reclaim land from the sea, and they developed better methods of crop rotation.

It should be mentioned that Netherlanders dominated music in this century, with the great Flemish composers Josquin Deprez and Orlando di Lasso greatly responsible for the development of polyphony. Perhaps this Holland accomplishment compensates, in part, for its development of a method of distilling spirits, which with Dutch encouragement led to an increased drunkenness all over Europe. (Ref. 125, 126, 127, 128)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND

This was a famous century in England, with the well known rulers Henry VIII, Queens Mary and Elizabeth and the Golden Age of English literature. The first quarter of the century was marked by an exceptional amount of unique local and foreign intrigue, deception, double-crossing and false conceptions. In the midst of this was one Thomas Woolsey, a priest whose origins we mentioned in the last chapter and who had by 1501 made himself chaplain to the Archbishop of Canterbury and was to rise to even greater heights from there. A second important factor was the continuation of some English territory on the continent in the marches of Calais, which had been English since it had been conquered by Edward 150 years before. It was a small area, 25 by 6 miles, but enough to justify the continued use of the title "King of France" by English kings and to maintain permanent military garrisons in Calais and Guisnes. To keep the English kings from further attempts on French territory, the kings of France paid 25,000 francs twice a year. Woolsey had some experience in the administration of Calais in 1503 and 1507 and was then taken into the service of King Henry VII.

In 1509 Henry VII died and his son Henry VIII became the monarch 2 months before his 18th birthday. He was a handsome, dashing young king, who reluctantly signed execution papers for some very unpopular tax collector-ministers of his father's regime. Even so, those tax collectors had made Henry VIII one of the richest kings in Europe and he was not long in taking advantage of this with elaborate banquets, tournament, jewels and dress.

Woolsey was already Dean of Lincoln and a second rank official in the king's government and in 1511 he was appointed a member of the Privy Council and by 1515 was a "Cardinal Sole"10 was supreme in the Council and in a month or so was made the Lord Chancellor of England. Like all medieval English kings, Henry VIII wanted the crown of France, in truth, and the time seemed ripe with France headed by an old, invalid king, Louis XII. Spain's King Ferdinand (and Henry's father-in-law) encouraged-him and Burgundy, now under Emperor Maximilian, was also ready for war with France. Most of all, Pope Julius feared French designs on Italy and would look with favor on any aggression against them. Only Scotland could be considered an ally of France.

Preparations for large scale war were time consuming and expensive. In the first 2 years of Henry VIII's reign his total government expenditure was 9,346 pounds but in the third year war preparations brought it up to 111,445 pounds. The whole financial arrangement, including loans from German and Flemish bankers, was handled by Cardinal Woolsey. In order to get the support of the English people it was publicly stated that by Easter, 1513 an English army of 60,000 would cross to Calais, while the Emperor Maximilian would invade France from the Netherlands, Ferdinand and his Spaniards would march into Navarre and Guienne and the pope with his Italian allies and Spanish armies in Naples attacked the French in Italy. But things were delayed and it was June 30th before Henry crossed to Calais and then heavy weather stopped everything. In the meantime James IV had invaded England from Scotland, to be defeated at the battle the English call "Branxton". Henry finally did manage to visit Margaret of Austria at Lille and besiege Tournai on the border of the Netherlands with 20,000 men. When this city fell, Woolsey was made Bishop of Tournai. But then Ferdinand double-crossed Henry and signed a truce with Louis XII and Maximilian's efforts were only "window dressing". Therefore, in secret, Woolsey and Henry, instead of invading France in 1514, signed a peace treaty at St. Germain-en-Laye, whereby Louis ceded Tournai to Henry and agreed to paying a million francs over 10 years, while Henry's beautiful, young sister, Mary, was to marry the aging Louis XII11. This separate peace annoyed the emperor, King Ferdinand and Pope Leo X, who had succeeded Julius II. The good relations between France and England did not long exist, however, as the ambitious, young Francois I took over the French throne.

Henry and Woolsey did not pursue war against the new French king but used all diplomatic means to thwart him, including offering of financial aid to any power who would oppose him. By the time of this "cold war" of 1515 Woolsey was bishop or archbishop of any number of communities, with additional income internationally from various Spanish, French, and Imperial agreements so that he was becoming very wealthy. Some considered him "ipse rex" - the king himself. Having close ties with Venice commercially, the English king and the cardinal soon tried to woo that Italian city away from their French alliance, but were unsuccessful until 1523.

Undoubtedly most of us tend to associate Henry VIII only with obesity, gluttony and beheading of enemies and wives, but actually in his younger years he was apparently a capable, bright, ambitious but well liked man. He was determined to make England the greatest artistic and literary center of Europe. Among the English intellectuals was Thomas More, the lawyer that we also mentioned in the last chapter. Initially one of the great humanists, More soon became a close friend of Erasmus of the Netherlands, who had made many visits to England. In addition to their humanist views they had in common the study of Greek and both wrote copiously in Latin and Greek. More's book Utopia12, written in Latin, developed a most unusual hypothetical community, which has given its name as a new word in most languages. Partly as a result of his reputation from this book and for his success in some diplomatic activities in Flanders, he was soon invited to join the king's government. It was thus that Henry VIII, Cardinal Woolsey and Thomas More all eventually were joined together in the control and manipulation of England.

The extent of the pomp and ceremony of governments and royalty in the 16th century is not easily pictured today. In 1520, when Henry VIII crossed to Calais on another trip to confer near there with Emperor Charles V, he was accompanied by a retinue of 3,990 persons and 2,087 horses, while 1,175 persons and 778 horses accompanied his Queen Catherine13. All of the accompanying officials had dozens of servants and/or knights, while the Lord Legate14, the Cardinal of York, Woolsey, had 300 servants. Initially all of these individuals professed the Catholic faith and suppressed Lutheranism, including the burning of the heretics' books and a few of the heretics themselves. Henry, the king, even wrote a book, The Assertion of the Seven Sacraments15. No subject in Europe could even approach the power, wealth and status of Thomas Woolsey. He lived at Hampton Court with its 280 rooms and a staff of 500 servants, although this was only one of several of his palaces. It was this man who was involved in the unscrupulous diplomatic maneuvers which pushed Charles V and Francois I into a major, western European war-which raged, with only brief intervals, for nearly 40 years at a time when Christendom was threatened internally by Lutheran heresy and externally by the Turks in Hungary. Through the first 25 years of the century, Woolsey kept promising the emperor and the Spanish that he would invade and conquer France, but this never actually materialized in any degree and at the same time Woolsey kept up secret negotiations with France. In this period there were several papal deaths and each time Woolsey tried to conjure, buy or blackmail himself into the papacy, but he always failed. Henry's only living offspring, his daughter Mary, was used in much international bargaining and intrigue - at one time offered to Charles V in marriage and other times to Francois I of France. While supporting the church, Cardinal Woolsey at the same time managed to get papal dispensation to confiscate any number of monasteries and nunneries to use the proceeds for constructions of 2 colleges of his founding16

In the meantime, after 1517 Thomas More underwent a profound intellectual and emotional transformation. His appointment to the Privy Council changed him from the humanist writer of Utopia to an instrument of Henry VIII's tyranny and the rise of Lutheranism in Europe turned him from an intellectual into a religious fanatic. Becoming a great persecutor of heretics, it seemed that he inwardly felt his original humanism was responsible for Lutheranism. He constantly wore a hair shirt beneath his outer clothing and regularly flogged himself with a knotted rope.

Finally in August of 1525, peace was agreed upon with France, the latter ceding no territory but agreeing to pay an enormous indemnity. England then changed sides in the struggle between France and the empire. Allied with the former, Henry could think of nullifying his 15 year marriage to Catherine (who had given him no male heir), since her nephew, Emperor Charles, was then the current enemy. The Lord Chancellor Woolsey spent the next many, many months trying to get the pope to accommodate Henry in this regard and Henry, himself, had already fallen in love with the young Ann Boleyn. No one knows exactly why Lord Woolsey fell from power, although there were many factors from which to choose - his failure to get the annulment or divorce for Henry from Catherine, the loss of public support because of the opulence of his life and immense wealth and a multitude of small offences and irregularities collected by- the king's secretaries over a 15 year period. At any rate, he was arrested on the charge of "praemunire", a grave offense just short of treason and punishable by life imprisonment. The charge was based on Woolsey's exercise of powers as Papal Legate, in which, as a representative of a foreign potentate he had usurped some of the king's powers. He was replaced as Lord Chancellor by Thomas More. Woolsey soon fell ill and for the first time in his life showed an interest in the spiritual side of religion. Although losing most of his estates and most of his wealth, he was essentially pardoned by the king and simply banished to York. It is interesting to note that even in that predicament he traveled there with 600 gentlemen and servants and 12 carts carrying baggage. But he was arrested once again in 1530 and on his way to the Tower of London he died, apparently of intestinal hemorrhage, cause unknown.

The new Lord Chancellor spent all his efforts persecuting heretics. In his mind every ill in the world was caused by Luther - even the terrible sacking of Rome by the emperor's troops. As King Henry gradually became more and more infuriated with the pope, More alone remained in favor of Catholic policy. Parliament convened in 1529 to stay in session for nearly seven years, during which time it placed the church under royal authority, repudiating the Papal Supremacy and recognized Henry as the Supreme Head of the Church of England. More's objections to this eventually caused him to lose his head. (Ref. 131) It was in 1531 that Henry assumed ecclesiastical leadership of the church and made Thomas Cromwell the chief administrator. The latter, in turn, sought to make the king supreme over every aspect of English life and was ruthless in his persecution of those attempting to remain Catholic. In spite of this, he too ended up beheaded. Between 1535 and 1547 all monasteries were dissolved by Henry and the spoils were distributed to minor nobles or business men who supported the king. The government did protect industry with tariffs and the manufacturers profited from cheap labor, so that the textile industry grew and made wealthy men, some of whom then became the new aristocracy of England. With the destruction of the monasteries, however, education almost disappeared and strangely enough, mead also disappeared. The monks of the monasteries had raised bees to get wax for votive candles and the mead had been made incidentally from the honey. The people of England were still surrounded by sheep, but now many only wanted cow dairy products. Their entire agricultural process was changing in the beginning of an agricultural revolution, with the development of the iron plow and soil liming, among other things. (Ref. 132, 133, 134, 135) Technicians imported from the continent discovered in 1543 how to cast satisfactory iron cannon, thus cheapening the big guns to about one-twelfth their former cost. (Ref. 136)

But to return to Henry VIII, the reckless and vicious elimination of his various wives have been the source of many books, dramas and histories and will only be tabulated here for record. Catharine of Aragon, mother of Mary the Catholic, was finally divorced after 20 years. Anne Boleyn, mother of Elizabeth, was beheaded. Jane Seymour, mother of Edward VI, died apparently of natural causes. Of the last three, Anne of Cleves was divorced and Catherine Howard was beheaded while Catherine Parr outlived the king. (Ref. 137) In the last of his reign Henry was the most absolute monarch England had known. His late, terrible disposition may have been in part fashioned by his syphilis and a chronic leg ulcer. Upon his death in 1547 his son by Jane Seymour became Edward VI, when he was but ten years old, and he never did gain the strength to rule. The power of the throne was contested by Edward Seymour, Duke of Somerset and his brother, Thomas Seymour. The former was ruined by Kit's Rebellion, a Catholic peasant revolt, as the duke sympathized with the losing peasants against the nobles.

When Edward VI died in 1553 followers of his half-sisters Mary and Elizabeth battled to put one of them on the throne. Mary, a nervously ill, unattractive woman, whose only solace was her Catholic faith, became the queen. In the meantime Archbishop Cranmer had written the First Book of Common Prayer as a substitute for the missal and breviary of the defeated church. Although at first tolerant, Mary soon had him burned at the stake. The papal legate was brought back and persecutions of Protestants resulted in the name "Bloody Mary" for the queen. In the end the people were more ready than before to accept the "new" or Protestant faith. Mary married Philip, destined later to be Philip II of Spain, but never having been crowned by Parliament, he returned to Spain not long before Mary died.

Elizabeth became queen in 1558, restoring Protestantism. Royal agents then tortured Catholic priests; non-attendance at some English Protestant Church cost 12 pence a Sunday in 1559 and by the 1580s reached 20 pounds a month. (Ref. 138, 139, 140) It was actually Elizabeth who signed the treaty of Cateau-Cambresis in 1559, officially dividing the spoils of the 60 year French-Spanish war, in which England had been intermittently involved. (Ref. 141)

In the last half of the century foreign trade began to be an important part of the English economy for the first time and in the last quarter, there was a great overseas expansion, first with piracy and then world-wide trade. The Merchant Adventurers was a wool and cloth, closed corporation which actually operated primarily outside of England in Antwerp and later Hamburg. Joint stock companies including the Moscovy Company (1555), the Levant Company (1581) and the English East India Company developed. (Ref. 142) Sir Francis Drake, the most unscrupulous of the English pirates, left England in 1577 to sail through the Strait of Magellan and enter the Pacific, there harassing every Spanish ship, ransacking cities of Chile and Peru and finally sailing up past San Francisco and then across to the Moluccas and Java. He arrived home with great loot, to be made a hero, and gave hope to English farmers and shepherds who were resenting feudal taxes and tithes. That trip really stimulated the colony experiments of the next century. Drake was also one of the chief admirals at the time of the Spanish Armada, when the English fleet drove off the Catholic ships, which had been sent to facilitate a channel crossing of Spanish troops from Belgium. (See pages 780-782). The backbone of the potent English navy included 18 powerful galleons, varying from 300 tons up, excellently armed; 7 smaller galleons of 100 tons or more; and a great number of pinnaces. While awaiting the great battle, the crews were kept healthy on land, with fresh food and good water, not going to sea until absolutely necessary. (Ref. 143, 144) After the remnants of the defeated Spanish fleet sailed away in the North Sea, the English kept expecting a renewed attack and kept their ships manned and vigilant. As a result, typhus fever then killed the English sailors in greater number than had the battles.

A former junior officer of Drake's, Admiral Sir Richard Hawkins, later also raided about the Atlantic and around the southern end of South America, eventually to be taken prisoner by the Spanish. He had reported that 10,000 men under his command had died of scurvy and that orange and lemon juice were anti-scorbutic, but his home admiralty did not accept this for another century or more. (Ref. 145) It is said that Sir Walter Raleigh brought the potato to England from South America in 1588 and this probably had greater effects on the future of Europe and mankind than the sea battles with the Armada. (Ref. 146)

There is evidence that between 1/2 and 2/3 of all English households received some part of their income from wages. All through this century the-Tudors depended upon unpaid justices of the peace, always land owners, to apply the laws. Failure to retain support of these land owners could result in revolts and one such uprising did occur against Elizabeth I in 1569-70 called the "Northern Rising". But overall, the last of the century was tranquil and an age of many exceptionally brilliant writers, including Shakespeare, Spenser and Ben Jonson. In 1599 London merchants were so upset over the rise in pepper from 37 cents to $1.00 per pound (these figures are the American equivalents) that they formed the East Indian Company to get their own pepper and thereby unwittingly started the British Indian Empire. (Ref. 147, 148)

SCOTLAND

At the end of the last century James IV had promoted the founding of Aberdeen University with the first medical school teaching in Britain and in 1506 he granted a royal charter to a College of Surgeons in Edinborough. After the king's marriage to Margaret Tudor, daughter of Henry VII of England, border peace was obtained at least for while and government, justice and order were improved. Scotland then had a powerful navy and the largest and most modern cannon. After England's Henry VII died in 1509, English border raids resumed and when Louis XII of France pleaded for Scottish aid in his war against the Holy League and the pope, James first moved to the English border with an army of perhaps 20,000 men to meet an English force of about the same size. King James and some 10,000 Scots were killed.

Scotland then again had a child king, James V, less than two years old and who should have had his mother, Margaret Tudor, as regent. She was so for a few months, but when she married Archibald Douglas, the 6th earl of Angus, Scottish lords and Parliament, loyal to France, appointed John Stewart, Duke of Albany, to be regent. He was a grandson of James II, shrewd and intelligent and spoke nothing but French, having lived in France since the age of four. The factions of Angus, Albany and the queen mother all struggled for control and finally in 1526 Angus seized the king and kept him in confinement. John Stewart returned to France, where he was held for four years while Scotland again fell into violent anarchy, with lord against lord and clan against clan. Some semblance of order was restored after 1528 by the 16 year old king, who emerged in some way from his captivity. He obtained some money from the pope and a good deal more from Francois as a dowry for marrying his unattractive daughter. The lady obligingly died within two months and James V then married Mary of Guise, a French widow. She brought a dowry of 150,000 livres. In spite of the king's attempt to promote law and order, great brutalities, fights and noble murders continued. In 1542 an English army again attacked Scotland; the Scots, failing to get French help, were not enthusiastic for the conflict; they lost and James V was killed, leaving an infant daughter who was to become Mary, Queen of Scots. (Ref. 149, 150)

In the middle of the century young scholars who had been educated in Germany and Scandinavia returned home, rejecting the Church of Rome. Among these was George Wishart, a zealous dogmatist and religious politician. Eventually he preached to large congregations, sometimes protected by an ecclesiastical notary, John Knox, carrying a great two-handed sword. With a charge of heresy, Wishart was strangled and then burned in 1546. Knox took up his reforms and preaching and was one of a band that killed Cardinal Beaton. After a long sojourn in Switzerland, where he had been strongly influenced by the Calvinists, Knox got a reformation parliament to repudiate the supremacy of the pope, forbid the celebration of the Latin mass and approve a Confession of Faith. He stated that soon the English would send an army to help. Instead came a French fleet, which took Knox prisoner for 8 years, during which time he was a galley slave. When he was finally released, he returned as a noisy rabble-rouser, advocating war and murder, drunk with a self -righteous passion and responsible for much of the blood and bigotry that was to follow. He glorified the Old Testament, claimed prophetic powers, rebelled against women rulers and felt that all should be killed who did not hold his beliefs.

Meanwhile war erupted again in 1548 when the Duke of Somerset took an army into Scotland, ravaging the countryside with the announced purpose of arranging a future marriage for the little Queen Mary with the Prince of Wales. The Scots resisted, with the help of the French army which came with a promise of Mary's betrothal to the dauphin of France. When the English withdrew in 1549, the French army stayed for another 8 years to protect Catholicism and finally the queen did marry the French heir, while she still ruled Scotland from France, under the regency of her mother, Mary of Guise. The new Protestantism was tolerated for awhile, but in 1559 the queen mother decided to crush the new faith. In 1561 the real queen of Scots came home from France, a widow at 18 years of age, tall, beautiful, Catholic and claiming not only the Scots but the English throne as well, thus becoming a thorn in the life of her cousin, Elizabeth. Either through a French variation or actual misspelling, her surname became changed from Stewart to Stuart. In 1656 she married again, this time to 19 year old Lord Darnley, a great grand- child of Henry VII. Not long after fathering Mary's child, the future James VI, the young groom was strangled. Subsequently the queen was made a captive for a year but ended up marrying her captor, the Earl of Bothwell. Captured again by Protestants she was held in Edinbrough, called a whore and declared ripe for a burning. Forced to abdicate her throne, she named the Earl of Moray as regent for her small son while she escaped into England. Freedom was short-lived, however, as the Elizabethan court imprisoned her again and eventually executed her in 1587.

In the meantime John Knox had died in 1572 and his place at the head of the Protestant movement in Scotland had been taken by Andrew Melville, who came from exile in Geneva to be principal of Glasgow University. An unbelievably strict, rigid Protestant morality doctrine descended on the Scottish people. In keeping with Scotland's long history of treachery and deceit and violence, the young King James VI was abducted in 1582 and confined for about a year. Subsequently he did rule for the remainder of the century, marrying a Danish princess and arranging to be the successor of Queen Elizabeth on the throne of England in the next century. (Ref. 151, 152)

IRELAND

When Henry VIII had completed his separation from the Roman Church in England he bade the Irish Parliament to acknowledge him also as head of the Irish Church. It accommodated him and the spoils of the monasteries and church properties were given to various Irish chieftains who thereupon became nobles of the English king. The clan system was abolished and Ireland was declared a kingdom, with Henry VIII as its king, in 1541. But when the king died, five years later, the Irish people remained Catholic, a factor which bolstered them in their later struggle for freedom. Irish rebels, including Red Hugh O'Donnell and Hugh O'Neill continued to fight for Irish independence, and the O'Neill badly defeated an English army at Yellow Ford in 1598. Spain even dispatched 4,000 troops to aid in this rebellion, landing at Kinsdale on the southern coast, but they were immediately evicted by English troops. In this century Ireland became a major ex- porter of salted butter and salt beef, the latter being used on shipboard and as food for the poor and the slaves. Salt beef even became a standard winter dish in England. (Ref. 153, 154)

WALES

There had been peace between England and Wales since the ascension of the Welsh Tydder (Tudor) King Henry VII and in 1536 Wales became officially incorporated into the English nation.

SCANDINAVIA

"The Baltic is a vast, almost land-locked, frequently ice-bound area of water covering over 166,000 square miles. In early modern times it provided the great bulk of the timber, tar, pitch, hemp and flax for the ships with which England, Holland, France, Spain and Portugal were building their world trading empires; also much of the grain needed to insure the rest of the continent against poor harvests, and the copper for its everyday money."17 Furthermore, the Baltic and the adjacent Gulf of Finland were almost completely under the control of Scandinavians during the 16th century. In the first quarter, all Scandinavia was, furthermore, under one king, in the Union of Calmar. Finland was a part of Sweden and all were subservient to King Hans (Dane) as the century opened. After Hans' defeat by the Frisians in 1500 the various segments of Scandinavia gradually began to separate again. At the end of the century all Scandinavia was still relatively sparsely settled, with only about 1.5 inhabitants to the square kilometer (compared to 40 in the Netherlands, for example) and remained only on the margin of European life. (Ref. 155)

NORWAY

Norway continued the docile partner of Denmark throughout the remainder of the century. The country did become an exporter of copper to Europe proper. (Ref. 157)

SWEDEN (See map in section on SWEDEN in 17th century)

In 1501, after King Hans had been defeated in -Frisia, the Union of Calmar was not officially dissolved, but it was simply "not in force" and Sten Sture was again considered Regent of Sweden. When Sten threw the Archbishop of Sweden into prison in 1520, Christian II, successor to Hans, took an army to Sweden and the Danish army, backed by some Swedish nobles, took the whole country by force. In Stortorv Square in Stockholm, after a celebration, Christian II had his soldiers murder 82 nobles of Sweden as heretics. A son of one of those so killed in this "Stockholm Bloodbath" soon thereafter got help from the peasants to assemble an army and within two years had all of Sweden under his control. This man, Gustavus Eriksson, was then crowned King of Sweden as Gustav Vasa, in 1523 and the Union of Calmar truly ended. During his reign a financial crisis developed and when the pope replied to the king's appeal for funds only in a very meager way, the king began to favor the Protestants. He commissioned a translation of the Bible into Swedish and this helped not only to transform the national religion but to promote the language itself. As in England, the king began to take over church property for his treasury and insisted that the Diet, or National Assembly, cut out the pope, eliminate confessions and give all the church property to the crown. This was another triumph of the state over the church. Gustav I Vasa was the father of modern Sweden. During his reign iron mines were expanded, trade increased. copper exported and soon there was great prosperity. Even the peasants manufactured iron, but only during the rise of the spring waters when water power was available to help in the operation of the furnaces. (Ref. 158) With all of this, we must not lose sight of the fact that the vast expanses of Sweden were still half-empty, with only a few settlements in a vast territory. Traveling merchants distributed horse shoes, nails, pins and religious books, among other things. (Ref. 159)

In 1544 the crown's status was changed from elective office to an hereditary monarchy so that Vasa's sons succeeded him, Eric XIV (1560-68) and John III (1568-92). During this period Reval, a previously independent Hanseatic port, now threatened on all sides put itself under Swedish protection, but by 1563 the entire area burst out in the Seven Years' War of the North. Sweden generally held pretty well in this struggle, although she had to pay ransom to Denmark for the return of Alvsborg and by 1581 she was becoming a significant factor far beyond the Baltic. John III married a Polish princess and his son ascended the Polish throne in 1587 as Sigismund III only to also become King of Sweden upon his father's death in 1592. He was deposed from the latter job, however, in 1599 with his Lutheran uncle taking the crown as Karl (Charles) IX. In the meantime, at the final settlement of the Seven Years' War of the North, in the Peace of Teusina, Sweden added Narva and almost all of the country of Estonia. The Gulf of Finland thus was a Swedish waterway. (Ref. 160, 161, 162)

DENMARK (Please read the remarks about Sweden, above, also)

Although Denmark's Christian II lost Sweden, he had a constructive reign within his own country. The Reformation movement there was led by the monk Poul Helgeson and was approved by Christian. Certain nobles and clergy rebelled, however, dethroned the king, made Frederick of Schleswig-Holstein monarch for while, but finally, after much fighting for the throne, in 1536 the National Assembly crowned Christian III, established a Lutheran State Church and confiscated all episcopal and monastic properties for the king. Norway and Iceland accepted Christian III and his Protestant legislation and the triumph of Lutheranism in Scandinavia was complete. Later in the century King Frederick II attacked Sweden and their then King Eric XIV and this war went on again as the Seven Years' War of the North.

Tycho Brahe (1546-1601), the famous astronomer of this period, was given an island in the sound off Denmark for his home and laboratory. About 1600 Denmark exported some 100,000 cattle each year through Lubeck and Hamburg. (Ref. 163, 164)

FINLAND

Finland, as a part of Sweden, was given the Lutheran faith by Gustavus I Vasa. 79% of Finns today are still, at least nominally Lutherans. Helsingfors (Helsinki) was founded in 1554. (Ref. 165)

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

The Norwegian settlement of Iceland in this 1 6th century took the brunt of what has been referred to as the "Little Ice Age", with Atlantic ice sheets extending well south of that island, interrupting shipping and destroying the Icelanders agricultural base in Greenland. In Iceland proper, the previous wheat-based economy gave way to sheep and cattle and life became very hard. Between 1500 and 1800 there were 37 years of famine in that country. Very important to Iceland is the physical fact that a mean annual temperature drop of only two degrees Fahrenheit reduces the growing season by 40 days or 25% and the drop in the average temperature during the growing days further reduces the crop. (Ref. 166)

EASTERN EUROPE

For centuries there had been a correlation between traffic on the Baltic Sea and prosperity of Eastern Europe. After 1581, when Russia lost Narva in Estonia, as noted elsewhere, Moscovy diverted its trade to overland routes and the Baltic trade diminished, only to be refurbished when the Thirty Years War cut the land traffic through Central Europe. Perhaps in connection with the above, huge areas from the Baltic to the Black Sea reverted to a "second serfdom"18. The peasant was being ever more firmly attached to the land and he was losing mobility and the right to free himself. Gradually through the century, the days of compulsory labor were increased in Poland, Hungary, Livonia and Moscovy. The need for food and raw materials to be shipped to the West and the decline of cities and rise of feudal lords all played a part in this. (Ref. 167)

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

As in the past, Sweden, Denmark, Russia and Poland all competed in this century for domination of the Baltic area. Of the original Balt tribes, the Letts had now become Latvians and the Curonians were Lettonized in this century. The Prussians were extinct as a people, but the Lithuanians remained strong and numerous. Until the middle of the century the Teutonic Knights held Livonia, Estonia and Courland and their stories thereafter will be taken up in a later paragraph. After somewhat of a poor start in the century, with the loss of the left bank of the Dnieper in 1503 and the city of Smolensk in 1514, both in wars with Russia, Poland-then enjoyed a Golden Age under Sigismund I and II, up to 1572. Both rulers were men of culture and spirit and gave religious thought and worship a complete freedom. Although there were interval wars with other powers for control of the Baltic, Poland prospered and remained a major European state. The power of the lesser nobility continued to grow, however, and all efforts of the kings to strengthen royal power, reform the government and establish a more modern army and administration met with failure and Poland gradually became transformed into a republic. Lithuania and Poland continued to be closely associated and the kings of Poland were usually also the Grand Dukes of Lithuania. As was true all across northern Europe, beer was consumed in large amounts - the peasants drinking three liters a day. (Ref. 169)

The Livonian War began in 1557 and was an armed dispute involving all the powers bordering the Baltic. As the Russians moved in from the east, Sweden took Estonia and the Danes acquired part of Courland. In 1561 Poland took part of Livonia and insisted on the Polish language and laws and the Catholic religion, but within two years Ivan the Terrible of Russia had re-conquered this area. Russia and Sweden continued the battles until 1582 with Narva falling to the latter in 1581, but the Pole's fighting had pretty well ceased by 1571, probably due to their preoccupation with their relationship with

Lithuania. In spite of opposition by the Lithuanian common people, Lithuania officially merged with Poland in 1569. Subsequently the two nations had a common sovereign and a common Diet, although Lithuania retained some separate administration and army. Russian threats to Lithuania were probably the deciding factors in forcing this union, because Russia had already taken the Ukraine territory, including Kiev. By the Polish union, Lithuania apparently was able to save White Russia from Ivan. (Ref. 170, 171)

The Reformation filtered in to Poland from Germany and Switzerland and both Lutheranism and Calvinism advanced rapidly, with the National Diet in 1552 voting religious freedom for all faiths, based on "The pure Word of God", legalizing clerical marriage and communion in bread and wine. The Unitarian movement, denying the Trinity, also became strong. But in 1564 the Catholics brought in the Jesuits and these trained and devoted men secured strategic places in the educational system and turned the Polish people back to Catholicism. In 1595 even most of the Orthodox bishops of the Ukraine and Lithuania had also accepted union with Rome on condition that they retain a Slavonic ritual. Thus, the "Uniate" Church came into existence. (Ref. 172)

One of the important products of Poland was lead and by this century the mines were producing between 1,000 and 3,000 tons a year. But money was necessary to construct the long, sloping tunnels and the horse powered pumps necessary to drain water of the depths and this brought in those who had capital. Thus 1/5 - of the mines fell to King Sigismund Augustus, 1/5 to the nobility and related people and 3/5 to the merchants of Cracow. (Ref. 173) Poland exported some 50,000 head of cattle to Central Europe each year. (Ref. 174)

For 2 years after the death of Sigismund II and the end of the Jagellon Dynasty, Henri of Valois was the elected king, subject to the new pact which gave the nobility the right to limit the royal power. In 1574 Henri went back to France, however, and finally the Poles elected Stephen Bathory, whose wife was a Jagellon. He ruled well from the standpoint of foreign affairs and war, dominating the Baltic until 1586, as he held the Russians in check. He was followed on the throne by Sigismund III, son of King John of Sweden, an ardent Catholic educated by the Jesuits. He squandered all of Poland's energy in wars with Sweden because of his claims to the Swedish throne. (Ref. 175)

RUSSIA (Please see map in section on RUSSIA in 19th century C.E.)

The search for a Baltic outlet was a critical issue throughout this century. Ivan III died in 1505 and Basil III assumed power. In 1511 Pskov succumbed to the fate of Novgorod and was incorporated into the state of Moscow and by 1514 there was war with Poland. Even at this early date Moscow and the Habsburgs of Vienna had discussed a possible partition of Poland, but the latter was too strong a military power. In the war just mentioned, Russia used foreign officers and up to date artillery and did capture Smolensk from the Poles.

The Orthodox Church had developed a schism: (1) Abbot Joseph Volotsky held that the state was under obligation to preserve the sanctity and purity of Jesus. (2) Abbot Nil Sorsky held that the faith was not to be enforced by police measures and the state had no authority in spiritual affairs. Joseph said monasteries should own property, Nil said "no". Joseph was for high ritual and temples, Nil said the heart was more important than the temple. Basil III divorced his first, barren wife and took another with Joseph's blessings and Nil's condemnation. Thus, Basil sided with the Josephians and they became the victors, loyally serving the state. (Ref. 176)

Ivan IV, son of Basil, became the Russian sovereign in 1533. The Tatars still held Kazan, Astrakhan and the Crimea, but there was now reduced nomadic pressure so Ivan attacked and after a long siege he not only won but then massacred the people of Kazan. This eastern expedition gave Muscovy control of two vital rivers, the Kama and the Volga, opening the way to the Caspian Sea and trade with Persia beyond. (Ref. 177) The Cossacks of the Don (but not those of Kiev, now under Lithuania) now also bowed to Moscow's rule.

Ivan's next project was to try to gain access to the Baltic through Livonia and it was this that precipitated the 25 year Livonian War involving Sweden, Denmark and Poland as well as the Livonians, themselves. He did temporarily get a window on the Baltic at Narva in 1558 but it was closed to him again in 1581. Furthermore, trouble then developed at home, with plots, counter-plots, defection of key people to Poland, etc, so that Ivan had to start a revolution of his own. First he engineered a terrible purge of the nobility whom he thought might be against him, endeavoring to elevate a new class to political power. Actually the Orthodox Church remained the real ruler of Russia. Ivan was a barbarian struggling to be civilized, but failing. He gave his people a demoralizing example of pious cruelty and uncontrolled passion and well earned the name of "Ivan the Terrible".

One of the few constructive aspects of this reign may have been the church Council of Stoglav in which many reforms were instituted by the counsellor Sylvester, who later compiled a book for instruction of the people in morality and general education.

The Crimean Tatars had been only temporarily controlled and in 1571 they again sacked and burned Moscow. At that time they were vassals of the Ottoman Turks, but their only duty to the Turks was to bring the Khan some 20,000 to 30,000 horsemen, when summoned. The Poles under Stephen Bathory invaded Russia also in 1579, regaining much border territory in Livonia, although they could not retake Smolensk. It was the Swedes who took Narva in 1581, cutting off Russia again from the Baltic. In 1584 the Cossacks invaded a Siberian Khanate and opened up the eastward movement which was comparable to the later westward migration of the American colonists. (Ref. 178, 179, 180)

Italians, Germans, Dutchmen and Englishmen penetrated Russia in this 16th century and one of the crucial issues was how to cope with these Europeans, much as it is today. With the arrival of German coins and ingots money began to be minted regularly, although still on a modest scale. (Ref. 181) A second big problem was control of the lower classes. In 1592 the Moscow government ordered the registration of all peasants and 5 years later decreed that any peasants who deserted could be returned to their former lawful masters, marking the initial steps toward curbing of peasant freedom, with the bulk of Russia's population turned into serfs. (Ref. 182, 183)

Ivan the Terrible killed his ablest son and bequeathed the throne to a weakling whose incapacity invited civil war. The actual control of the government fell to Nikita Romanov and when he died, by his brother-in-law Boris Godunov, with the latter being elected to the throne by the National Assembly in 1598. Although a novice in politics, Godunov's military record was an outstanding one. In the meantime, the Russian Church had become entirely independent from Constantinople, as the first Patriarch of Moscow was created in 1589. (Ref. 184)

North of the Ural Mountains the Eurasian Nenets herded reindeer and hunted seals and whales in the Arctic Ocean. Prosperous herders of ten had two or more wives, who busied themselves setting up conical tents and dressing skins. In this and the next century, gun-bearing European settlers and hunters killed enough reindeer to start a decline in the number of the wild herds.

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [21] BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

6 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

9 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

10 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

11 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

12 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

13 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

14 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

15 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

16 [86] HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

17 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

18 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

19 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

20 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

21 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

22 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

23 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

24 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

25 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

26 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

27 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

28 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

29 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

30 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

31 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

32 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

33 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

34 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

35 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

36 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

37 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

38 [121]  LEONARDO DA VINCI. (Reynal & Co. New York, 1956).

39 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

40 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

41 [50] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

42 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

43 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

44 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

45 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

48 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

49 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

50 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

51 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

52 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

53 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

54 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

55 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

56 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

57 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

58 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

59 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

60 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

61 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

62 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

63 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

64 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

65 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

66 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

67 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

68 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

69 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

70 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

71 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

72 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

73 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

74 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

75 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

76 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

77 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

78 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

79 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

80 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

81 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

82 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

83 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

84 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

85 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

86 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

87 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

88 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

89 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

90 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

91 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

92 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

93 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

94 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

95 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

96 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

97 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

98 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

99 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

100 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

101 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

102 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

203 [160] OXENSTIERNA, Eric, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

104 [218] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

105 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

106 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

107 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

108 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

109 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

110 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

111 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

112 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

113 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

114 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

115 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

116 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

117 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

118 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

119 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

120 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

121 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

122 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

123 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

124 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

125 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

126 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

127 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

128 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

129 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

130 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

131 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

132 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

133 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

134 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

135 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

136 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

137 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

138 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

139 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

140 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

141 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

142 [133] MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

143 [39] Cooke, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

144 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

145 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

146 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

147 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

148 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

149 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

150 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

151 [291] RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

152 [110] Judge, Joseph, The Travail of Ireland", National Geographic 1159: 432-441, Apr. 1981.

153 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

154 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

155 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

156 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

157 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

158 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

159 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

160 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

161 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

162 [117] LA FAY, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

163 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

164 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

165 [237] Wilson, David, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

166 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

167 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

168 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

169 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

170 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

171 [51] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

172 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

173 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

174 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

175 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

176 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

177 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

178 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

179 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

180 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

181 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

182 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

183 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

184 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

1.  Quotation from McNeill (Ref. 24), page 79

2.  McNeill makes the interesting suggestion that syphilis may have been a transition from the old, endemic disease, yaws. (Ref. 33)

3.  Quotation from Rodes (Ref. 55), page 137

4.  Zapola was actually supported against Ferdinand by Henry VIII and Cardinal Lord Chancellor Woolsey, in order to annoy the emperor. (Ref. 60)

5.  This date is that of the Gregorian calendar, already adopted by the Spanish, but not by the English

6.  Regarding the smallness of this potato, see Section VIII, C, SOUTH AMERICA, this chapter

7.  This "displacement tonnage" is an entirely different measurement of ship size than the carrying capacity tonnage we have mentioned in the note on page 742 as pertaining to the number of "tuns" of wine in the hold

8.  Henri II later took Catherine de Medici for his wife, but retained Diane as his mistress

9.  Trager (Ref. 111) on his page 201, says that this information was found in the diary of the lawyer, Pierre de L'Estoile

10.  That is, he was appointed individually, without waiting for the usual time of election of cardinals

11.  Within two months after the marriage, Mary was a widow

12.   The full name was The Best State of a Commonwealth and the New Island of Utopia. "Utopia" was coined from the Greek word for "nowhere". (Ref. 129)

13.  Catherine of Aragon was the daughter of King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella

14.  By this time Cardinal Woolsey was also the Papal Legate to England

15.  Although the authorship of this has been debated in the past, it is now pretty generally acknowledged that the king did write it. (Ref. 130)

16.  One of these persists today at Oxford as Christ Church

17.  This quotation taken from The Times Atlas of World History (Ref. 156), page 188

18.  The term is Braudel's (Ref. 168), page 265

Europe: A.D. 1601 to 1700

Europe

In the early century, inflation was such that prices were four times what they had been between 1525 and 1550. (Ref. 1) Three great powers contested for dominance – the Ottoman Empire, the Spanish Empire, and France, under Louis XIV and Richelieu. Each had a mass of about 17 million people. (Ref. 2) In spite of the presence of these great monarchies, there were still areas all over Europe from southern Italy to Scandinavia and from Scotland to Auvergne where primitive social enclaves persisted, with hundreds of dialects and local, semibarbaric, religious cults. Attempted control of these numerous pockets sapped the resources of the great powers, similar to the drain on the Roman Empire when it was ringed with barbarians. In addition, after about 1620 the entire continent suffered from food shortages as the population increased to about 118 million by 1648 and the result of this was often political instability. Even by 1640, rebellion was everywhere. Although this is often called the century of scientific revolution, this was completely irrelevant to the mass of Europeans as they squandered most of their energies in massive wars. During the whole of the period there were only seven years of peace in Europe. All of the people tended to revolt against the powers of princes and kings over their bodies and properties and to protest against taxation, interference with trade and arbitrary imprisonment. Over most of Europe the peasantry represented vast numbers of people and in one way or another they were almost always in revolt, with occasional open rebellion, as in Naples in 1647. In Orleans, out of an active population of almost 120,000 there were over 67,000 wage earners, but this did not signal great productivity. Many districts were over-populated with great numbers of unemployed. Vagrants were universally put under lock and key, usually in work-houses. (Ref. 3)

The last quarter of the century saw the establishment of responsible parliamentary government in most areas. By 1700 the old north-south trade axis had swung almost 90~ and ran east-west from England-Holland to Saxony, Bohemia and Silesia. Population growth at the end of the century had been slowed not only by war and famine but also by plague, so that shortly after the turn of the century (1713) the population had dropped to about 102 million. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7) Still, Europe remained in a favored position when compared to other civilization, particularly in regard to food. Europeans consumed great quantities of meat. Water-mills supplied the chief energy and were owned and supplied by the lord of the manor, while the peasants contributed their labor. The mill, which ground grain, was thus the essential tool of the manorial economy. Otherwise the 17th century civilization was one of wood and charcoal. Buildings, machines, wine-presses, plows and pumps were all made of wood, with a very minimum of metallic parts. Fortunately Europe was well-endowed with forests. Iron, although available, was still in short supply. (Ref. 8) Wigs and then powdered wigs came into fashion in this century despite initial objection by the church.

Practically all the armies of Europe had adopted the military reforms initiated at the end of the previous century by Maurice of Holland. (See page 792). This resulted in obedient, responsive units of soldiers able to function efficiently in any part of the globe. The new drill and techniques spread from officers trained at Maurice's Military Academy, which was founded in 1619, first to Sweden, then to the northern Protestant European states and finally to France and eventually Spain. (Ref. 9) (Continue on page 942)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

Continuing their take-over of Mediterranean islands, the Turks conquered the Cyclades and all of Crete except two off-shore Venetian forts. The Hospital of the Knights of Malta became a kind of teaching institution, treating patients from all over Christendorr. In 1653 Louis XIV of France gave the Knights four Caribbean islands, but they soon sold them to the French West India Co. (Ref. 10, 11) (Continue on page 944)

GREECE AND UPPER BALKANS

Greece and most of the Balkans were under Ottoman rule although several Christian communities had survived and there was some degree of local autonomy by the prelates of Greek and Serbian churches. Many of the men of those western Christian Balkans fought as mercenaries, either for Venice or Constantinople. The Turks helped Istran (Stephen) Bocskay drive the Austrians out of Transylvania in 1605 and by the Austro Turkish Treaty of Zsitva-Torok, this area was left to his control. (See also HUNGARY, this chapter). (Ref. 12, 13)

Commercial agriculture became increasingly important with cotton, tobacco, wheat and maize produced by entrepreneurs, a feature which led to the diminution of military land-holding. After 1638 there was no more recruiting of Christian boys for Ottoman administration and the army and this, in turn, meant a widening gap between Christian and Moslem, landlord and peasant, village and town. Eventually this shift in relationships destroyed the Ottoman polity. (Ref. 14) Travel in the Balkans could be precarious and in open country travelers deployed their carriages in a circle at night, with everyone ready for defense, just as in the American west, centuries later. (Ref. 15)

The great Venetian Admiral Francesco Morosini captured the Peloponnesus and laid siege to Athens in 1687. One of his shells hit a powder magazine which the Turks had stored in the Parthenon and it blew up, reducing the structure to its present state. (Ref. 16) The City of Senj of Croatia was the home of the Christian, Uskok pirates and Venice had to make war against them from 1613 on in order to protect its trade and its coastal regions such as Cattaro, Corfu and Levkas. We have noted above that near the end of the century Albanians became the grand viziers of Turkey. (Ref. 17) (Continue on page 946)

ITALY

Italy continued in an age of invasion with the monarchs of Europe and petty Italian princes fighting over its territory. Most of the old ruling families of the city-states were dying out and Italy had little history of its own in this century. Even Venice fell into some decline and only in its war with Turkey was there some vestige of its earlier glory. The wealthy class of that city-state now abandoned trade and put all its resources into farming. Still, thanks to foreign shipping, Venice remained a very busy port. It was the rise of agricultural prices that drove Venetian capital to the land. (Ref. 18) Genoa lost its island of Corsica and for reasons still debatable, its credit collapsed. Braudel (Ref. 19) believes that it had to do with a change in the discount rate of bills of exchange. A bill had to acquire value as it went from country to country, or someone lost all. The plague obviously did not help. The Black Death killed a million people in north Italy between 1628 and 1631 and in Genoa there were perhaps 700 rich nobles left out of about 80,000 inhabitants. In Venice there were only 14 or 15 wealthy patricians lef t who were capable of holding high state positions. Florence barely existed, being little more than the Grand Duke's court. He had seized everything - money, the right to govern and distribute honors. (Ref. 20) In spite of all these troubles in Italy, active Jewish colonies survived for many years in Piedmont, Venice, Mantua and Ferrara. Jews even launched Leghorn on a prosperous new career in this century. (Ref. 21)

One of Italy's great men, Galileo Galilei, astronomer, experimental physicist and mathematician was throttled by the Inquisition, still being promoted by the Church. The outstanding anatomist of the age was Marcello Malpighi, born at Bologna and teacher of medicine there for 25 years. His descriptions of capillaries, Malpighian tufts and corpuscles are only a few of his multitude of important anatomical discoveries. (Ref. 22, 23, 24, 25)

The island of Sicily remained rooted to the past, pretty well untouched by the machinations of politics and commercialization seen in the market society of most of Europe. (Ref. 26) (Continue on page 947)

CENTRAL EUROPE

Most of central Europe was still a part of the Holy Roman Empire, which, however, consisted of several more or less separate parts. First there was a loosely bound union of almost completely independent German states, seven in number, each ruled by an "Elector" and nominally subject to the Habsburg emperor, who was routinely elected by those Electors. The Protestants of the north gave no support militarily, unless the emperor paid for it. Secondly, there was the true Habsburg Empire, which consisted of the Archduchy of Austria, the Kingdom of Bohemia-Moravia, Silesia, the Kingdom of Hungary and other Balkan territories conquered from the Turks. The Habsburgs also had claims to the throne of Spain with all its possessions in Europe. (Ref. 27) But from 1618 to 1648 the terrible Thirty Years War raged, disrupting the entire continent. This was basically a war of mercenary soldiers, and in lieu of pay they lived on the country, with resulting robbery, pillage and outrage. Neither side won, but hostilities finally stopped with the Treaty of Westphalia. The trouble started in the previous century when Ferdinand took over the German and Austrian half of Charles V's Habsburg Empire. The northern German barons protested against that Catholic ruler, and the conflagration started as a civil conflict of Protestant, northern Germany against Catholic, southern areas. It very soon became complicated, however, by the intervention of various other domestic and foreign elements. Some feel that foreign interference and pressures on the German princes actually precipitated the conflict. It had some similarities to the civil war in England and the War of the Fronde in France, in that in each case the crown was Catholic and the recalcitrant nobles tended to be Protestants. It is to be re-emphasized that the Thirty Years War was brutal and destructive, involving a semi-guerrilla force, which plundered, raped and killed wantonly. It was a series of bloody campaigns in which civilians often suffered more than soldiers. The following material, giving more of the actual details of this war, has been taken chiefly from Roden (Ref. 28), unless otherwise indicated. (Continue on page 948)

THE THIRTY YEARS WAR

UNDERLYING CAUSES

To some this was primarily a religious war in defense of one of the three faiths involved. The Calvinists fought for recognition as co-equals with Lutheranism and Catholicism. For most rulers it was a political struggle; for the Habsburgs it was a struggle to retain some measure of control over the various political-units in Germany and to keep some semblance of empire. It was also a civil war among jealous territorial princes and a dynastic struggle among ruling families such as the Wittelbachs in Bavaria. It was a predatory war fought by mercenary generals for fame, power and booty. Finally, it was an international war for territorial and economic gains, including efforts of Dutch, - Spaniards, Swedes, Bohemians and French.

STAGES OF THE WAR (Named for Habsburg opponents in each period)

BOHEMIAN PHASE

Frederick V of the Palatinate became a Calvinist Bohemian king and fought Habsburg Ferdinand II, but he got poor support and lasted only one winter. Ferdinand occupied and completely subdued all of Bohemia, outlawed the Czech language and replaced the elective kingship by the hereditary rule of the Habsburgs. The remarkable achievements of the Bohemian Baron von Wallenstein during the war years are detailed in subsequent paragraphs and the CZECHOSLOVAKIA section of this chapter.

DANISH PHASE

Christian IV of Denmark responded to Franco-English pressure and invaded lower Saxony, but was eventually defeated by both General Tilly and General Wallenstein, of the Catholic imperialist forces. In fact, by 1630 imperial and Catholic power had reached its greatest mark and the German princes, Catholic and Protestant alike, began to worry about their own rights and powers.

SWEDISH PHASE

After Sweden's Gustavus Adolphus finished his Polish War, in which he obtained the Lithuanian coast and bases in Prussia, he swung around and into Germany, probably for both religious and territorial reasons. After defeating Tilly near Leipzig, Gustavus, who spoke fluent German (learned from his mother), became a German hero and Protestant forces flocked to his side. The Swedes moved far into south Germany and even occupied Munich. In 1632, in a battle with Wallenstein, now restored to power again by the Habsburgs, Gustavus Adolphus was killed while leading his victorious forces. Swedish power was at once dimmed by the disappearance of this forceful king-general and his minister, Oxenstierna, could not carry the field much longer. Furthermore, after Wallenstein was murdered by some of his own sub-generals, the Catholic forces again became more active and forced the Swedes out of southern Germany. Then Saxony made a separate peace with Errperor Ferdinand III, in the Peace of Prague (1635). The terms again gave much power to the emperor, and although accepted unwillingly by most of the German princes, France could not acquiesce in this increase in imperial power.

Map taken from Reference 97

FRENCH PHASE

So, in 1635 France declared war on Spain and Austria, and began full scale war in the Pyrenees, in the north against the Spanish Netherlands and in the east against Spanish and Austrian possessions in Germany. In the long run Swedish-French power prevailed almost everywhere and Germany was thoroughly exhausted. Debates about peace drug on in Westphalia for 4 years while armies continued to fight, with the final peace concluded in 1648.

THE PEACE OF WESTPHALIA

The war left the basic Habsburg Empire intact but destitute. Only the territorial lords seemed to get a clear-cut victory. Prussia emerged as a strong state and Bavaria gained territory and retained the Upper Palatinate. While most German cities were ruined, Hamburg actually prospered by taking over the previous function of Antwerp as a center of refuge for all exiles, after the latter city had fallen to the Spaniards. (Ref. 29) No religious freedom remained in the Habsburg hereditary lands. France and Spain remained at war for another 11 years after the treaty, but France, along with Sweden, reaped the most important benefits. Toul, Metz and Verdun were all given to France, along with other valuable cities and territories in Alsace which gave a bridgehead whereby France could move forces into Germany at will. Sweden got western Pomerania, Stettin and many harbors, keeping good control over northern Germany. Holland and the Swiss Cantons were permanently free.

Following the Treaty of Westphalia the histories of Germany and Austria definitely diverge, with various German states remaining definitely independent, although soon to be dominated by Prussia. The Habsburgs confined their interests and power to the soon to be formed Austrio-Hungarian Empire. The war had cut the population of Germany from 20,000,000 to 13,500,000 and there was a dearth of men. At the Congress of Franconia in Nuremberg in 1650 a resolution was adopted that every man should be allowed two wives and every male should be so reminded from the pulpits. Taxes were imposed upon unmarried women. By 1700 equality of the sexes had been restored and there were again 20,000,000 Germans.

The many Jews in Germany led a precarious existence in this century. In Frankfort in 1614 a Christian crowd forced entry into a ghetto and after a night of plunder and destruction, compelled 1,380 Jews to leave the city. In general the higher classes of people and clergy were tolerant, but the lower clergy and masses were easily stirred to a frenzy of hate. After the Thirty Years War persecution lessened and the Jewish settlements expanded rapidly.

The second half of the 17th century after the Treaty of Westphalia presents an entirely new picture in Central Europe and we shall now examine that situation in more detail.

GERMANY

Although still divided into many separate states, overall the peasants of Germany occupied a middle ground between the serfs of the east and the freer life to the west. Their slow emancipation was an important reason for the slow appearance of the industrial revolution in Germany. The food situation was helped greatly as the potato, yielding 4 times as much carbohydrate per acre as wheat, reached even eastern Germany in this century. (Ref. 30) Drunkenness became a universal German characteristic, perhaps fueled by various strong spirits developed by the Dutch. (Ref. 31) The Fuggers had gone bankrupt in 1627; the Hanseatic League, with their trade taken over by Holland, was dissolved in 1669. (Ref. 32) Since prior to that wage-earners had begun to make up at least 50% of the Hanseatic town populations, this probably meant considerable change in life styles. (Ref. 33) German intellectual power could not be denied. Gottfred Wilhelm Leibniz, man of the world, intimate with statesmen and courts, accepting both Protestantism and Catholicism, writing 50 treatises and embracing God and the world with desperate optimism, was the great philosopher of Central Europe, living and working at various times in Leipsig, Jena, Altdorf, Mainz and finally Berlin, where he was the first president of the Berlin Scientific Society. He published an infinitesimal calculus in 1684, 3 years before Newton's similar work. (Ref. 34, 35) (Continue on page 948)

It may help to clarify the rather confusing situation in Germany if we discuss some of the more important divisions, separately.

BRANDENBURG - PRUSSIA

After 1618 these two states were united by marriage of two branches of Hohenzollerns and were under the same ruler. This was the third largest state in Germany, behind only Bavaria and Saxony in size. (Ref. 36) During the Thirty Years War the area had been devastated by the Swedes, but the accession of Frederick William Hohenzollern, the Great Elector, in 1640, led to an astonishingly rapid recovery in economy, prestige and power. He organized a central government with a civil service, a postal system and a graduated income tax, along with improved roads and a canal system which permitted the growth of Berlin. Because the state was in the path of the Swedish armies in another of their attempts to conquer Poland (First Northern War of 1655-1660), Frederick was inevitably drawn in, but in the end he did gain full sovereignty over East Prussia. In 1680 his warships even defeated the Spanish navy off the Portuguese coast and by 1688 he had a modern standing army of 30,000 men to protect his 1,000,000 people. (Ref. 37)

The success of Frederick's administrative system started Prussia on a path of more absolute monarchy, while Holland and England were moving toward decentralization of government. For many years the Prussian monarch was intermittently at war with France and/or Sweden, sometimes with and sometimes against other German states and the empire, but finally affecting a rapproachment with Louis XIV, joining Saxony, Bavaria and some other states already getting subsidies from France. Frederick broke with that country only after the French king had revoked the Edict of Nantes, in 1685, resuming the persecution of the Huguenots. 15,000 to 20,000 of the latter went to settle in Prussian cities and became influential in cultural life then and for centuries to come.

The Great Elector's pretentious son, Frederick III, took over Prussia in 1688. His constructive efforts were few and concerned entirely with cultural advancements - establishing an Academy of Arts in 1696 and the University of Halle in 1694, which soon became a center for the emancipation of German culture from foreign influence. But the enormous sums he spent on beautifying Berlin, importing architects, painters, etc. almost bankrupted his state. (Ref. 38) In 1700 Berlin had 25,000 Protestant, frugal, efficient people and Prussia was spread all over the northern European plain from the Rhine at Holland to the Neman, some 500 miles east, but cut off from the sea, with poor soil and no natural re- sources. (Ref. 39) (Continue on page 949)

BAVARIA

Duke Maxmilian I ruled through the Thirty Years War as an absolutist, with full support of the Catholic Church, actually gaining some territory at the final peace treaty. During the succeeding reign of the next Elector, Maximilian II Immanuel, Bavaria became one of the focal points of European intrigue, chiefly because of involvement in the War of the Spanish Succession of 1700. Bavaria's treasury was subsidized by-the French. (Continue on page 951)

SAXONY

Saxony quickly regained its importance after the terrible Thirty Years War and Leipzig became a center for book trade, newspapers and journals. Dresden's Art Gallery was one of the best in the north. But Saxony's Elector, Frederick Augustus I, accepted the elective crown of Poland in 1697 and the unnatural tie-up of Saxony and Poland eventually led to the downfall of both. We shall hear much more of this under the discussion of POLAND later in this chapter. (Continue on page 952)

LESSER GERMAN STATES

Palatinate, Hanover, Wurttemberg, Baden, Hesse and Mecklenburg remained as other important states in this period, in which overall there were some 300 separate principalities. One of the most basic discoveries of the age was made by the Jesuit, Athanius Kircher of Fulda, Hesse, when he initiated the use of the microscope in diagnosing disease and found the "worms" in the blood of plague victims and realized their significance. (Continue on page 953)

AUSTRIA

To regress for a moment, the learned Emperor Rudolf II ruled the Habsburgs domains from the last quarter of the 16th century on into this 17th. As the new century began he lost Hungary, Moravia and Austria to his brother Matthias and when Rudolf died in 1612, Matthias became emperor, living just long enough to see the beginning of the Thirty Years War. He was succeeded by Ferdinand II.

Austria was a Catholic world with a heavy Jesuit influence. The center of the empire was the Hofburg palace in Vienna, a structure not elegant like Versailles, but with a court of 2,000 noblemen and 30,000 servants. The Habsburg monarchy had emerged from the Treaty of Westphalia with only minor losses of territory such as Alsace, but the Holy Roman Empire, as such, had disintegrated. Ferdinand III, emperor at the end of the war, and the next four emperors, were all skilled musicians and composers. There was continued hostility from France and from the Turks who surged-up on Austria's eastern frontier 300,000 strong in 1683, just after Vienna had been hit by a plague which killed 100,000 people. France supported the Turks at that time and Vienna was surrounded on three sides, with even women manning some of the defenses and the people on the point of starvation. At the lowest ebb, Jan Sobieski, the Polish king, marched through the Vienna Woods with 50,000 Poles and Austrians and put the Turks to rout. At that point Leopold I, a typical Habsburg with a swarthy complexion and a projecting lower jaw, which was almost disfiguring, was emperor. Although almost always at war he was not a warrior and preferred theology, arts, the study of genealogy and similar pursuits. The basis of his policy was that the throne and empire had been fixed on the Habsburgs by God, but in actuality his real power came from the sword of Prince Eugene of Savoy, a frail man born in Paris and rejected by the French army, and who had turned to Leopold to become general of the cavalry at age 26 and commander of the Imperial Army of Hungary at 34. It was he who finally crushed the Sultan's main forces, 3 times larger than his own, at Zenta in September of 1697. This led to the Peace of Karlowitz in 1699 which gave all Hungary, with the exception of Croatia, to the Habsburg Empire. (Ref. 40)

In this century Salzburg was a separate territory and was not even involved in the Thirty Years War. A University was established there in 1623. (Continue on page 954)

HUNGARY

As the century opened Hungary was still a partitioned country and a battered one. Besides Turkish atrocities, the Habsburg administration began to take land from the estates in eastern Hungary and forced a counter-reformation against the Protestants. Istvan (Stephen) Bocskay revolted against the Austrians with an army of wild soldier-herdsmen and drove the emperor 's General Basta out. Bocskay became the prince of an enlarged Transylvania and by the Treaty of Vienna of 1606, the Protestants were declared equal to the Catholics. In the same year a new treaty with the Ottoman Porte cancelled all tribute to the sultan, although the territories remained as before. There were then no Turkish aggressive moves for a half century. In 1608 the State Assembly had proclaimed the perpetual serfdom of peasants, and later a group of these called "Haiduks" took to the hills and lived by marauding and pillaging the Turks. (Ref. 41, 42)

A successor prince of Transylvania, Gabriel Bethlen (also Bethlen Gabor), developed mines, industry, and foreign trade and promoted education. He and his successor, Rakoczi I (1630-1644) were able to hold off the Habsburgs. The power and status of Transylvania ended, however, when the Turks made another great excursion and installed once again an Ottoman prince over that area. The Hungarians appealed to Leopold I in Vienna for help but he was fighting France and was also reluctant to offend the sultan and gave only token help. Hungary went into a decline and soon the Turks swept across to the walls of Vienna. As described above in the section on AUSTRIA, the tide soon turned and the Turks were beaten back across the Danube. As noted previously too, the Peace of Karlowitz in 1699 gave all of Hungary with the exception of Croatia, back to the Habsburgs. The Hungarian Diet fixed the succession of the ruler of Hungary in the male line of the Habsburgs, so that thereafter there was truly an Austro-Hungarian Empire. (Ref. 43)

An interesting side-light relative to the long, intermittent Christian-Turkish wars in Hungary had to do with the basic prerequisites of battle. Just as modern warfare would grind to a halt without gasoline and related substances, so the 16th and 17th century warfare was inconceivable without barley (or oats) for the cavalry. "No barley, no war."1 At about the same time Hungarian cattle breeders found that they could obtain great profits exporting cattle to western Europe, so they stopped cultivating their arable land and bought grain rather than producing it. (Ref. 44) (Continue on page 954)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Moravia was a margraviate and Bohemia a kingdom, both under the domination of the Habsburg family, although a Calvinist king was elected in Bohemia in 1618. One of the triggers that initiated the Thirty Years War was a rebellion in Bohemia in that year against heavy taxes which had been levied on all Protestants by Emperor Ferdinand as a measure to bring the country back to Catholicism and Habsburg obedience. The rebellion was put down over a period of 3 years of war by the emperor with troops and money from Spain, German Catholics and the Pope. Thereafter only the Catholic religion was permitted in both Bohemia and Moravia. (Ref. 46) During that war a petty Bohemian nobleman,

Albrecht von Wallenstein, made soldiering into a vast speculative business. Although nominally only a contractor for the emperor, in effect he was almost a sovereign himself, because of the size of military forces which he commanded and supplied by taxation, outright plunder and massive, complex market transactions. In the latter, he cooperated with a Flemish businessman named Hans De Witte. Both were untouched by religious fervor or business scruples, but they developed an army of exceptional efficiency, numbering over 50,000 at its peak. Wallenstein's assassination was arranged by some of his enemies in the emperor's court in 1634. (Ref. 47)

Late in the Thirty Years War Bohemia was invaded again, this time by Swedes under Gustavus Adolphus. Ferdinand II bore the brunt of the fighting, but even then the Swedes penetrated through until they were actually in sight of Vienna. Then their long supply lines began to fail and they withdrew. But Bohemia was ruined, with only 6,000 villages out of an original 35,000 considered habitable. The population fell from 2,000,000 to 700,000. (Ref. 48) The lower classes of Bohemia along with the city-states of Germany were subordinated to princely power based on control by standing, professional armies. (Ref. 49) Recovery began, somewhat, at the end of the century when, along with Saxony, the Bohemian woolen and linen industries began to even outdo the old English and Flemish markets. (Ref. 50) (Continue on page 954)

SWITZERLAND

The long antagonism of the buffer state of Savoy and Switzerland flared again as the Savoyards attacked Geneva in 1602. The attack was frustrated, but it resulted in a reaffirmation of alliance between the whole Swiss Confederation and France, although the Catholic cantons also retained their alliance with Spain. (Ref. 51) Officially the Swiss remained neutral in the Thirty Years War but they were involved some on their border at the Valtelline Pass, the most important link between Habsburg Austria and their Spanish possessions in Italy. In 1625 the pass was seized by a Swiss force in French pay, but in 1637 pastor George Jenatsch, originally a Protestant from Zurich, turned Catholic, secured Austrian aid and drove out the French. By treaty of 1639 the passes were left open to the use of Spanish troops. The chief occupation of the Swiss in the last half of the century was fighting, but usually as mercenaries. Tens of thousands of their men hired out in this way, particularly in France. Some of the Swiss cities, particularly Basle, became important relay stations for intercontinental traffic where overland vehicular freight, the Rhine and mule trains from the mountains came together. Some of the large transport firms made their headquarters in Switzerland. (Ref. 52) (Continue on page 956)

WESTERN EUROPE

All of the Atlantic coast nations had overseas empires, but the rise of French and British enterprise was made possible by smooth cooperation between business capital and government administrations. In contrast to Spain's constant constraints of the market and confiscatory taxation of private capital, the northern nations set taxation limits and allowed total wealth, private and public, to expand. (Ref. 53) (Continue on page 958)

SPAIN

The Habsburgs had convinced the Castilian nobility that the Spanish, as the strongest, most orthodox and "purest" people in Europe, should police Germany and the Netherlands, control France and invade England2. In these imperial enterprises, the Spanish manpower and the American gold and silver were squandered. Spain became a mere channel for its colonies' silver as it quickly went into the purses of other nations. (Ref. 54)

There was further enfeeblement by the Inquisition and by decline of Spanish industries because of high taxes. The only profitable enterprises seemed to be the making of cheap brandy, production of some cotton and some iron works, particularly in the Basque area where every village seemed to have a forge. Smelting was done with charcoal, which exhausted the forests. Overall, however, it was a period of industrial, commercial and financial failures, along with inadequate government, military defeats and some eleven general famines during the century. (Ref. 55)

In the 1620s and 1630s a powerful Dutch West India Company cut the Spanish shipping lines and stopped the flow of silver from America and thus indirectly allowed French and English settlements in the Caribbean. (Ref. 56) The wool industry was gradually lost to German wool and imported cotton. By 1630 there was violence and revolt. The situation was certainly not helped by terrible epidemics of plague between 1647 and 1654 in which half the population of Seville died. In Galacia the Church and other land owners tried to draw in the land leases (see page 623) and the tenants were thrown into long, legal struggles.

Some migrated to America, Portugal and Madrid. (Ref. 57) War with France, which began as an offshoot of the Thirty Years War, continued on for 12 years after the Treaty of Wesphalia but finally ended in 1659 with the Peace of the Pyrenees, after which Spain was pushed back behind the Pyrenees for good and began sinking down to the level of a secondary power. Even so Spain did add to her overseas empire with the addition of the Philippine Islands.

There is little doubt but what religious issues played a great part in the decline of Spain. Besides the terrible effects of the Inquisition, Philip III's deep religious devotion was a great factor in that as he personally developed 9,000 monasteries he put 1/3 of the entire population in the church service and he left the government entirely to the Duke of Lerma. Intrigue, corruption and decline followed. By 1700 the male line of the Spanish Habsburgs died out. Leopold of Austria had trained his younger son, Karl, to be King of Spain, but due to the early death of the older brother Joseph, who was the Austrian-line successor, Karl had to take over Austria instead of Spain. The resulting vacuum resulted in the War of the Spanish Succession, starting in 1700 and carrying on into the next century.

A few other remarks about Spain in this period seem indicated. Velasquez was a fine painter in that country. A feature often little noticed was the great influx of French into the Iberian peninsula. Artisans, odd job men, retailers, masons, builders as well as peasant farmers came from France apparently because of over-population there. As many as 200,000 Frenchmen may have been in Spain by 1669. (Ref. 58) (Continue on page 958)

PORTUGAL

Portuguese power and prosperity continued to decline under the Spanish rule which had begun in 1580. By 1640, however, a revolt organized by a Professor Ribeiro, supported by the nobility and the clergy and financed some by France, then at war with Spain, succeeded and the Duke of Braganza became the Portuguese leader. After the country became officially independent by the Treaty of Lisbon in 1668, the Duke became King Joao IV. There followed 28 years of war with Spain to defend that independence. Later, while Pedro II was king, gold fields were discovered in Brazil and after 1697 the Portuguese court was one of the most lavish in Europe, and no local money was needed for support. Multiple aqueducts brought water from the mountains to Portuguese cities throughout this century. (Ref. 59) (Continue on page 960)

FRANCE (The Century of Louis XIV, the Sun-King)

After the assassination of Henri IV in 1610, civil and religious war again erupted, not to end until 1624 when Armand Jean du Plessis, duc de Richelieu (he had been made Cardinal in 1622) took over the reigns of government, as Louis XIII remained chiefly a figure-head. The king died in 1643 of intestinal tuberculosis.  (Ref. 60) Although not a good financial administrator, for better or worse Richelieu increased the power of the royal bureaucracy at the expense of the nobles and Huguenots. His greatest achievements, however, were in foreign affairs, as he restored French influence in Italy, the Netherlands, Germany and Sweden. His work actually laid the foundation for the later power of Louis XIV, all of this occurring in spite of droughts, locust plagues and intermittent famines. (Ref. 61)

France's participation in the Thirty Years War was chiefly as an ally of Sweden, first with subsidies and later with troops who fought the Bavarians. Along with the Swedes they ravaged Bavaria on their second invasion in 1648, just before the Treaty of Westphalia in which France received absolute sovereignty over Metz, Toul, Verdun and Upper and Lower Alsace, although some of those cities retained their membership in the Habsburg Empire. The French monarchy gradually became the greatest and most consolidated power in Europe. One reason for this domination was manpower, as France had 20,000,000 people in 1660 while Spain and England each had but 5,000,000 and Italy 6,000,000. The Holy Roman Empire had 21,000,000 but it was an empire in name only and was impoverished by the Thirty Years War. Although the French had cannon, they were not very effective. They developed a flintlock rifle by 1630, but it was accurate only up to 100 yards and until the end of the century the steel-headed pike on a wooden shaft was still the main infantry weapon. (Ref. 62)

Another reason for French supremacy is to be found in the calibre of its chief ministers. Guilio Mazarini, born in Sicily, sent as papal nuncio to Paris, caught the eye of Richelieu and after he had been made a cardinal (even though he had never been ordained a priest) in 1641, he followed Richelieu as chief minister under the name of Jules Mazarin, in 1642. He was the guiding hand at the Treaty of Westphalia. He served the Queen Mother well (Louis XIV was but 5 years old when he came to the throne) and perhaps was her lover. Even the king was only 1/4 French, being 1/2 Spanish from Aragon, Basque and Castilian lines (with possibly some Jewish and Moorish blood in the back-ground) by his mother Anne of Austria and 1/4 Italian by his grandmother, Marie de Medici. (Ref. 63) He was only 5' 5" tall, but robust, a good horseman and dancer, a skillful jouster and could turn a woman's head. (Ref. 64) He was basically a country person, loving the outdoors and his mind was not as good as his manners. He reigned from 1643 to 1715. Early in his rule some discontented nobles formed a resistance league, the "Fronde", which eventually came to open rebellion resulting in disruption of the Paris government and civil war in 1652. The nobles were conclusively defeated by the Crown and were tamed at the price of escaping taxations so that thereafter the economic burdens of the throne were thrown entirely on the lower classes. It was in this civil war, chiefly a war by Prince de Conde, trying to unseat Mazarin, that Mademoiselle de Montpersier, niece of Louis XIII, became known as the "Maid of Orleans" as she led her soldiers to take Orleans and later Paris, for Conde'. McNeill (Ref. 65) says that the successful suppression of the Fronde marked a turning point in European war and statecraft. Northern Europe then developed civilian control of army supply, paid soldiers regularly with money from tax revenues and learned to coordinate infantry, cavalry and artillery. All this had already been done by the 15th century in Italian city-states.

At the same time as the "Fronde", France was continuing a 23 year war with Spain, ending it in 1659 in the Peace of the Pyrenees, which probably only set up a situation which led to still another, later war. One cannot but help but relate France and German~ in this period to the Middle East in the 20th century where civil wars and wars with neighbors and various types of foreign interventions occur almost simultaneously and constantly. The Peace of the Pyrenees, besides yielding some territories to France, gave Marie Teresa, Spanish King Philip's daughter, in marriage to Louis XIV. Supposedly Louis, in turn, gave up all rights to succession to the Spanish throne. The peace was a triumph for Mazarin, who soon amassed a tremendous personal fortune amid the poverty of the common people. In the latter part of his reign, Louis also began to show defects of bigotry, vainness and arrogance. In spite of everything, however, France was well governed. Laws were revised into the Code Louis (1667-1673), a system of police was established in Paris, the streets of that city were paved and lighted by 5,000 lamps.

Upon Mazarin's death Nicolas Fouquet became chief finance minister, but was found to be incredibly corrupt. He was followed by Jean Baptiste Colbert, a remarkably able man who formed a nationally unified system of agriculture, industry, commerce and finance to support the "Grand Monarchy". Paris had already become a fabulous place, surrounded by a ring of markets. Although livestock markets were held twice a week, there might be 3,000 horses in any one day. Every district had its livery stable. (Ref. 66) But there was scarcely a year without famine someplace in France. Colbert actually sacrificed agriculture to industry, as he brought in Venetian glassworkers, Swedish iron workers and Dutch cloth-makers. By 1669 there were 44,000 looms in the country. The wealth of the business classes grew, but the condition of the workers became lower than ever on the economic scale. It has often been said that northern France was the industrial area while southern France was wine country. That division is somewhat misleading as witness Languedoc in the heart of the wine country with 450,000 textile workers in 1680 and some 12,000 artisans scattered among the villages of Orleans. (Ref. 67) In 1681 the Languedoc canal was completed, connecting the Bay of Biscay to the Mediterranean via the canal, the Rhone and the Garonne rivers. (Ref. 68)

By the time of Colbert's death in 1683, France had known 10 years of its greatest prosperity, but it had not been easy. Representing the classical Frank of French heritage, Colbert had had trouble with the more frivolous Gauls. The great nobles refused to invest in his overseas projects and the workmen refused to give up their 60 public holidays a year (not counting Sundays) and there were many strikes. Colbert, himself, worked 15 hours a day, 7 days a week. Lest we think too highly of him, however, it should be noted that he encouraged the slave trade and increased the number of galleys in the French navy from 6 to 40, each containing 200 slave oarsmen. He did not use blacks for these galleys, as he felt that they had no stamina and died too quickly, but used French criminals and captured Turks. (Ref. 69) His shipbuilding exploited the forestry resources of the entire kingdom. (Ref. 70)

This was an age of strict manners and loose morals. Public baths became less frequent than previously both because of the fear of infections, particularly syphilis, and the moral concepts of the Church. Even at the king's court baths were taken only rarely, in cases of sickness. (Ref. 71) Table manners were improving and although the "Sun King" ate with his fingers, forks were now in general use and napkins were in vogue. As with many kings and most European nobles, the monarch had many women, some of whom have become among the famous courtesans of history. But there were also famous and productive men in this era. Artists, playwrights (such as Moliere), scultpors, literary men and scientists all thrived in this glorious period of France. We shall speak of Huygens, Descartes, and others in the separate science summary at the end of this chapter. The science of surgery was elevated in France after Felix operated successfully on King Louis XIV's fistula. It was decreed to be a liberal art and its exponents began to assume a high rank in French society. (Ref. 72) There were 24 medical schools in France, of which 4 were dominant - Montpellier, Paris, Toulouse and Strasbourg (Ref. 73), but it must be admitted that in general medicine was bad. Infant mortality, helped by the physicians' bleeding, purging and emetics, was appalling. (Ref. 74) It seems strange that as late as this 17th century the muddy Seine was the chief water source for the city of Paris and no purification system was present. Water was sold by carriers who extolled its virtues, but it was an admitted purgative and, of course, unpleasant for foreigners. (Ref. 75) Religion was an important phase of life and as important as politics is now. One of the scientist-mathematicians of the age was also one of the prominent figures in the great religious furors of the time. Blaise Pascal at age 11 had already composed a treatise on vibrating bodies and at 19 he contrived a computing machine. Later he came close to inventing the calculus, but by that time he was also embroiled in the intra-faith controversy between Jansenism and Jesuitism. Blase's "Provincial Letters" became the strongest Jansenist denunciation of the Jesuit posture. In a sense, Jansenism, in its reformation attitude with the Catholic Church, was the final effort of the Reformation in France.

Map from Reference 97

Louis XIV was suspected by the rest of Europe of wanting to conquer the continent, but actually his military objectives may have been much less extensive, wanting only to secure his own borders from the Spanish Netherlands in the north down to the Barcelonette Valley, which had access from Italy. Thus, the two aggressive wars of France were the War of Devolution to lay claim to a part of the Spanish Netherlands (1667-1678) and the attack in the Dutch Republic in 1672, which unfortunately flared into a European-wide war, in spite of Louis' best attempts at arbitration. Louis XIV built the great palace at Versailles near the end of the century so that he would never have to return to Paris, but actually he lived there only during his later years. Like most feudal kings he was always on the move, generally at war. (Ref. 76) Louis kept a standing peace-time army of 150,000 men, which was increased to 400,000 in the event of war. Versailles became the official seat of government in May of 1682. The palace had 3,000 mica-paned windows in 270 rooms, but no baths or toilets. There were 1,500 jets of water from octagonal lakes. When there was no war in progress with Holland, some 4 million tulip bulbs were imported from that country each year. The construction required 36,000 men, 6,000 horses and there was a high mortality rate from both injury and malaria. (Ref. 77)

Louis' relations with the Protestant Huguenots of France were one of the crucial defects of his reign. Fluctuating between tolerance and non-tolerance for years, this Catholic king finally, in 1681, turned again to a Holy war against the Protestant Huguenots. The majority of the latter, terrified, pretended conversion, but thousands fled, abandoning homes and properties. In 1685 the king revoked the Edict of Nantes and France was almost entirely Catholic. The few remaining Huguenots in many provinces were then subjected to horrible tortures, some say much worse than the later revolutionary terror of 1793. Of the 1,500,000 Huguenots in the country in 1660, 400,000 escaped across guarded borders. The Elector of Brandenburg gave them so friendly a reception that by 1697 one-fifth of Berlin was French. The Protestants were unpopular in France probably for the same reason that Jews were unpopular in pre-World War II Germany - they were too rich, successful and clannish. (Ref. 78)

Colbert's massive system of state-regulated commerce and industry had begun to collapse before his death in 1683. (Ref. 79) Many factors played their part - the drain of men from the farm to the factory and battlefield, self strangulation from governmental regulation, the loss of the Huguenot economic skills and some of their savings. Taxes rose even as prosperity declined. Then, as a final straw, Louis XIV's imperialism frightened Emperor Leopold I, Elector Maximilian II Emanuel of Bavaria, the Elector of Brandenburg, King Karl (Charles) XI of Sweden and Stadhalder William III of the United Provinces (Netherlands) into forming the League of Augsburg for defense against the French. Louis then made a great mistake. He attacked Germany and thus committed himself to a long, debilitating war and freed his Dutch enemy to help launch William III in his conquest of England. By 1695 Louis had only second-rate generals left and although they were still celebrating victories, the French people, taxed as never before, were nearing exhaustion in body and spirit. In 1694 famine had been added, the national economy verged on collapse, transportation was in chaos, foreign commerce was at a standstill because of enemy fleet blockades and privateers. (Ref. 80) Poverty, famine, disease and war reduced the population of France from some 23,000,000 in 1670 to some 19,000,000 in 1700. At last Louis realized his follies in continuing warfare and the Peace of Ryswick (1697) ended the war in so far as England, Holland and Spain were concerned. Separate peace was signed later with the German empire.

We must not make the mistake of centering all our attention on Paris and the Court in these centuries. Much of what is present day France had only limited or no real allegiance to the central government. In Aquitaine, for example, between 1590 and 1715 there were about 500 insurrections or would-be insurrections among the peasants. In Savoy, which remained separate from France proper in the early century under Charles-Emmanuel I, there were innumerable calamities - plague, extreme poverty, bad harvests and wars of their own. Out of this turmoil a new aristocracy supplanted the old feudal nobility. (Ref. 81) (Continue on page 961)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

In 1609 Spain recognized the independence of 7 provinces of which Holland was the chief one, while keeping the entire southern Spanish Netherlands. Those 7 provinces warred with Spain (1621-1648) as an off-shoot of the Thirty Years War and after the peace, formed in essence, the Dutch Republic. (Ref. 82) It was initially ruled by a States-General made up of representatives from each of the provincial assemblies. The control was an oligarchy of business men with the aristocratic House of Orange given the control of the army. Those two ruling classes clashed at intervals, but it did not seriously interfere with the tremendous prosperity and progress of the country. In the first half of the century Holland had the intellectual leadership of Europe. The Frenchman, Descartes, working in Holland, developed his laws of refraction, his philosophy and his mathematics in his Discourse on Method, published in 1637. (Ref. 83) Van Leeuwenhoek did his early work with the microscope and single-celled organisms; the artists Rembrandt, Hals, Vermeer and Ruisdael did their painting; and Baruch Espinosa, later known simply as "Spinoza", born in Armsterdam of Jewish-Spanish heritage, wrote his philosophy, alienating all religion, not accepting Christianity - and he was cast out of Judaism. Christian Huygens, who developed the wave theory of light was second only to Newton as the greatest scientist of the age, inventing among other things, the pendulum clock. (Ref. 84) Two Dutchmen were the greatest medical teachers of the time - Sylvius and Boerhaave, both at Leiden. Jan Baptiste van Helmont (1577-1644) was the leading Paracelsian and iatrochemist of the century, although he re jected Paracelsius ' astrology, as well as the medicine practiced by most churchmen of the era. He felt that enzymes were fundamental to all physiological mechanisms, a most modern concept. (Ref. 85)

Amsterdam became the financial and trade center of the world, where both expertise and credit were readily available. When Lisbon was closed to Dutch trade as a result of French and English influence, the Dutch had to find their own way to the East and they were soon challenging command of the Indies with Portugal. The Dutch navy became supreme, supplanting Portuguese commercial power in the South Seas. The Dutch East India Company took control in Batavia in 1619, Ceylon in 1638, the Cape of Good Hope in 1652 and Sumatra in 1667. It paid dividends averaging 18% over a period of 198 years. Of 20,000 vessels carrying the maritime commerce of Europe in 1665, 15,000 were Dutch. In the middle of the century 33% of busy Amsterdam's East India trade was in pepper. (Ref. 86, 87)

But to regress a little, in the middle of the century Holland had some serious difficulties. It was in 1651 that the English Parliament passed a Navigation Act forbidding foreign vessels to bring any merchandise into England except that locally produced. One of the Dutch-Anglo wars resulted and the supremacy of the English naval power at that time was soon obvious. An English blockade of the Dutch coast ruined the economy and the population approached starvation. At that point Jan de Witt undertook the leadership of the country. He was diligent and devoted to the tasks of the government. For awhile England continued to dominate, taking over New Amsterdam in North America, among other indignities and thus started the 2nd Dutch War. In the end the Dutch still lost New York, but gained some territory in South America and more freedom on the seas. A four year Portuguese war over Brazilian interests started in 1657. (Ref. 88) Jan de Witt and his brother Conrelis finally lost favor with their people and were assassinated. The Dutch Republic went down with them.

Protestant Holland and her successes were an affront to Louis XIV and in 1672 he entered Holland at the head of a large army and swept to within sight of the steeples of Amsterdam. William of the House of Orange (a family originally from near Avignon, France), now only 21 years of age, was nevertheless appointed Stadholder and Captain-General of the army, forever. Despite his army's holding efforts, he finally had to open the dikes and flood a great part of Holland, leaving Amsterdam as an island. After much destruction, the French withdrew and a peace came in 1678, but William's hatred of the French king never abated and even after he became King of England, the situation remained unchanged.

In the second half of the century there were 2,000,0003 people in Holland and it had an army of 120,000, with the 2nd largest navy of the world. The very fertile land had a large yield per acre, allowing one farmer to feed two non-farmers, thus allowing the promotion of commerce, industry and shipping. The Dutch had some 4,000 merchantmen ships. Amsterdam was the wealthiest city in the world and the greatest port in Europe. In reality it was an archipelago of 70 islands with 500 bridges and surrounded by great windmills on watch towers, to get the energy to keep out the sea. There were multiple industries, factories, warehouses, iron workers and beautiful homes. (Ref. 89) In the naval yards there were mechanical saws, cranes, mast-erecting machines and factories with hydraulic wheels. Dutch dairy farmers were then specializing in dairy products and the large scale export of cheese. (Ref. 90) From 1609 the Amsterdam Exchange Bank was the focus of continental trade, commerce and finance. The fortune of Amsterdam marks the decline of the great credit fairs of Europe. A stock exchange was developed, dealing in government stocks and shares in the Dutch East India Company. Even the concept of a commodities market was present, with men dealing in "futures" in such things as herring and wheat. Leyden continued as a textile manufacturing center, but already labor-management troubles appeared as a forerunner of capitalism's albatross. There were at least 5 great strikes in that city in this century. (Ref. 91, 92)

It is of interest that one of the greatest trade commodities in early 17th century Holland was the tulip bulb. This famous flower had been brought from Turkey via Carolus Clusius, previously Prefect of the Imperial Medicinal Garden of the Austrian emperor. Any unusual tulip (often resulting from a virus infection) became a status symbol and prices sky-rocketed, with the tulip trade becoming a full-time occupation for many. Speculation in "futures" followed and laws and regulations were drawn up defining the way business should be carried on. Sometimes a single bulb would sell for 2,500 florins. Finally, however, as more and more bulbs flooded the market the collapse came and by mid-century Holland was on the brink of bankruptcy with this as a major factor. Tulip-mania ended, but the flower remained. (Ref. 94) Tea was introduced to the Dutch in this century, probably from Japan and soon all Europe thought that it would cure all illnesses. (Ref. 95)

In religion the Dutch found it profitable to practice a degree of toleration broader than elsewhere in Christendom. The majority were Calvinists, but the Catholics were so numerous that suppression was impractical. Marrano Jews accumulated in many of the cities and they were granted freedom of worship but were forbidden to marry Christians.

The Jews included some of the wealthiest merchants. Some 4,000 Portuguese-Jewish families built a beautiful synagogue, which is still one of the sights -of Amsterdam. About 1630 Ashkenazaic, or Eastern (German) Jews arrived but were not welcomed well by the existing Sephardic group. Dutch cities were flooded with books and publishers and in at least five different cities there were books printed in Latin, Greek, German, English, French and Hebrew, as well as in Dutch. Amsterdam, alone, had 400 shops with books.

The area now called Belgium broke free from Spain for about 20 years at the opening of this century under Archduke Albert, but then it fell back under Spanish rule. Although ethnically diverse, the people were overwhelmingly Catholic, preferring to be dominated by a distant Catholic Spain than be subjected to Protestant neighbors. They welcomed the Jesuits and followed the intellectual lead of the Catholic University of Louvain. By the treaty of Westphalia, Spain had agreed to the closing of the River Scheldt to foreign trade, so that the city of Antwerp and the country 's entire economy was crippled. At the end of the century Belgium served as the battle ground for the French-Spanish wars, with the result that a large section of the beautiful city of Brussels was destroyed by French bombardment in 1695. It is somewhat ironic that Liege had developed a booming armaments industry, supplying much of Europe. (Ref. 96) One of the few great Flemish painters of this century was David Teniers, the Younger. (Continue on page 968)

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND AND WALES

This 17th century was a time of transition from the island kingdom of Queen Elizabeth to the great European power of the later 18th and l9th centuries. (Ref. 97) The struggle of the English throne to rule with absolute monarchy against the powers of Parliament had ensued through the reigns of Henry VII and VIII, Edward VI, Mary and Elizabeth I, but it came to an acute reckoning at the death of James I (Stuart of Scotland and son of Mary, Queen of Scots) in 1625. When Charles I then became king, civil war broke out and he countered by declaring war on Spain and France, further deteriorating the financial state of England. In 1628 Parliament issued the "Petition of Right", citing the old Magna Carta and reviewing various limitations on the king. Charles dismissed the Parliament and called none to meet for 11 years. A long civil war followed (the English Revolution, 1640-1688), with the king holding out in Oxford and the Parliament controlling London. Oliver Cromwell emerged as a military organizer, who picked religious enthusiasm as a rallying agent (Puritans), formed the "Ironsides" as a democratic military unit, beheaded Charles after a "trial" by a Rump Commons, suppressed an Irish Catholic insurrection, chastised Scotland again at the battle of Dunbar (1650) and then took to sea, trouncing the Dutch navy and making the English fleet supreme. Cromwell's Puritan supporters, who often wore short hair, were derisively called "Round-heads" in distinction to the wigged Cavaliers, supporters of the king. Commercially England was far behind the Dutch, but it soon became clear that only the English could possibly challenge them. More war with Spain followed and the Spanish fleet was again destroyed. At Cromwell's death in 1658 his republicanism came to an end and the son of Charles I, Charles II, was brought back to the throne, restoring the Stuart Monarchy. Under Cromwell the simple citizen profited little, although the merchant princes prospered from the wars. Rule by army and naked force, even coated by the religious cant of Puritanism, was still offensive and at the end Cromwell's regime was hated perhaps more than any that had gone before.

A few details about the Puritan faith seems appropriate at this time. Durant (Ref. 98) says:

"Perhaps only among the Jews did religion play so pervasive a role in everyday life as among the Puritans; and indeed Puritanism agreed with Judaism in almost everything except the divinity of Christ."

The chief object of life was to escape the fires of hell and the machinations of the Devil. Only a few were destined by God for salvation. They attempted to legislate morality, establishing fasting days, the "blue" Sunday still with us to some extent today, made adultery a capital crime and oaths a severe misdemeanor. Some say that while the Puritan regimen narrowed the mind, it strengthened the will and the character and helped to prepare Englishmen for self rule. An offshoot of the Puritan faith is found in the Quakers, founded by George Fox. Their basic faith was obscured for a time with fantasies and bigotry. They distinguished themselves by allowing no ornaments on their clothing, ref using to remove their hats for any reason whatsoever and by addressing all persons by "thou" and "thee". They were very intemperate in their denunciation of other sects. Pagels (Ref. 99) writes that George Fox, although probably unaware of it, carried on the old Gnostic tradition (see pages 320 and 339), with analogous interpretations of religious experience.

Under Charles II, military and naval power declined and the Dutch navy regained supremacy on the seas. In England, however, there burst out pent-up intellectual energy. We must list such names as Robert Boyle for his work in chemistry, Robert Hooke, the perfecter of the microscope, Halley the great astronomer, Christopher Wren, geometer, astronomer and architect and William Harvey, former student at Padua, who described the circulation of the blood in man. But above all, we must mention Sir Isaac Newton, who, using Galileo's and Kepler’s work, formulated the laws of gravity. Newton developed the calculus and the binomial theorem and used his mathematics in physics and astronomy. His work had far flung consequences, even giving rise in the religious field to Deism. The king conferred an official charter upon the Royal Society of London for improving natural knowledge, in 1662. Most of the men just mentioned, along with some poets like Dryden and Waller, were members. The poet John Milton is said to have introduced more than 600 words into the English language, all derived from the Latin, Greek or Hebrew. (Ref. 100)

The English common man of this time was a coarse, rough, profane individual. When prisoners were hanged, drawn and quartered, their heads were parboiled first with Bay salt and cumin seed, to keep them from putrefaction while on public exhibition and to keep the birds from seizing them. (Ref. 101) Most roads in England were nearly impassable. Carts usually moved at about two miles an hour and were often held up for days by high water. The various parts of England were essentially cut off from each other and that was a factor in making the inns of that day so important and so different from those of today. The inn was a hub of commercial activity. For example, in 1686 Salisbury in Wiltshire, then a small town, could accommodate 548 travelers and 865 horses in its inns. (Ref. 102) Most of London in-city transportation was by boat on the Thames, as the streets were narrow and covered with garbage and filth, crowds of people and deep ruts, which made carriage rides hazardous. There were abnormally cold winters in this century and Londoners held all the festivities of Carnival (Christmas to after Twelfth Night) on the frozen Thames. In early 1683, however, huge ice floes at the mouth of the river froze in ships, so that food and goods ran short and prices quadrupled. But city life took refuge on the frozen river and even huge markets were held. It was a violent city with murders common and frequent hangings and the inevitable drawings and quarterings. Although the richest city in Europe, as late as 1660 London was so short of food that 1/5 of the people who were buried in even prosperous parishes had died of starvation. (Ref. 103) But the nobility continued to live extravagantly. It is said that when Henry Berkeley, Lord Lieutenant of Gloucestershire, went to London he took 150 servants with him. Business in the city was run by fewer than 200 merchants. (Ref. 104)

The population of England and Wales in 1660 has been given at about 5,000,000 and it probably increased to 5,500,000 by 1700. Five-sevenths of the people lived in the towns with 1 out of every 10 Englishmen living in London, with its 750,000 people. Of about 800 market towns in England and Wales, at least 300 were for single trades: 133 for grain; 26 for malt; 6 for fruit; 92 for cattle; 32 for sheep, with others for horses, swine, fishy poultry, dairy products, leather, linen and whatnot. Livestock could be driven to market, sheep much farther (up to 70 miles) than cattle, while grain was carried overland no more than 5 to 10 miles. Leadenhall may have been the largest wholesale market in Europe after about 1666, when 100 stalls sold beef and another 140 were reserved for other meats, not even including fish. (Ref. 105) Child labor was the rule and people were proud to say that any child of 5 years could make his own way. Beer was cheap and everyone drank it, even children, as it was easier to find than decent water. Coffee came in from Turkey about 1650 and tea came from China about the same time. Household staples were dear and the price of grain rose 500% between 1500 and 1700. The historian Nussbaum has stated that a Gregory King estimated in 1696 that 1/4 of the English people were dependent upon alms and that money collected for poor relief equaled 1/4 of the whole export trade. Air pollution was already a problem because of the immoderate use of coal. (Ref. 106)

A very severe epidemic of plague broke out in 1665, with 70,000 Londoners dying of the disease. Tobacco was widely considered to be prophylactic against the plague and even children were encouraged to smoke. (Ref. 107) In 1666 a fire burned for three days, destroying most of London north of the Thames. 200,000 people lost their homes, as 2/3 of the City went up in flames. After this disaster, though, the Corporation of London organized a fire department, fireplugs were placed in the main water pipes, streets were made wider and straighter and sanitation was improved. (Ref. 108) The fire had also destroyed rats, fleas and germs and f or this or perhaps some unknown reason, plague soon disappeared and it was 253 years before native cases of the infection again caused death in England. As a matter of fact, from this time on plague left all of northwestern Europe, although it remained active in the eastern Mediterranean and in Russia. Although quarantine and other public health measures may have helped some, probably the chief reasons lay elsewhere. Wood shortages had resulted in more stone and brick houses4 and thatch roofs, which were homes of rats, had given way to tile and the gray rat had pretty well replaced the carrier black rat. The former did not climb as much and preferred to burrow in the ground rather than live in roofs and house walls. Perhaps also there was some transition in the Pasteurella organism itself, perhaps mutation to the milder Pasteurella pseudo-tuberculosis. (Ref. 109)

It will be noted that no credit has been given the medical profession for the disappearance of the plague. Nevertheless, some progress in this field continued to be made. Thomas Sydenham was a great clinical physician who recognized that each major disease had many varieties. Thomas Willis contributed the De Anatome Cerebi, a thorough study of the nervous system. A circle of arteries at the base of the brain and the 11th cranial nerve still bear his name. The Royal Society, with physicians as the major component, was formed in this century and still exists today. The battle between apothecaries and physicians over the practice of medicine was bitter. (Ref. 111) As the power of plague ebbed, that of typhus fever rose. That infection had first been described in 1643 by Willis, but it did not become a major problem in this century. Measles, in both the 1 6th and 17th centuries appears to have been closely associated with small-pox. A severe epidemic occurred in 1674, causing the extreme degree of contagion of the disease to be recognized. (Ref. 112)

But we must return to the governmental scene. When James II, another devout Catholic, reached the English throne in 1685, he brought back to focus the old "King or Parliament" issue and the latter, continuing the revolt, promptly dethroned him, thus expelling the last Catholic king from the British Isles. After some intrigue, Parliament allowed William of Orange, the great Dutch leader, to arrive with an army and take over the English throne nearly bloodlessly. His royal claim was through his wife, Mary, sister of James, although a Protestant. William, a persistent hater of the French, as we have seen, and Mary made alliances with various European powers in an attempt to curtail the powers of France. Louis XIV was William's sole target. He had taken the English throne to acquire the wealth and land and sea forces to wage a European war. (Ref. 113) He was not interested in the domestic affairs of England and left those problems to ministers, the most influential of which was George Savile, Marquis of Halifax. John Churchill, Earl of Marlborough, was virtually commander-in-chief of armies, leading 8,000 men against the French in Flanders. Later Churchill was dismissed because of royal family intrigues, regaining the king's confidence again only at the end of the century. William just barely lasted out the century, dying in 1702. He was father-less, childless, asthmatic, had a tubercular lung, was partly crippled, lived with a loveless wife (Ref. 114) and was considered a homosexual by most historians. (Ref. 115) During his reign, in spite of an expanding economy, there were constant political battles between landowning Tories (From "Tory", an Irish word for robber) and the money making Whigs (apparently a shortened form of Whiggamore, a band of Scots active in 1648 against Charles I). (Ref. 116) There were also battles between the English and the Scots and with William 's supporters and those who would assassinate him and restore James on the throne. In 1692 an army of 10,000 desperate Irishmen and 10,000 French regulars assembled around Cherbourg, ready to attack England and restore the Catholic James to the English throne. The subsequent invasion fleet was destroyed by the British navy's Admiral Russell, formerly a James backer. On land William's armies were not so successful, with the war finally grinding down to a truce in the Treaty of Ryswick in 1696.

In spite of everything there was some grace and beauty in England. After the Great Fire, Sir Christopher Wren erected 52 new parish churches, most of which stand today. On the economic scene, the Bank of England was formed in 1694 to consolidate some older firms and to get on an even footing with Amsterdam. (Ref. 117) The progressively increasing coal production, particularly at Newcastle, slowly modernized England as this fuel was used in such industries as salt manufacture from sea water, sheet glass, bricks and tile production, sugar refining, bakeries and breweries. We have mentioned before that throughout history people have tended to resist technological progress. This was even true when the first stagecoach went from Manchester to London in a day in 1669 – it would be the end of the noble art of horsemanship, it would ruin saddle and spur manufacturers and Thames boatmen. (Ref. 118) In 1675 10,000 silk-workers of London rose up against the introduction of French ribbon-looms, with which a single worker could weave 10 to 12 ribbons at a time. Soldiers had to be called in when the new machines were burned. But business activity continued anyway. By 1695 the Royal Exchange was handling transactions in public stocks and shares in the Indies and the Bank of England. (Ref. 119) (Continue on page 970)

SCOTLAND

Scotland continued as a Protestant stronghold under the common monarchy with England, with Scotland now supplying the Royal House of Stuart for most of the century. On the death of Elizabeth, James VI of Scotland had become James I of England. This was not to say that all was peace and harmony between the two countries, for the Scots were shocked by the execution of Charles I and they were almost immediately to claim the son, Charles II, then exiled in the Netherlands, to be the rightful king of the two nations. This declaration of Charles II as king was made by the Scottish "Covenanters", a group formed to protect Scotland against "popish" practices of the preceding monarch. (Ref. 120) When the new Charles landed in Scotland, professing to support Presbyterianism, he started immediately for the English border, but he was met and defeated by an army led by Cromwell himself. The ultimate result was suppression of this Scottish "revolution" and the country was again subject to England, its separate Parliament dissolved, although it was allowed to send 30 delegates to the London Parliament. Scotland waited and prayed for the Stuart restoration, which came in 1660 with Cromwell's death and finally the ascension of Charles II on the English throne.

Unfortunately, Charles II still had a great tendency to Catholicism and when upon his death his Catholic brother took the throne as James II of England (James VII of Scotland) he immediately started removing Protestants from office, suspended all laws against Catholics and punished ministers who preached against Rome. When the revolution to depose James was started in England it was seconded in Scotland, as bands harried the Jesuits, destroyed the Holyroodhouse printing press and sacked the Chapel Royal. But when William of Orange took over the English throne, he was not immediately accepted by the Scots and in traditional fashion the clans squared off - some for James and some for William - and fought, killed and robbed each other for months. Episcopalians were soon as much the victims as Catholics, as Presbyterianism finally began to triumph. Rob Roy, son-in-law of Gregor Macgregor, became chief of the Macgregor clan in 1693, controlling lands from Loch Lomond to the Braes of Balquihidder. (Ref. 121, 122 (Continue on page 976)

IRELAND

At the end of this section in the last chapter we described the encirclement of 4,000 Spanish troops sent to help the Irish in their rebellion. In the final battle of 1601 the Irish and Spanish lost to the English Lord Mountjoy. The Irish O'Neill with 100 other chieftains and a thousand followers then went into exile on the continent. James and Charles I of England continued the oppression of Ireland, crushing rebellion af ter rebellion and giving land progressively to Protestants at the expense of Catholics. It even became illegal for Catholics to buy land, although most of the Irish remained with their faith, anyway. Caught up in the religious and civil wars of England, in 1641 the Ulster Irish rose, scattering thousands of colonists. In 1646 Irish Catholics beat the English at Blackwater River, but victory was short lived. After Oliver Cromwell defeated and beheaded Charles I, he came to Ireland to get revenge and forever settle the "Irish Question". He smashed Catholic Ireland and its people with massacres. 30,000 lrish hurriedly left for the continent and Ireland lost a quarter of its population. Within 50 years Catholic Ireland was largely owned by wealthy, often absent Protestant English. (Ref. 123)

Later, when James II fled England he went to Ireland, enlisted a Catholic army and attempted to retrieve his throne, but was beaten at the battle of the Boyne in 1690.

Although the resulting treaty yielded the Catholics some land and rights, neither the English nor the Irish Protestant Parliaments would ratify it and the oppression continued. All the inhumanity that was to be visited by Catholics upon the Protestants of France in 1680-1690 had been visited by Protestants upon the Catholics of Ireland, particularly from 1650 to 1660. Those bitter years remain in Irish memory as an undying heritage of hate.

Peasants of Ireland were of ten close to f amine. They bled cows, boiled the blood with some milk and butter and herbs, making a savory blood pudding, a version of which is still known in County Cork and elsewhere. In Tyrone and Derry, the coagulated blood was salted and preserved for use at other times of the year. (Ref. 124) Fortunately for the Irish, one quarter acre of land will yield 20 hundredweight of potatoes and this, with a few pigs, could just sustain a family. (Ref. 125)

The battle of the Boyne was actually not the last gasp for Catholic Ireland. Patrick Sarsfield defended Limerick until a great battle at Aughrim (1691) where William and Mary's Dutch General Ginkel defeated a French General St. Ruth and the Irish. Sarsfield then led some 14,000 troops to the continent to try to continue to fight on against England along with French troops. (Ref. 126) That Irish brigade subsequently played a prominent role in French military history. (Ref. 127) (Continue on page 977)

SCANDINAVIA

NORWAY

Many factors allowed the continuation of dominance of Denmark over the geographically larger Norway. Denmark had a much larger population, a much larger capital and much more productive land. Only 5% of Norway is cultivable, while 75% of Denmark is so. The tide of Renaissance splendor which washed in over Denmark never reached as far north as Norway. The country was just basically poor. There was fishing, timber and some farming, but the roads were terrible and the country thinly populated. In the pre-railroad centuries, all of Denmark's military forces could be assembled at any point in a few days, whereas it took weeks or months to bring Norwegians together from scores of separated valleys and fjords. (Ref. 128) Norway stagnated under Danish rule and the only redeeming monarch was Christian IV (1588-1648) who made an honest effort to give the Norwegians a better position. He developed mining, instituted new civil and religious laws and developed Norwegian trading companies. He founded Oslo, naming it "Christiana". In his endless wars with Sweden, however, several Norwegian provinces were given away and Norway's population fell to about 480,000.

The Reformation was manipulated by Denmark to the great detriment of Norway in that Protestantism was forced on her as a means of subjugation. (Ref. 129) Danish language Bibles and hymnals were also forced, doing much to establish a common Dano-Norwegian language. This is still one of the languages of Norway, called "Riksmal", in contrast to the now revived native language "Landsmal". Before Christian IV, the Hansa merchants had established themselves in Bergen and were a parasitic growth on the whole economy. One of the most famous Danish Navy heroes, elevated to nobility under the name of Tordenskjold, was born Peder Wessel, in Trondheim, Norway. (Continue on page 978)

SWEDEN (Beginning Sweden's Age of Power; the Struggle for the Baltic)

Sweden, proper, goes 1,000 miles north from its southern tip and has 96,000 lakes, but in this 17th century it had only 1,500,000 people. Iron was its chief export, making more that 1/2 the total, with silver and copper being next. (Ref. 130) In about 1625 Flemish techniques of blast furnace construction and metal casting were imported, allowing the casting of excellent iron guns, so that soon Sweden dominated the international cannon market. This boom had been initiated in 1620 when Louis de Geer, a native of Liege, had sent Walloon ironworkers to this Scandinavian country. (Ref. 131) The blast furnaces were financed with money from both Holland and England. (Ref. 132)

The century opened with the youngest son of Gustavus I as first regent and then King Karl (Charles) IX of Sweden. He established Lutheranism as the state church and then because of claims of the Polish Sigismund to the Swedish throne, he invaded Livonia, beginning the long Polish-Swedish Wars. King Gustavus Adolphus (1611-1632), "Lion of the North", made Sweden briefly the greatest military power in Europe. Axel Oxenstierna, his chancellor, helped the nation grow in industry, trade and scholarship. Sweden entered the Thirty Years War in 1630 "to save the Protestant cause" in Germany, but in so doing, virtually conquered most of that country. Adolphus went as far as the Danube but then was killed at age 38, while leading a cavalry charge. His daughter Christina at 6 years of age became queen, but she became an eccentric woman and poor ruler, who at 28 years of age pleaded illness and abdicated to go to Rome, where she announced her Catholicism and became a patroness of the arts and the lover of Cardinal Azzolini. Christina was followed on the throne by her cousin Karl (Charles X, Gustavus), son of John Casimir, count palatine of Zweibrucken, who had had military experience in the Thirty Years War under Torstensson and Chancellor Oxenstierna. He had frank expansionist aims and reopened war with Poland, took Riga and transplanted its iron and steel industry to Sweden, laying the foundations of an even stronger industrial basis for his martial policies. (Ref. 133)

After the Treaty of Westphalia in 1648 Sweden, at the peak of its imperial power and "Mistress of the North", completely encircled the Gulf of Bosnia and the Gulf of Finland, controlled Finland, Karelia, Ingria, Estonia and Livonia, most of the Baltic Islands and had two large beach-heads on the north German shore. The first of these was at the mouth of the Oder River, with Stettin, Stralsund and Wismar and reaching to within about 30 miles of Berlin and secondly the Duchy of Holstei-n-Gottorp on the west side of the base of the Danish peninsula. Needing money during the Thirty Years War, the Swedes had cut down vast forest areas in Pomerania, with the result that subsequently many of these areas were invaded by sand dunes. (Ref. 134)

It may have been that frequent harvest failures from cold may have, in part, stimulated the swings of the Swedish kings into Germany and Poland. (Ref. 135) At any rate, Karl X Gustavus found it easy to invade Poland, but difficult to subdue it. When Frederick William of Brandenburg tried to steal West Prussia, while Poland was under duress, Karl turned on him and forced the Treaty of Konigsberg, which gave East Prussia to Sweden. Finally, when the Catholic powers on the continent rose up against him, he turned his forces against Denmark with his army crossing the ice of the frozen Kattegut (1658). Only a valiant defense of Copenhagen saved the Danish throne. Although the open sea in the center of the Baltic did not freeze in winter, the shore line and the northern ½ of the Gulf of Bosnia did freeze from November until early May, shutting down all merchant shipping and in some years, as in that just mentioned, even the Kattegut froze solid. Finally, Karl Gustavus was defeated on the sea by the combined efforts of England and Holland, who wanted no nation to exclusively control access to the Baltic.

Karl (Charles) XI (1660-1697) was not as successful militarily as his predecessors. He was defeated in 1675 in the battle of Fehrbellin by the Great Elector of Brandenburg-Prussia, but later by treaty and through the help of Sweden's new ally, France, he was able to recover Swedish Pomeria. (Ref. 136) At home, however, Karl XI was determined to reduce the power of the aristocracy and one way was to demand the return to the crown of various lands previously given to the nobles, a measure which brought much disfavor to him, not only at home but in the possessions south of the Baltic. When he died in 1698 of cancer of the stomach, he was succeeded by his 15 year old son, Karl (Charles) XII, a frail boy, slender and wiry, but already a superb horseman, hunter and avid student of military science. He did not care for the Swedish language and spoke and wrote it poorly, but used German, which was the court language of all the northern kingdoms. He also had a knowledge of Latin and French and was a student of the campaigns of Caesar, Gustavus Adolphus and particularly of Alexander the Great. Even at his young age he ref used to have a regent and crowned himself king immediately and took over the reign. He participated in dangerous sports such as fighting a bear using only a wooden pitchfork, etc. and played at war as did his contemporary, Peter of Russia. (Ref. 137) (Continue on page 978)

DENMARK

Although Denmark had a king the actual power was in the hands of noblemen who lived well, although not on the scale of other European countries. In large areas of the nation the old Danish "free" peasants had fallen into a dependent state, roads were poor and heather began to take over fields, because farmers did not know how to control it. (Ref. 138) Even then, the Danes were able to send some 80,000 head of cattle to Germany each year.

The most renowned Danish king, Christian IV, was crowned in 1596 and in spite of continued war with Sweden, he was a builder, constructing Europe's largest naval arsenal at Copenhagen and also a new Stock Exchange. He got into a disagreement with the great Tyco Brahe, living on an island in the sound by previous royal decree and Brahe went to Prague where he soon died. During Christian IV's reign, Copenhagen doubled in size. He made the sad mistake of entering the Thirty Years War on the side of the Protestants and after being defeated by Tilly he retreated, only to have the German troops move up and ravage Jutland. Just a few years later, the Swedish troops also came up from Germany into Jutland and then down from Sweden into Scania, thoroughly defeating the Danes.

At the Treaty of Broemsebra in 1645 Denmark lost the island of Gotland as well as Scania, across the sound. Between 1650 and 1660 Denmark lost more than 20% of its population from disease and starvation. (Ref. 139) The wars were continued later in the century when Sweden also tried to take control of Norway. At one point Sweden hired Scots mercenaries to attack the Norwegians, but the peasants rallied and killed most of them. All in all, as Sweden's star rose over Europe, Denmark's began to fall. (Continued on page 981)

FINLAND

Although a part of Sweden, the Finns maintained their own language and way of life. At the beginning of this 17th century Finland was made a Grand Duchy of Sweden and given orders of nobility. Their land served as a battle ground for the later Swedish-Russian wars for control of the Baltic. After a temporary peace with Russia in 1617, Gustavus Adolphus inaugurated the first Finnish Diet, with representatives from the new nobility, the clergy, the town dwellers (burghers) and the peasants. Peasant sailors were small traders, operating between Helsinki and Revel, across -the gulf. (Ref. 140) The University of Turko was founded in this period. Illustrating that the bad side of Europe was the East, however, was the Finnish famine of 1696-7 when perhaps 1/3 of the population died. That was said to be one of the most terrible events of European history. (Ref. 141) (Continue on page 982)

EASTERN EUROPE

While peasants of western Europe were freeing themselves gradually from serfdom (with the exception of Spain), feudal power grew and spread in eastern Europe, until the peasant state became almost slavery. Free peasants survived only in newly conquered lands where they substituted military service for rent. But eastern Europe's wheat and rye was in great demand in western Europe, some of ten going even to Portugal, Spain and Italy. (Continue on page 983)

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

As the century unfolded the great struggle for the Baltic continued with Sweden, Russia, Poland, Brandenburg and Denmark all being eager participants. From the Neva Delta southwest, the states lining the Baltic south shore were Ingria (Ingermanland), Estonia, Duchy of Courland, Lithuania, Prussia, Pomerania, Polish corridor to Danzig and Brandenburg. Livonia was now under Polish control, but the Livonian nobility were descendants of the Teutonic Knights and they were not at all happy with the Polish imposed Catholicism, so that late in the century (1660) they had no difficulty becoming aligned with Luthern Sweden. But Livonia, like all the southern Baltic countries, experienced almost a hundred years of being overrun by various armies, with shif ting borders with every treaty. Johann Reinhold von Patkul, of old Livonian nobility - a cultured, experienced military officer spoke to Charles XI of Sweden about his "reduction" policy (the policy of returning nobles’ lands to the crown of Sweden, as mentioned under SWEDEN, above), as Livonia had supposedly been guaranteed against such, but he not only got no relief but was later sought by Swedish officers for arrest. He eluded them and helped a little later to form the alliance which challenged Sweden in the Great Northern War. Thus, in the end when Sweden controlled almost all, the other concerned powers had already entered into an alliance to dismember Sweden by war. We shall have a special feature section on this Great Northern War which actually began in 1700, at the end of this section on Eastern Europe.

Poland deserves further consideration. While a giant in size, it was the weakest and most vulnerable of all the European states. It had a population of about 8,000,000 (France had over 16,000,000), but it was poor politically and militarily and it became a battle ground for invading foreign armies. The causes of Poland's impotence were several. First, there was no real racial or religious cohesion - 1/2 the people were true Poles and were Catholic, but the other half were Orthodox Lithuanians and Russians, Jews and Luthern Germans. In addition the Cossacks obeyed only their Ukranian "Hetman" and refused all orders from the Polish king. To continue, the political situation was bad. Poland was a republic with a king who was elective and who had only that power given him by feuding nobility. The true rulers were the great Polish and Lithuanian lords and among the latter the Sapieha family defied all kings of Poland. Furthermore, neither king nor Diet had any machinery for tax collection. The army, although with individually brave men, had no discipline and the lords might withdraw their own contingents for any reason, at any time. (Ref. 142) At times, particularly early in the century, the Poles tried to be aggressive, but in the end they always seemed to be on the short end of the stick. With these generalities in mind, we shall give a little more political detail.

Upon the death of Bathory at the end of the previous century, the Polish Diet bargained for a year before finally giving the throne to Sigismund III, who, as heir to the Swedish crown, might unite the two countries and control the Baltic, checking Russia. Half of his reign was devoted to this vain struggle. The sudden death of Boris Godunov in Russia, gave Sigismund another idea of also ruling Moscovy. He marched into Russia with an army, took Smolensk and even entered Moscow for a short time (1611-1612), retreated and later again marched on that city but was unable to reach it in the Russian winter. The only result of all this was the possession of Smolensk and Severski and a strong infusion of Polish influence into Russian life. (Ref. 143) The rest of Sigismund's reign was a succession of other disastrous wars, including an expensive struggle with the Turks, during which time the Swedish king took advantage of his preoccupation to invade Livonia. Upon his death in 1632 the Diet gave the crown to his son Ladislas IV, a fine general and an enlightened man who encouraged debate on religion an~ promoted art and music. He died in 1648 just as a great Cossack Revolt threatened the existence of the Polish state. (Ref. 144)

The Cossack Revolt, resulting from a complex set of dissatisfactions, including interference with their Orthodox worship, was first led by Bogdan Chmielnicki and supported by the Moslem Tatars of the Crimea. As the Polish Diet selected the Jesuit John II Casimir as ruler, Chmielnicki cast his lot with Orthodox Russia and offered the Ukraine to Czar Alexis. Russia accepted, knowing that it meant war with Poland. But the Crimean Tatars preferred a Polish to a Russian Ukraine and they shifted their support back to Poland. As the war raged, the Swedish king slipped in and conquered Warsaw. But the Swedes became over-enthusiastic, plundered the country, despoiled the churches, etc, until the populace united and pushed them back. Karl (Charles) X, the Swedish king, died and that part of the Polish war ceased. The Russian involvement came to an end in 1667 with Smolensk, Kiev and the eastern part of the Ukraine ceded to Russia. A terrible side effect of the Cossack Revolt was the accompanying ferocious massacres of the Polish Jews, who had served as stewards and tax gatherers for the Polish and Lithuanian estates. Early in the century 40% to 50% of all trade in Poland was handled by itinerant Jews5, but later they were butchered without mercy and thousands of infants were thrown into wells or buried alive. (Ref. 145, 146) In the town of Polonnoye alone perhaps 10,000 Jews were killed by Cossacks or taken prisoner by Tatars. Altogether in the 10 years of 1648 to 1658 it is estimated that nearly 35,000 Jews were killed in Poland, Lithuania and Russia. This began their massive migration to western Europe and America, resulting in a completely new distribution of the Jewish population.

Poland continued the disastrous war with the Turks and the latter soon gained sovereignty over the western Ukraine. Jan Sobieski, a general of that war, was elected king to become Poland's greatest sovereign. He launched further campaigns against the Turks, wresting the western Ukraine away from them again and finally defeated them in their last siege of Vienna. As a help in this last war, Sobieski signed a treaty with Vasily Golitsyn, prime minister of Russia and incidentally the regent Sophia's lover, by which Russia attacked the Crimean Tartar vassals of the Ottomans. In exchange, Poland again ceded Kiev to Russia. (Ref. 148) At home Sobieski, although he tried, could not improve the conditions of the peasants, for their masters dominated the Sejm (parliamentary body); he could not compel the rich to pay taxes for the wealthy were the Sejm; he could not keep the factious nobles in order, for they refused him a standing army. (Ref. 149) The Turkish domination of the Balkans had cut off the southern trade routes from Poland and this, along with the rise of a class of great landlords, lessened the prosperity of - Poland's commercial centers and prevented the development of a Polish middle class. The nobles, who owned serfs, sent a regular river of grain from their estates down the Vistula to Gdansk. (Ref. 150)

Upon King Sobieski's death, in spite of the Sejm's decision to accept Louis XIV's choice of Prince de Conti, Augustus of Saxony simply marched in with a Saxon army and took over as king. As he changed his religion to Catholicism, it was soon apparent that he was shrewd, deceitful and, in modern terminology, a real "double dealer". At the end of the century in 1700, this section of Europe was wrapped up in the Great Northern War, with Karl (Charles) XII of Sweden defeating Russia's army at Narva, Livonia. But Karl did not pursue, probably because of fever, dysentery and hunger in his army. His horses were eating bark, because of a "scorched earth" policy of the retreating Russians. By the spring of 1700 only 1/2 of Karl's troops were fit for action. (Ref. 151) (Continue on page 983)

RUSSIA (See Map in RUSSIA section, 19th century)

In the last chapter we left Russia with Boris Godunov on the throne. He immediately had several problems. First of all he was not of royal descent and this aroused the old boyar families - the Golitsyns, Shuiskys, Romanovs and others. Next, crop failures between 1601 and 1603 caused catastrophic famines and finally there were rumors that Boris had actually been involved in the assassination of the "rightful heir", the infant Dimitri. In 1604 a motley army of mercenaries from Poland, including restless Cossacks and disgruntled peasants, marched on Moscow and in the middle of this uprising Boris died and was replaced by his son Theodore. The advancing army had the "False Dimitri" with them and through intrigues with Jesuits and Polish-Lithuanians and various opponents of Theodore, the "False Dimitri" was set up as Czar, taking a Polish girl as his wif e. Polish-Lithuanian influence suddenly became very predominant. When it was discovered that the Czar's wife was Catholic, however, a popular uprising resulted in Dimitri's death and the appointment of Vasili Shuisky as the new ruler.

Violence from political, social and religious elements continued to be present. Led by I.I. Bolotnikov, a former serf, many landless Cossacks and poor peasants formed a mass movement against not only Shuisky, but all nobles. Although Bolotnikov was killed in the first battle with the forces from Moscow, the rebellion continued, again also involving forces from Poland and Lithuania. Helped by local dissidents Polish forces actually occupied Moscow in 1611 and 1612. Prince Dimitri Pozharsky, after getting an agreement with the disgruntled Cossacks, entered Moscow with his own forces in October 1612 and forced the Poles to surrender. (Ref. 152)

In 1613 the National Assembly elected Michael Romanov as Czar, starting a new dynasty. Michael was the son of a patriarch Filaret and he re-established the autocracy and the service nobility as rulers of the Russian state. Under Michael peace was obtained with Sweden in the Treaty of Stolbovo in 1618, with Novgorod going to Russia, but other towns in that area to Sweden. All of the first Romanovs sought to exclude foreign influence. Thus, while foreigners were needed as drillmasters, armament makers, merchant contact for furs, etc., they were all enclosed in special ghettos in Moscow and were treated with general suspicion as dangerous heretics. There was a new formulation of law, but actually it merely codified existing laws based on medieval absolutism and orthodoxy. Thus it was a criminal offense to look at a new moon, play chess or not attend church during Lent. As we have noted in the section above, in 1648 the Ukranians and Cossacks revolted against their Polish rulers for both social and religious reasons and, gaining independence, put themselves under Moscow's protection. It should be noted that at this time Russia's commercial ties were still chiefly with the East and there was no real sense of property, industry or individual enterprise. (Ref. 153)

In this century Moscow was a rich and beautiful city, as large as London. Hundreds of gold domes topped with golden crosses dotted the sky-line, as there were 1,600 churches in the city. Red square was a brawling, open-air market place. Most of the city was of wood, however, and there were great fires in 1611, 1626, and 1671. Even the streets were wooden planks to keep people out of the mud in the spring thaw, although this attempt was often unsuccessful. At noon all Moscovites stopped for a large meal and then a 2 or 3 hours nap. At night few were on the streets but thieves and cutthroats. The Kremlin was on a hill 125 feet above the Moscow River, with walls 12 to 16 feet thick, rising some 65 feet above the surrounding rivers and moat. The whole fortress area included 69 acres.

In 1636 there were more than 40,000 houses in Moscow, but one must not get the idea that Russia was an urban society. In 1630 only 2.5% of the people lived in towns and this had increased only to 3% well into the next century. (Ref. 154) The Nenets continued to be the chief inhabitants of Arctic Russia, spreading to all the peninsulae of the Kara and Barents seas. (Ref. 155) For 300 to 400 miles north of the Black Sea there was a "no-man's land" between the Ukranian Cossacks to the north and the Black Sea itself and this was the hunting ground of the Crimean Tartars, remnants of the old Mongol conquerors and now vassals of the Ottoman Turks. Sometimes these Tartars raided north, taking thousands of Russians as slaves for the Ottoman slave markets.

In the third quarter of the century the Czar was Alexis Mikhailovich, considered a demigod, almost inaccessible to his people but called the "father of Russia", while the earth was "mother". Even when only 16 years of age he had been called the "young monk" and he spent most of every day praying and working. On fast days he frequented midnight prayers, prostrating himself on the ground as many as 1,000 to 1,500 times. He often ate only 3 meals a week. Near the end of his reign there were about 8,000,000 Russians, only a fraction of which lived in the larger towns. Most were scattered in villages in forest clearings or along the rivers. May Day, still celebrated by the communists, was an ancient holiday of rebirth and fertility after the long, frozen winter.

Czar Alexis' first wife, Marie Miloslavsky, died bearing her 14th child, but those that survived were sickly and only 2 lived to rule. Alexis then married Natalya Naryshkina, raised by his chief minister and friend, Artemon Mateev, but whose real father was a Tartar. The bride, through her upbringing in the educated Mateev's home, introduced many western ways into Czar Alexis' previously monastic life. Their "Camp David" was an immense wooden building at Preobrazhenskoe of jumbled architecture. A separate three story building with two peaked towers served for their young son Peter and his half-brother, Ivan. The palace had baths for family and servants while its elaborate contemporary at Versailles in France had none. Alexis died at 47 years, apparently of a respiratory ailment and his invalid son Fedor (by his first wife) became Czar. His legs were so swollen that he had to be carried to his coronation at age 15. His mother's family, the Miloslavskys, had Alexis’ minister and Natalya's surrogate father (Mateev) arrested, stripped of property and sent as a state prisoner to Pustozersk, a remote town north of the Arctic circle - such has always been and remains the custom for change of political power in Russia’ Peter and his mother remained secluded in the Kremlin.

Fedor, with a scurvy-like disease, mild-mannered and relatively intelligent, of ten had to rule giant Russia lying on his back and he lived only 6 more years. But he did one great thing by abolishing a medieval system of precedence which had burdened the administrative system with boyars (nobles) of inadequacy and allowed-henceforth offices and power to be distributed on a basis of merit, not birth. At Fedor's death, his brother Ivan would normally have been the next czar, but he was lame, nearly blind and spoke with difficulty so the throne was given to Peter, 10 years old, with the idea that Mateev, recently removed from exile, would be his advisor, although his mother Natalya would be regent.

In the middle of the century, even though Russia had tried valiantly to remain isolated from Lutheran Sweden, Catholic Poland and the Islamic Turks and Tatars, foreigners and their more modern ideas had begun to f ilter into Russia so that even the church began to doubt itself, resulting in a Great Schism, as in the Catholic World long before. Alexis' patriarch, the iron-willed Nikon was a reformist, trying to get the wandering Russian liturgy and church ritual back to the classical Greek Orthodoxy. Arch priest Avvakum, a fanatical fundamentalist, became the leader of the "old Believers" - many common people who had migrated to the Urals and forests and established remote villages. Avvakum, originally Nikon's friend, was banned to Tobolsk in Siberia in 1653, but by writing and lectures he remained a leader of the Schismatics. Nikon continued as a stern enforcer of discipline on laity and clergy alike, banning Cursing, card playing, sexual promiscuity and drinking. Eventually he assumed powers which seemed to exceed the czar 's and was brought to heel by the four Orthodox patriarchs of Jerusalem, Constantinople, Antioch and Alexandria. Nikon then condemned himself to exile but the turmoil did not end and soon there was a full scale rebellion. After Fedor became czar, Avvakum wrote to him saying that his father Alexis was in hell, suffering terrible torments because he had originally backed Nikon. Fedor had the old patriarch burned at the stake, but as a martyr he inspired 20,000 old Believers to burn themselves to death in the next 6 years (1684-1690). The Schism almost destroyed the Russian Church.

It is appropriate to remark here that Russian women were considered silly, intellectually void, morally irresponsible and potentially evil and promiscuous from childhood on. As wives they could be legally and religiously beaten or divorced by forced entrance into a convent, where they were essentially considered "dead". Any Russian man could thus have two "divorces" but had to keep the third wife. For the men of that time the chief problem was drunkenness and in the lower classes the women joined them in drunken, free-love carousing until all fell asleep in an alcoholic stupor, night after night. Sisters and daughters of the czar were different than other women and could never marry Russians beneath their rank (and there were none other) and their religion prevented marriage with foreigners, considered heretics. They spent their time in prayer, embroidery, gossip and boredom, in what was called the terem.

Almost immediately after the crowning of Peter as czar, his half-sister Sofia Miloslavsky instigated a terrible revolt of the Streltsy, a professional police-army originally formed by Ivan the Terrible and consisting of 22 regiments of 1,000 men each and whose officers had become rich through "moon-lighting" and paying no taxes. Fed by untrue rumors of the poisoning of Fedor and plotting to kill Sophia's brother Ivan, they stormed the Kremlin and in a bloody and terrible massacre dismembered and killed most of the boyars as well as Mateev and finally, after torturing Natayla's brother, demanded the crowning of young Ivan as co-czar, with Sophia serving as regent. In that way she succeeded in ruling Russia for the next 7 years. The impact of all this savage revolt and the murder of many of his family scarred young Peter for life and affected the whole future of Russia, Moscow and the Orthodox religion as well.

Peter was a bright, physically healthy and attractive boy, who started to learn the arts of war from foreigners in the "German" suburb (actually a ghetto), using his boyhood friends and neighboring children in the vicinity of Preobrazhenskoe as soldiers, as each year he had more real implements of war sent out from Moscow. He learned to build and sail western-type boats from Dutchmen in the foreign colony and developed an intense interest in the sea. In the meantime, under Sophia the regent and her prime minister and lover, Vasily Golitsyn, a treaty had been signed with King Sobieski of Poland in which Russia received Kiev in exchange for warring against the Crimean Tatars, vassals of Sobieski's enemy, the Turks. Twice Golitsyn marched south to wipe out those Tatars and twice he came back soundly defeated, although this was never acknowledged in Moscow publicly. The Tatars had previously carried off 20,000 Russian men to slavery in one raid alone in 1662 and by the end of the century Russian slaves manned the oars of galleys in every harbor in the eastern Mediterranean. In Golitsyn's two abortive attacks he lost 80,000 men - dead or taken prisoner - and to aggravate matters the Tatar Khan then raided the Ukraine again, taking 60,000 more prisoners.

When he was 17 Peter's boyar backers overthrew Sophia as regent and confined her to a convent. Although officially czar, Peter did not actually reign until 1694 when he was 22 and in the meantime administration of Russia deteriorated rapidly. There was reaction again against all foreigners and they were stopped at the borders unless permission was obtained from the central government. The patriarch ordered all Jesuits out and even wanted all Protestant churches in the German suburbs destroyed, but Peter spent much time there and prevented that. Peter, as all Russians before and after, was a heavy drinker, often drinking all night long. He even formed "Peter's Jolly Company" in which the primary requisite for membership was a capacity for drink and like the lowest Russian worker, they simply drank every night until they became unconscious. The Jolly Company even created the "Drunken Synod", a thinly veiled mockery of the Church. Married at 16 1/2 years, he soon had a male child but thereafter ignored his wife Eudoxia. At about the time he actually assumed his duties as a czar, he developed what was apparently focal epilepsy, frequently having severe spasms about the left side of his face and neck with occasional radiation to the left arm. This may have resulted from a high fever in l693, now speculated to have been encephalitis. By 1695 Peter's war games had progressed up to the use of 30,000 grown men and as czar he then decided to attack the Ottomans at Azov and promptly took an army there. He failed, partly because he had no ships to control the River Don, bordering Azov. So he next built a shipyard at Voronezh, getting shipbuilding experts sent in by the Doge of Venice, while he cut up and transported a galley previously ordered from Holland from its docking at Archangel down to Voronezh to serve as a model.

Peter's co-czar, crippled half-brother Ivan V, died in the same year that Peter made a second strike at Azov with 46,000 Russian soldiers, 15,000 Ukranian Cossacks, 5,000 Don Cossacks and 3,000 Kalmucks, semi-Asiatic horsemen who could ride with any Tatar, along with hundreds of new barges and 29 war galleys. Af ter a 2 month seige, the Turks surrendered the city. Peter was in the midst of all the fighting and at the end he reorganized and fortified the city and then constructed a new fort, harbor and naval base some 30 miles from the Don on the north shore of the Sea of Azov, at Tagonrog, using some 20,000 Ukranian laborers. He sent 3,000 peasant families and 3,000 Streltsy and their families to Azov as colonizers. The state then undertook to build 10 large ships, but great landowners and monasteries were to supply everything except the timber. Western shipbuilders were imported and Russians were sent west to learn shipbuilding, seamanship and navigation. It is obvious that Russians were not seamen, although wild Cossacks in boats crammed with sails, had pirated the Black Sea throughout this century. (Ref. 156, 157)

Young Czar Peter then took off to western Europe on what has been called "The Great Embassy". The real purpose of this trip was to strengthen the old alliance against the Turks, as Peter had decided he could not f ight them alone. King Sobieski of Poland had died in 1696 and France was possibly preparing for new wars with the Habsburg Empire. In addition, Peter wanted to educate himself concerning his new navy. The czar went incognito, although with his towering height of 6' 7", he was hard to hide and although some deception was kept, the ruling powers of Europe knew his identity. Officially the top ambassador in the group was Peter's Swiss friend and confidant, Lefort, and he was assisted by Fedor Golovin and Prokof y Voznitsyn. There was an additional escort of 20 noblemen and 35 young Russians, chiefly old friends and previous "play" soldiers. Chamberlains, priests, secretaries, interpreters, musicians, cooks and soldiers made up the rest of the party of 250. The trek started in 1697 through Livonia, thence through the Duchy of Courland to Brandenburg and then to Hanover. The embassy's first extended stop was in Holland, where Peter studied and worked in the shipbuilding yards of both Zaandam and Amsterrdam. In the latter city he lived in a small house and cooked his own meals, while he worked each day in the yards. But he also visited engineers, printers, anatomist Fredik Ruysch, botanist Boerhaave and naturalist van Leeuwenhoek, inventor of the microscope. After meeting William of Orange, who was King William of England as well as Stadholder of Holland, the czar was invited with a small party to visit England for 4 months. Although still incognito, he did visit with the King and Princess Anne. His residence in England was Sayes Court, a large, elegant house with great gardens opening onto the dockyard on a river. After 3 months Peter's Russians had practically destroyed the house, the furniture (apparently used for firewood), pictures and portraits (used for target practice) and the garden. Peter paid 28,000 pounds for permission to import a limited amount of tobacco into Russia, although the use of this plant had been accompanied by the death penalty under Czar Michael.

In the meantime the remainder of the embassy in Holland had recruited 640 Dutchmen, including one Rear-Admiral and other navy officers, seamen, engineers, physicians and others along with ten ship loads of equipment to go to Russia. Returning home the embassy went through Saxony to Vienna, where Leopold I reigned as emperor and where Peter was considered scarcely better than other eastern princes who lived in tents. The embassy made great efforts to try to get Austria to push harder against the Turks, but Leopold, becoming more nervous about the French king, was about to make peace with Turkey. Peter then tried to get the emperor to have the Ottomans yield Kerch (controlling the entrance to the Black Sea from the Sea of Azov) to Russia and again Leopold would not accommodate.

At about that time the czar received news from Moscow of a revolt of 4 regiments of Streltsy. The revolters had already all been killed or taken prisoner by an army under General Patrick Gordon, an old Scots friend and advisor of Peter's, but the czar decided to go on home anyway. He had determined to transform Russia into a modern state on western principles. He initially decreed such superficial changes as the cutting off of beards, change to western clothing by abolishing the long cloaks and sleeves going below the finger tips, etc. Women were to use petticoats, skirts, bonnets and western shoes.

The calendar was changed to the Julian one so that the old Russian year 7,206 then became the year 1698. Russian coinage was revised and instead of giving large estates or money for service to the state, one would henceforth get the "Order of St. Andrew" - a ribbon to wear diagonally across the chest. The prisoners remaining from the Streltsy rebellion, numbering 1714, were now "examined" under terrible torture by knout (a type of lash) and fire and then most were executed. A few of the young ones were not killed but were either branded on the right cheek and exiled or had their noses or ears cut off. The Streltsy were no more.

Peter the Great's southern fleet, built at Voronezh on the Don, was never used, because in the Peace of Carlowitz between Austrians, Poles, Turks and indirectly Russi ans, the Turks did concede Azov but not Kerch to the Russians. In June, 1700 the Russian ambassador in Constantinople negotiated a 30 year truce with a demilitarized zone supposedly to be established between the Crimean Tatars and Russia, proper. This agreement infuriated the Tatar Khan, Devlet Gerey. In the meantime, Peter's two most trusted foreign advisors, the Swiss Lefort and the Scot General Gordon, had died. And then the Great Northern War came towards Russia. (Ref. 158)

1 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

10 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

11 [86] HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

14 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

15 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

16 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

17 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

18 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

19 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

20 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

21 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

22 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

23 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

24 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

25 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

26 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

27 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

28 [184] Rodes, JOHN E., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

29 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

30 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

31 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

32 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

33 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

34 [52] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part VII - The Age of Reason Begins. (1961).

35 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

36 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

37 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

38 [184] Rodes, JOHN E., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

39 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

40 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

41 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

42 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

43 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

44 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

45 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

48 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

49 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

50 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

51 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

52 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

53 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

54 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

55 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

56 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

57 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

58 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

59 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

60 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

61 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

62 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

63 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

64 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

65 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

66 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

67 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

68 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

69 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

70 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

71 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

72 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

73 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

74 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

75 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

76 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

77 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

78 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

79 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

80 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

81 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

82 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

83 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

84 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

85 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

86 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

87 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

88 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

89 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

90 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

91 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

92 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

93 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

94 [13] BERGER, Teny, "Tulipomania was no Dutch treat to gambling burghers", Smithsonian 8:70-77, April, 1977.

95 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

96 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

97 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

98 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

99 [163] PAGELS, ELAINE, The Gnostic Gospels. (Random House, New York 1979).

100 [218] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

101 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

102 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

103 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

104 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

105 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

106 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

107 [214] THOMSON, DANIEL, "The Ebb & Flow of Infection", Journal of the American Medical Assoc. 235: Vol. 3, page 269, Jan 19, 1976).

108 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

109 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

110 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

111 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

112 [214] THOMSON, DANIEL, "The Ebb & Flow of Infection", Journal of the American Medical Assoc. 235: Vol. 3, page 269, Jan 19, 1976).

113 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

114 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

115 [147] MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

116 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

117 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

118 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

119 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

120 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

121 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

122 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

123 [110] JUDGE, JOSEPH, The Travail of Ireland", National Geographic 1159: 432-441, Apr. 1981.

124 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

125 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

126 [110] JUDGE, JOSEPH, The Travail of Ireland", National Geographic 1159: 432-441, Apr. 1981.

127 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

128 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

129 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

130 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

131 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

132 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

133 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

134 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

135 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

136 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

137 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

138 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

139 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

140 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

141 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

142 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

143 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

144 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

145 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

146 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

147 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

148 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

149 [53] DURANT, Will and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

150 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

151 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

152 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

153 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

154 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

155 [288] "PEOPLES of the Arctic", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

156 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

157 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

158 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

1.  Quotation from Braudel (Ref. 45), page 110

2.  This was after the ascension of the heretic Queen Elizabeth

3.  Of this number, 10,000 made up the ruling aristocracy. (Ref. 93)

4.  The wood shortage also led to use of coal in houses, and by 1660 Britain produced 1/2 million tons of coal, five times that of the rest of the world. English coal, however, interacted poorly with iron ore and was not good for smelting iron, which was still imported. (Ref. 110)

5.  Italian merchants were also numerous in the cities and fairs of Poland in this century. (Ref. 147)

Europe: A.D. 1701 to 1800

EUROPE (A "French Century", with a decline of religion in political affairs)

Even before the Industrial Revolution of the last quarter of this century, there was dramatic change in Europe. Spain and Italy were declining rapidly, while England, France, Sweden (exploiting mineral resources) were developing quickly. But it was a century of almost constant warfare, with conflict going on in some area all the time and in several localities at once most of the time. (Ref. 1) McNeill (Ref. 2) emphasizes that there were four limits to the existing military organizations:

The difficulty of controlling the movements of an army of more than about 50,000 men. New forms of communication and more accurate terrain maps were needed
Slow transport of supplies. Food for the men and fodder for thousands of horses made a bulky and awkward supply train. Living off the countryside destroyed the tax-base and allowed the soldiers to get out of control as they became immersed in plunder, so the rulers sought to supply armies from the rear
Organizational and tactical problems. With the long history of mercenary contingents and patronage appointments, it was difficult to organize an effective, cohesive army based on training and ability, tempered with seniority
Sociological and psychological restraints. Peasants were needed to produce the food and townsmen to provide the money, so that it was difficult to recruit enough men for a professional army without infringing on those two necessary groups

The answer to some of the above situations was in the development of new technology in weapons, such as mobile field artillery; development of accurate small-scale mapping; the break-down of the armies to divisions, units of about 12,000 men, but complete within themselves, with infantry, cavalry, artillery and all supportive elements; and better road-building .

At the same time, in spite of the warfare, the 18th century saw the heyday of wealthy merchants all over Europe. (Ref. 3) The philosophers were convinced that this was an age of enlightenment and progress, but it was a time of bungling politicians, greedy nobles, of immorality and corruption also. There were other paradoxes. In spite of great scientific advancements in physics and chemistry, the practice of medicine lagged far behind and may even have declined. Bleeding, cupping and purging remained prominent treatments. (Ref. 4) An estimated 60 million Europeans died of small-pox in the century and early there was an extensive famine, as frost killed crops as far south as the Mediterranean coast. The winter of 1709 was especially severe, with most northern rivers and even ocean coastal waters frozen. (Ref. 5) Typhus fever took its own toll, with a severe epidemic in Sweden and the loss of 30,000 people in France in mid-century. Yellow fever killed 10,000 in Cadiz, Spain. (Ref. 6)

The population of Europe went from 140 to 188 million from 1750 to 1800. The majority of the people were illiterate. In the f irst half of the century their civilization was based almost as much on wine as on wheat. Europe as a whole must have been burning 200 million tons of wood yearly up until about 1790 when coal came into more common usage. At the same time there were approximately 14 million horses, 24 million oxen, the equivalent of 4 to 5 million horsepower in the form of wood, 1.5 to 3 million horsepower potential in 600,000 watermills, 900,000 horsepower in the 50 million human workers and 233,000 horsepower in the form of sails, not counting war-fleets. (Ref. 7, 8)

A new business development was the concentration of trade and its profit to warehouses and storage depots. Raw cotton from Central America was stored in Cadiz, that from Brazil in Lisbon, Indian cotton was pooled in London, while Marseilles took that from the Levant. Mainz and Lille were great wine depots. By the end of the century, the Europe of fairs was turning into the Europe of warehouses. Exchange rates of silver and gold varied from time to time, seriously affecting the European economy. France over-valued silver and so that metal was attracted there, while Venice, Italy, Portugal, England and Holland put a high price on gold. (Ref. 9) Finally we must emphasize the tremendous effects from the extensive overseas colonies of multiple European nations. The map of the next page is well worth study in this regard.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The Ottoman Empire maintained its domination of the eastern Mediterranean islands with the exception of Malta, which remained independent under the Knights of Malta, until Napoleon's troops conquered it in 1798. (Ref. 10, 11)

GREECE

Greece was still docile under the Ottomans but Greek sea-farers and traders became prosperous at the end of the century as blockade runners through Napoleon's overseas domains and through other waters. By the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainardji (see page 942) the Turks allowed Russian ships to sail on the Black Sea, but since they had no ships or seamen of their own in those waters, they accorded Greeks and other Christians the right to fly the Russian flag.

UPPER BALKANS

In 1711 Peter the Great of Russia vowed to free the Balkans from "the enemies of Christ". Both Moldavia (now a part of both Romania and the Soviet Union) and Wallachia pledged to help Peter, but only Moldavia actually supplied any troops and at the last minute Wallachia double-crossed the Russians so that Peter ended up pocketed with only 138,000 infantry, almost surrounded by 200,000 Turks and Tatars. The Russians surrendered, giving Azov and the Tagenrog harbor back to the sultan, abandoned their southern fleet and evacuated Poland. Russia did not give up any territory about the Baltic. Karl (Charles) XII of Sweden, who had just spent over three years in Moldavia, could now go back to Sweden. Meanwhile, Brancovo, the Hospodar of Wallachia, was beheaded by the Turks for his original thoughts of helping Czar Peter, even though in the end he had reneged. (Ref. 12)

As a result of a war of the Ottomans with Austria and Russia again in 1736 to 1739, northern Serbia and Belgrade were freed from Austrian domination. Again, in the First War of Catharine, Moldavia and Wallachia were both overrun by Russian troops and about 7 years later (17~1) by an Austrian-Russian Treaty the Austrians were to receive the whole western half of the Balkans. Af ter the Second War of Catharine, the Austrians gave up Belgrade in return for a strip of northern Bosnia, while Moldavia and Bessarabia were returned to Russia.

Maize from America had been grown in gardens in the Balkans under at least ten different names for many years, but it was not until this century that it began to be grown in the wide open fields, as in much of the rest of Europe. (Ref. 13)

ITALY

Italy had a population of about 15,000,000, living under divided rule. The old noble families of Florence and Venice were shrinking and fresh blood had to be brought in. Titles were granted for money. (Ref. 14) The Habsburgs took over Tuscany in 1737 and except for Venetia, Genoa and Savoy, they soon controlled all of northern Italy. The Papal States and Kingdom of the Two Sicilies remained as previously, and the Genoese Republic remained independent but was constantly encroached on by Savoy, France and Austria. The forces which led to the revolution in France were also at work in Italy in the last of the century and when the French Revolution did break out, some Italian states tried to join in a coalition against France. As a result, Napoleon invaded the peninsula, crushed all resistance and once again Italy became a French dependency. At that time, General Napoleon was only a young army wizard, but that military conquest initiated his climb up the ladder of fame and power. The 1797 Treaty of Camp Formio, however, gave Venice to Austria1 and divided the rest of Italy into 5 republics: Cisalpine with Milan as capital; Liguria, with Genoa as capital; Roman, including Rome itself; Bologna; and Parthenopean, which included the entire southern third (except Sicily), with Naples as the capital. (Ref. 15, 16)

Naples, with perhaps 500,000 people, was the 4th largest city in Europe, although at the end of the century at least 100,000 were extremely poor, living like "filthy animals". (Ref. 18) All southern Italy had a feudal system, with powerful barons who were sovereigns on their own estates. In the Kingdom of Naples over 50% of the population were subject to feudal justice and in some provinces this was over 80%. As in the rest of Europe, food supplies in Italy frequently were short and unreliable. As an example, Florence experienced hunger in 111 years of the 400 leading up to 1791 and had had only 16 "very good" harvests in that same period. Maize, with its high yield, finally put an end to the recurrent famines in Venetia. All over Italy, soon the peasants ate maize and sold their wheat. Transportation and communications remained slow. With horses, coaches, ships and runners, messages could make at most 100 kilometers in 24 hours. (Ref. 19)

The islands bordering the Tyrrhenian Sea were in constant political turmoil throughout this century. In 1713 Spain ceded Sardinia (along with Naples) to Austria and Sicily to Savoy, but by 1720 the latter had exchanged Sicily for Sardinia. In 1732 Genoa recovered Corsica from insurgent forces, who had revolted two years previously, but French help was necessary to control the island. In the same spot local clans under Paoli again rebelled in 1755 against Genoese rule and established a democracy, but France bought the island from Genoa in 1768 and crushed Paoli, only to see him rise again in 1793. On the latter occasion he was defeated by Napoleon, himself a Corsican. In that same year, Sardinia tried to get autonomy within the combined kingdom of Piedmont-Sardina. Through this century Sardinia was a strong military state - the Prussia of Italy. Usually it was allied with Austria through Eugene of Savoy, a great military leader for the Habsburgs.

In spite of the turmoil, Italy continued to be a center for scientific and medical studies. Luigi Galvani started electro-physiology with electrical stimulation of nerves; Allessandro Volta developed a battery. Giovanni Morgagni, at the medical school at Padua for 56 years, is considered the "father" of pathological anatomy, describing the changes associated with such diseases as cirrhosis of the liver, kidney tuberculosis, syphilitic brain lesions and pneumonic consolidation of lungs. (Ref. 20)

CENTRAL EUROPE

GERMANY

After a long period of disorderly aftermath of the horrors of the Thirty Years War, the German-speaking people, with peace, stability and their natural strength, returned to add to the European civilization, particularly in music and Rococo style architecture. (Ref. 21) Germany was made up of 20,000,000 people divided into more than 300 practically independent states, each with its own sovereign prince, but all loosely subject to the head of the rather phantom Holy Roman Empire. The average east German village was still somewhat "servile" in 1750, however, and serfs still owed their masters heavy services and payments and they were not allowed to leave their estates in most German areas as late as 1788. (Ref. 22) In spite of considerable river traffic on the Rhine, Elbe and Oder rivers, overland transport still carried 5 times as much goods as waterways. It has been estimated that there were 40,000 horses used as dray animals, not including those on farms. (Ref. 23)

The story of this country f rom this time on was that of the power policies of two royal families - the Prussian Hohenzollerns, - represented by Frederick I, Frederick William I and Frederick 11 and their counter-parts, the Austrian Habsburgs. The complete power structure also involved Catherine II of Russia and to some extent, England. We shall try to clarify this situation by discussing some of the individual states, separately.

PRUSSIA

The Junker landlords of Prussia distinguished themselves by competent management and their quick adoption of improved agricultural techniques. (Ref. 24) On the political side, the Prussian Elector Frederick III2, son of the Great Elector, had himself crowned King Frederick I of Prussia in 1701, but his extravagancies merely hastened bankruptcy of the state. Some 300,000 deaths from plague in 1709 did not help the situation. (Ref. 25) Then came Frederick Wilhelm I (1713-1740), an austere king who hammered out a military power. At his death Prussia had the 4th largest army in Europe and strong financial resources. He was a friend and ally of Peter the Great of Russia, but in his personal life he was eccentric and unfortunate3. He suffered from a severe, combined form of porphoryhia, a genetic disease which can affect skin and visceral organs at times, along with great abdominal pain. He was subject to sudden, uncontrollable attacks of rage at which times he might even beat his own children. His eccentricities included hatred of everything French and he had a hobby of collecting giants from all over the world, some 1,200 of them, whom he formed into two battalions of grenadiers. On his death in 1740, his son Frederick II became king and initiated the Francophile tradition.

At the end of the Great Northern War, which will be discussed again later, Prussia had acquired the city of Stettin and some Baltic islands. Having been raised as a warrior prince, Frederick II, later to be called Frederick the Great, hastened to put the Prussian war machine to work by invading Silesia and provoking war with the Habsburg Empire. (Ref. 26) He gained not only Silesia but after three wars with the Austrian Empress Maria Theresa, also gained a part of Poland. The Seven Years War (1756-1763), the last one with the Habsburgs, involved Prussia, Hanover and England on one side and France, Austria and Russia on the other. After initial- victories through Saxony and Bohemia, Frederick began to meet def eat and was pushed back so that at one time the Russians even occupied Berlin. In the f inal Peace of Hubertusburg, Saxony was restored to its pre-war size, Silesia was retained by Prussia and Frederick agreed to vote f or Maria Theresa's son Joseph for emperor when the occasion developed. Frederick estimated that that war alone cost him 853,000 troop casualties and 33,000 civilian deaths. (Ref. 27) Furthermore, he had developed a great fear of Russia and started a campaign of vilification while at the same time plotting that future relations with that country should be based on friendship. Thus, in 1770 he made an alliance with Catherine the Great. In the newly gained Silesia, the government combined with land owners to invest in mining, iron and textiles. In Prussia proper Berlin had 140,000 people by 1777. (Ref. 28) Imported techniques, including artificial drainage and canalization particularly, allowed considerable new land to be brought under cultivation and thus added wealth. (Ref. 29)

Frederick the Great actually hated the German language and thought that anything French was great. He had a long and close relationship with Voltaire, as fellow philosopher, poet and confidant. At one and the same time he had a great mind, while being a benevolent king and a great general. But he was also an untrustworthy ally and a power-mad monarch.

The advancement of Prussia as the dominant northern Germanic state did not occur by accident. Frederick William II came to the throne in 1786 and when France declared a new war on Austria in April of 1792 Prussia and most German states sided with the new Emperor Francis II. Austro-Prussian forces met severe defeat at Valmy, allowing the French to take the offensive on all fronts. Russia invaded Poland and in spite of the deterioration of the Prussian armies, in the resulting last partition of unfortunate Poland, Warsaw and environs with its 1,000,000 people fell to Prussia. In the Peace of Basel of 1795 Prussia recognized the legal status of the republican government of France, while the latter promised neutrality of the German states north of the Main. (Ref. 30)

But Prussia was not all militarism. In 1717 Frederick William I had made primary education compulsory and in 20 years he founded 1,700 schools. German universities became excellent, although German literature suffered some from lack of national consciousness and the influence of French among the aristocracy. German intellectuals remained cosmopolitan and considered nationalism as a "political monstrosity". The development of science and philosophy shared with powerful secularizing forces in weakening the influence of religion on German life. Art and architecture was not at its best, but music was supreme, with Handel and Bach. Bach's works are said to be the Reformation put to music and he is accepted as the "greatest musical poet that has ever existed". (Ref. 31) Christian Thomasius furthered the cause of the German language by lecturing at the university in German, rather than Latin. A literary revival was initiated near the end of the century as the works of the great Johann Wolfgang von Goethe began to appear. Frederick von Schiller contributed some fine dramas. Gottfried Leibniz, scientist and mathematician, founded the Academy of Sciences.

Map taken from Reference 97

BAVARIA

Bavaria continued to be ruled by the Wittelsbach family. In 1777 the Elector of Bavaria, Joseph Maximilian, died childless and the nearest heir, another Wittelbach concluded a pact with Emperor Joseph of the Habsburgs whereby most of Palatinate and northern Bavaria went to Austria. Other Wittelbachs, along with Frederick II of Prussia, anxious to keep things in balance, protested Austria's aggrandizements and opened the War of the Bavarian Succession. In a year Bavaria had regained her territory. At the end of the century, however, Bavaria became the chief battlef ield of the Spanish War of Succession and Austrian troops devastated the land. In 1799 Elector Maximilian I united all Wittelsbach lands and allied himself with Napoleon, as a protection against Austria.

It is interesting that in spite of some food shortages, the potato was slow to be adopted in middle Europe. In 1795 the poor of Munich refused to eat a supposedly scientific soup containing potatoes. (Ref. 32) At the end of the century there was one market in Bavaria for every 7,300 inhabitants. (Ref. 33)

SAXONY

The young Elector of Saxony, Augustus II, had also been elected King of Poland in 1697. In August of 1706, as part of the Great Northern War, the Swedish army crossed the Silesian frontier to march on Saxony itself, to permanently dispose of the Elector Augustus. The Saxon governing council, having already sacrificed 36,000 troops, 800 cannon and 8,000,000 lives in an effort to keep Augustus on the throne of Poland, wanted no more trouble and signed the Treaty of Altranstadt, which disavowed Augustus and agreed to supply the Swedish army during the coming winter and to turn over all Swedish "traitors" harbored in Saxony, a feature which finally resulted in the horrible death of the Livonian patriot, Patkul - first tortured on the wheel, then beheaded and quartered. While resting in Saxony in 1707 the Swedish King Karl XII was visited by John Churchill, Duke of Marlborough, who already had Louis XIV more or less "on the ropes" and then wanted to scout the Swedish king's intentions and get a look at his troops.

Elector Augustus II eventually did return to his people and then he and Karl XII got along well. Actually they were first cousins, as their mothers were sisters as Danish princesses. (Ref. 34)

In spite of all the warfare, Elector Augustus II continued the policies of his predecessors and collected fabulous works of art, so that Dresden eventually became known as Florence on the Elbe. His son and successor Augustus III carried on the same tradition. (Ref. 35) Dresden, Leipzig and Chemnitz specialized in porcelain, silk, armaments and textiles, but the first cotton spinning mill was not started until 1794. Only 5 of Saxony's 200 towns had over 10,000 people. The Swiss Albrecht von Haller, a disciple of the Dutch Boerhaaves settled in Saxony and helped to create the University of Goettingen. He became a great physician, physiologist, botanist and neurologist. (Ref. 36, 37)

Saxony served as a battleground for many of the Prussian campaigns and in the Second Silesian War of 1744 Frederick II took 80,000 men through Saxony to invade Bohemia.

Shortly thereafter Saxony joined an alliance with Austria, England and Holland against Prussia, again on the wrong side, so that at the Treaty of Dresden, Saxony was forced to pay Prussia 1,000,000 rix dollars. Once again in the Third Silesian War (the Seven Years War) Frederick invaded Saxony with 67,000 men and defeated the combined Austrians and Saxons, taking 18,000 of the latter as prisoners. At the final peace, however, the original status of Saxony was preserved. In the War of the Bavarian Succession (1778) Saxony even joined Prussia, with Prince Henry joining Frederick in another invasion of Bohemia, but no real battles with the Austrians developed. For the remainder of the century, Saxony continued to oppose the grandiose schemes of Emperor Joseph.

HANOVER

In this century Hanover, in northern Germany, had about as much power as Denmark, Prussia or Saxony. Its status was helped when George, the Elector of Hanover, became George I of England. He never did like the English, nor they him, although they would take any sovereign Protestant over a Catholic. George spent most of his time in Hanover and used the English navy and money to try to make Sweden negotiate peace with Denmark and the German states on the Baltic. (Ref. 38)

LESSER STATES OF GERMANY

Like Bavaria, Baden and Wuerttenberg became battlefields at the end of the century as the French forces fought Austria. Throughout these years, although their princes had difficulty acknowledging it, these lesser states of Germany lost more and more power and influence. The Rhineland of west Germany became the first industrial area, with the first steam engine installed in a lead mine near Duesseldorf in the Duchy of Berg in 1751. (Ref. 39)

AUSTRIA | HUNGARY | CZECHOSLOVAKIA

Although all German states were nominally subject to the Holy Roman Empire, the real heart was the Austro-Hungary-Bohemia region, ruled by the Habsburgs in Vienna. In 1711 Austria lost 300,000 people to the Black Death and another Turkish army was near their border. The latter were put to rout by Prince Eugene of Savoy, who had become a great militarist for the Habsburgs. His success at this time was in part due to Austrian cavalry using fine Arabian horses. (Ref. 40) Emperor Joseph I, the elder son of Leopold, had a premature death and Karl (Charles), trained to become king of Spain, now had to be Austria's emperor as Karl (Charles) VI. Raised as a Spaniard, he remained such. The Spanische Reitschule (Spanish Riding Academy) is a remnant of his Spanish court. His death in 1740 marked the end of the male line of the Austrian Habsburgs, but it was the beginning of Austria's greatest era. (Ref. 41) Interpreting Karl's death as indicating a coming weakness in the empire, Frederick II of Prussia was tempted to move on Silesia for the First Silesian War4. (Ref. 42)

When Karl VI's daughter became Empress Maria Theresa, the Austro-Hungarian Empire included all of present day Austria except Salzburg, Hungary, Bohemia, Moravia, Silesia5, Transylvania, Croatia, Slavonia, Dalmatia, Istria with Fiume and Treiste, parts of southwestern Germany, Belgium, Lombardy, Tuscany, Sardinia, Peacenza and Parma. The intrigues and power politics of this empress involved not only Frederick the Great but Catherine II and Peter of Russia. Their wars for prestige and for portions of Poland seemed almost without end. Austria's part in the Seven Years War, which exhausted the country, is more fully explained in the sections on GERMANY, FRANCE AND ENGLAND. In 1772 Maria Theresa shared with Prussia and Russia in the first partition of Poland.

Austria, itself, with 6,000,000 people was prosperous. All land was owned by nobles or clergy and tilled by serfs. The nobles were not particularly religious, but worked to promote the Catholicism, which helped their serfs to accept their earthly lot. Industry was initiated as Maria Theresa founded a woolen manufactory in Linz, employing no less than 15,600 workers (26,000 by 1775) although about 2/3 were spinners and weavers working at home. (Ref. 44) The empress was a great patron of Mozart and he played for her at Schoenbrunn Castle. The Dutchman Gerhard van Swieten, another pupil of Boerhaave, was called to Vienna by the empress to be her personal physician and he started a medical school which drew flocks of students from all over Europe. Incident to this was the building of the famous Allgemeines Krankenhaus in 1784 as a hospital for teaching and caring for the underprivileged. (Ref. 45)

After 1765 Maria Theresa6 shared her power with her son Joseph II until her death in 1780. Joseph anticipated the welfare state by 150 years. The spate of reforms was torrential. He abolished serfdom and torture and eliminated heresy as a crime. He made German the official overall language, and antagonized his nobles, his mother, and even the pope. Joseph was followed by Francis II, who engaged in a constant and losing war with the advancing French. At the Peace of Basel, Austria agreed to French control of almost the entire left bank of the Rhine and gave up Belgium.

Although a part of the great empire, Hungary did not lie quietly. The Rakoczi rebellion from 1703 until 1711 was a Hungarian revolt against the Imperial Crown of Austria. In the end it only resulted in more disunion among the people. By that time Karl (Charles)VI was emperor and he sincerely wanted the Hungarians to be treated generously. The reign of Maria Theresa is considered by some Hungarian historians as a period of rest and recuperation, but by others as one of stagnation. Population and immigration both increased rapidly during the period of peace. The wealth of the Catholic Church and the size of the mansions and estates of the great nobles also increased, while the economy was still agricultural and industry was kept down by the Austrian rulers. The Protestant Church was suppressed and no Protestant could enter public service. By the end of the century only half of the magnate class was Hungarian and even they spent much time in Vienna and Paris, intermarried with German-Austrian and Bohemian aristocracy and often forgot or didn't even learn their Magyar language. The middle nobles were the ones who remained home and kept the national spirit and the language alive. The immigrants were from all the surrounding states but the greatest number were from south Germany and, in general, classed together as "Swabians". In the 1760s and 1770s there were 50,000 German immigrants and another 25,000 in the 1780s. (Ref. 46) By the end of Maria Theresa's reign the 3,350,000 Magyars made up 35% of the total population and were chiefly in the central part of the country. There were 1,500,000 Romanians, 1,250,000 Slovaks, 1,000,000 Germans and 750,000 each of Croats and Serbs. The latter were always a thorn in the Hungarians' flesh. Although Joseph II replaced Latin with German as the language of administration and schools, when his brother Leopold II became emperor in 1790 he reversed this decree.

Bohemia's fate was similar to Hungary's. Subject to the Habsburg autocratic rule the life of both Bohemian and Moravian peasants was hard, with compulsory labor accepted. Persecution of Jews began in 1744, with some fleeing to England. (Ref. 47) Near the end of the century the Czechs began to feel a spirit of national unity and started ideas of freedom. Leopold II tried to conciliate them, but he was the last Austrian ruler to be crowned King of Bohemia.

To complete our story of the 18th century Habsburg Empire, we must relate that upon Joseph II's death, his brother, who had succeeded their father as grand duke of Tuscany, became Emperor Leopold II. The state was in some disarray and he had to repeal most of Joseph's radical reforms. After reaching an agreement with Frederick William II of Prussia, he negated the old alliance with Catherine of Russia and concluded a separate peace treaty with Turkey at Sistova in 1791. He also marched troops into the Austrian Netherlands and suppressed the Belgian Republic. He was succeeded in 1792 by his son, Francis II, who was soon confronted by the French Revolution. His armies were defeated by Napoleon and by the Treaty of Campo Formio of 1797 he ceded the left bank of the Rhine to France, but obtained Venetia and Dalmatia. In 1798 he joined the Second Coalition against France and was defeated again.

SWITZERLAND

In 1715 the Swiss Federation was made up of 13 Cantons, a complex of three peoples, four languages and two faiths. Most of the Cantons were oligarchies, with very limited suffrage, but serfdom had almost completely disappeared. Bern was the largest canton, embracing approximately 1/3 of Switzerland. Religion was half the government and half the strife. (Ref. 48) The two rival religions - Calvinist and Catholic – exuded hatred and shackled the mind. Some Cantons prohibited any but Catholic worship and some forbade any but Protestant. Geneva was not a Canton, but a separate republic with French speech and Calvinist faith. The emigration of Huguenots to this city was a great boon.

Map taken from Reference 97

In 1789 Switzerland was overrun by the armies of Napoleon and he set up a centralized Helvettic Republic, which was in close alliance with France and all the old liberties of the Cantons were wiped out. The most famous Swiss of the century were Jean Jacques Rousseau, philosopher, author and political theorist, who developed a persecution mania, living some in Switzerland, some in England and some in France and Albrecht von Haller, who did most of his medical work in Saxony.

WESTERN EUROPE

In Western Europe this was a century of warfare, at first involving Spain, France and England primarily and then the latter two especially near the end of the century.

The War of the Spanish Succession lasted from 1701 to 1714, beginning with the death of the last Spanish Habsburg, when Leopold of the Austrian branch of the family opened the struggle trying to get the Spanish inheritance of Carlos II, by invading Italy. The idea was to keep Louis XIV's grandson Philip off the Spanish throne and in his effort he was encouraged by England and the Dutch Republic. The Holy Roman Empire, Portugal and Savoy also declared war on France, while Spain, itself and France were backed by the Electors of Bavaria and Cologne. The antagonists fought most of the battles in the beautiful countryside of Bavaria. At the end, the compromise Peace of Utrecht allowed Spain to keep Philip, but the Spanish Netherlands went to the Austrian Habsburgs and Spain's previous Italian territories went to Savoy. (Ref. 49)

The new luxury of the 18th century meant a change in the living conditions of both rich and poor. Of primary importance was the separation of living quarters from the workshop or business. Up until this time merchants' and artisans' houses had the shop on the lower floor, the master's dwelling above and the workmen's or apprentices' rooms above that. (Ref. 50) Industrial activity was widespread so that there was not a town or City without its own looms, forges, brick or tile works or sawmill. In some areas there were huge concentrations of workers: 30,000 in the coal industry in Newcastle; 450,000 weavers in Languedoc; 1,500,000 textile workers in five northern French provinces. But commerce and its accompanying wealth were in the hands of but a few, 4 or 5 merchants in Seville, 8 or 9 in Le Mans and less than 1% of the population of Marseilles. Similarly, the nobility of Lombardy made up 1% of the population, but possessed about 1/2 of all landed property. (Ref. 51)

SPAIN

We have mentioned Spain's problem of establishing a new ruler after the death of the imbecile king Carlos (Charles) II in the remarks just above. Practically no battles were fought on Spanish soil. Although both the English King William and the Emperor Leopold died during the war, it dragged on with Eugene of Savoy handling the Habsburg war machine and the great Duke of Marlborough (John Churchill) handling English policy. Spain did lose Naples, Parma, Sardinia and Milan to Austria, while Sicily went to Savoy and Gibraltar and Minorca went to England. In the last 3/4 of the century Spain was more or less involved in continuous wars with various European alliances over various territories and successions - the War of the Polish Succession, the War of Jenkins Ear with England, the War of the Austrian Succession, the Seven Years War, then war with France, then with France against England again. At the end of that last one, at the 2nd Treaty of Ildefonso, France obtained Louisiana from Spain. In spite of all, the Spanish overseas empire brought wealth and prosperity throughout the century. Spain made war on American gold.

Map taken from Reference 97.

Philip V, grandson of Louis XIV was the first Bourbon on the Spanish throne. A melancholy man, he was dominated by women, first the princesse des Ursins, lady in waiting to his first consort, Maria Luisa of Savoy, then by his wife Elizabeth Farnese, who in turn was dominated by the chief minister, Cardinal Alberoni. In the War of the Polish Succession Naples and Sicily passed to Don Carlos (later Carlos III), son of Philip and Elizabeth. In the War of the Austrian Succession Spain obtained Parma and Piacenze for Charles' younger brother, Philip. Philip V was succeeded by Ferdinand VI, his son by Maria Luisa. In the years before the Seven Years War both France and England had sought a Spanish alliance, but Ferdinand, by manipulating his ministers, kept Spain out of that war during his lifetime. He died in 1759 and was followed by his half brother, Carlos (Charles) III, who finally succumbed to pressure from France and got involved in the war, which drained Spanish revenues and resulted in England receiving Florida, although he did obtain Louisiana from France. Because he helped the Americans some in their revolution, Carlos re-obtained Florida and picked up Minorca from England at the Treaty of Paris of 1783. Carlos III is regarded as the greatest Bourbon king of Spain, but Carlos IV, who followed, was ineffective.

The best silk in Europe was grown in Valencia, where there were 5,000 looms by 1787. By 1790 there were a hundred cotton factories in Catalonia, with some 80,000 workers, chiefly women. Trading, even in slaves, was generally farmed out to Genoese contractors and French merchants dominated Seville. (Ref. 52) Galacia had 5,243 watermills and 12 windmills in an area of 2,000 square leagues and a population of 2,000,000. (Ref. 53) The Basque country was tending to become a national market. In the end, even Church property and estates went on sale and overall, land ownership became concentrated in a few hands and the poor became still poorer. (Ref. 54)

PORTUGAL

Portugal had now practically abandoned the Indian Ocean, except for its colony at Goa, India to which it occasionally sent a boatload of convicts. This was a century of Portuguese alliance with England. The Methuen Treaty of 17037 established Portugal's wine trade and admitted English manufactured products without duty. Many of the vineyards in the Oporto area were English owned and England admitted the wines at markedly reduced duties, much less than for French wines. (Ref. 55) The English penetration of the country was such that some Europeans referred to Portugal as an English colony, and it caused some warfare with Spain again and again. Lisbon had expanded into a huge city, with the rich becoming excessively so and the poor-more wretched. Shanty towns grew up around the margins where once there had been fields. There were as many as 10,000 vagrants in that city. (Ref. 56) But Lisbon was destroyed by a great earthquake in 1755, followed by a seismic wave with the flooding of the Tagus River basin and a great fire, so that all the city's treasures disappeared, along with the thousands-of deaths. (Ref. 57) The Jesuits were expelled from Portugal in 1759. Later, at the time of the French Revolution the nation was drawn into the war through its English alliance.

FRANCE

Like the 17th, this was a French century and French culture was as encompassing as French power. (Ref. 59) In the last years of his reign, Louis XIV drifted to the propitiation of the papacy, with continued and aggravated religious persecution. Great numbers of most valuable Protestant subjects left France, taking arts and industries with them, leaving mainly Catholic believers or Catholic atheists behind. Other serious troubles accumulated at the same time. The year 1709 was perhaps the worst year France had known. All the rivers and the Atlantic coastal waters froze, with the winter wheat, vines and fruit trees killed. Children starved to death and both public and private finances were in desperate ways. Then in 1711 the Grand Dauphin, Louis' only legitimate heir, died of small-pox and within 11 months the Dauphine and 2 of her 3 sons died of measles, leaving only the youngest grandson Berri. Even he died in 1714 after an accident on a horse, leaving only his nephew as heir to the throne. Thus, when Louis XIV died with a gangrenous leg in 1715, this great grandson became Louis XV, with a great uncle, Philippe Duc d'Orleans as regent. (Ref. 60) There resulted much unrest among the common people and a tumultous workers' strike of 1716 in Abbeville had to be put down with armed troops. (Ref. 61) During that interim Regency, a transplanted Scot, John Law, attempted to redeem the bankrupt finances of France by issuing paper money on the credit of the state, up to twice the value of the national reserves in precious metals and land. A central banking system was necessary and eventually established. The idea was basically sound, but in the end the entire system collapsed because of overspeculation by all of the people in Law's additional scheme of establishing a company to develop the Mississippi basin in America. In 1721 France had perhaps the world's worst stock market crash, as the leading value of stock in that Mississippi development company fell from 12,000 livres to 200. Durant (Ref. 62) says that the Regency was, morally, the most shameful period in the history of France. Religion disgraced itself by having immoral men at the top; government was corrupt by having immoral men throughout.

In 1707 almost 70,000 cattle were sold annually in Paris and later in the century there were some 21,000 horses in the city. By 1717 the capital h-ad about 500,000 people, the third largest city in Europe, but the streets were narrow and crowded, the noise deafening and the smells from human excrement dumped from windows and piles of manure and slaughtered animal carcasses were unbelievable. When the Swiss guards prevented Parisians from relieving themselves under a row of yews in the Tuileries, they simply went to the banks of the Seine, which was just as bad. Straw was put daily on the streets and the old straw pulled up and simply dumped in the river. Af ter midnight, when the candle lamps on the streets went out they became very dangerous. The same situation could be found in all towns, large and small. A bathroom in a house was a rare luxury. Fleas, lice and bugs conquered Paris as well as London and other European cities. (Ref. 63) High society was consumed with gambling - pharaoh, dominoes, checkers and chess were all played for high stakes. (Ref. 64) An average of 20,000 people died in Paris every year, even after the 1780s, some 4,000 of them ending their days in the poor-house. 7,000 to 8,000 children out of about 30,000 births were abandoned and depositing these at the poor-house became an occupation in itself. Hardly anyone in Paris took baths and those that did confined them to one or two a year. (Ref. 65)

Mass consumption of low quality wine became commonplace, even at the times of famine and drunkenness was everywhere. In the country the peasants were poverty stricken and there were a series of disastrous harvests between 1773 and 1789. Overall there were at least 16 general famines during the century as well as numerous local ones. The last great western European plague epidemic occurred in Marseilles in 1720 (but it continued in eastern Europe). (Ref. 66, 67) While glass was used in window-panes in Paris, oiled paper was still used for windows in Lyons and various provinces. But even in the midst of relative squalor, France began to set the fashion for dress for the whole of Europe. Dressed French mannequin dolls were sent far and wide for dressmakers to copy and one aspect of progress was the extension of decently surfaced highways. (Ref. 68)

The larger towns continued to have fairs and sometimes the latter simply took over the former. The modern day "rock" concerts may have been foreshadowed by some of these. At times 50,000 people would invade a town and it took all the police available to keep a semblance of order. "Fairs meant noise, tumult, music, popular rejoicing, the world turned upside down, disorder”8. At about the same time there were allegedly 91,000 persons without homes, except temporary shacks, and without visible means of support. (Ref. 69) There was a huge volume of road transport as well as canal traffic. The waterway network was incomplete, requiring many portages. Between the Lyons and the Rhone rivers alone some 400 to 500 oxen teams were employed permanently.

But to return to government affairs, when Louis XV matured he was more concerned with chasing women than government and continued the "Grand Monarchy", oblivious to the restless ideas developing in the populous. For at least a decade of his tenure, France was in essence ruled by his mistress, Mme. de Pompadour, born Jeanne Poisson and one of the most remarkable women of history. She had an extensive influence on French and European art as well as government and it was the period when French influence reached the peak of its effect on European civilization. Pompadour helped pave the way for the ultimate expulsion of the Jesuits from France and played a part in the Seven Years War. In that encounter, France helped Austria, on the losing side, and due to its extension in North America, France lost Canada to England and also lost territory in India. That was the time of the Swiss Rousseau, who did much of his writing in France, eulogizing the life of primitive man and it was also the period of Voltaire, the great Mocker, born Francois Marie Arouet, playwright, poet, historian, philosopher and confidant of kings and Voltaire actually spent some time in the Bastille because of a poem he wrote about the Regent and his daughter, the Duchess de Berri, But there is much misconception about the Bastille. It was actually a luxurious prison and incarceration there carried no particular dishonor. Most prisoners were aristocrats or gentlemen, who were treated there according to their rank. (Ref. 71) Other famous men of the century included Boucher, known for his nude paintings, Chardin, who depicted a still healthy France in labor and family life and Quentin de La Tour, who painted the leading personalities of the age. Charles Louis de Montesquieu was a powerful novelist, influencing religion and government. Denis Diderot and D'Alembert published Encyclopedie, in 1750. This taught Europe the meaning of such things as "rights", authority", "liberty", "equality", etc., and gave a tremendous storehouse of knowledge.

From the military standpoint perhaps nothing was more important to France than the development in the middle of the century, by Jean Maritz and his son, of the technique of casting cannon as a solid piece of metal and then boring out the barrel. The advantages of these guns, with straight and uniform bores, were enormous; Safety, accuracy, lightness (less thickness and thus more maneuverability) and reliability were all enhanced. The closer fit of cannonball to gun tube also meant less "windage" allowance and a smaller powder charge could be used to obtain even greater velocity. Using these features, Jean Baptiste Vacquette de Gribeaval created a powerful field artillary previously unknown in Europe. (Ref. 72)

A thumb-nail sketch of life in France before the revolution may be of value. One basic conflict involved the effort of philosophers and others to end ecclesiastical control over education. The great majority of the peasants could not read and even in the colleges the curriculum paid little attention to advances of knowledge; studies were almost entirely religious. The French Revolution can be traced back to the ambitious absurdities of Monarchy, but also to the revolt of reason against Catholic Christianity as it existed then in the nation. Although the lower classes, still dominated by the church, led moral lives for the most part, this was not true in the aristocracy. Adultery was usual, as a substitute for divorce. Children were seldom seen by their aristocratic parents; men were slaves to women, women to fashion, and fashion was determined by couturiers. The French language had now become the second language of every educated European. Frederick the Great used it regularly, except to his troops. Gibbon wrote his first books in French. (Ref. 73) Between 1715 and 1771, French foreign trade, previously very low, increased eightfold. (Ref. 74) By the end of the century there was no shortage of money, at least in some parts of France. In Marseilles, for example, men who offered money at 5% found few takers. Of course in France, even at this late period, merchants who borrowed money were looked at with some suspicion. (Ref. 75)

In the reign of Louis XVI, in 1789, the king's treasury was empty, however, in spite of high taxes, which were born by the middle class and peasants and the king found it necessary to call a National Assembly in an effort to find new sources of money. The Assembly traditionally was composed of nobles, clergy and the "third estate" (middle class), each group to have, in effect, one vote. Since it was apparent that the non-tax paying nobles and clergy could thus dominate the assembly, the third estate withdrew, held their own meeting and vowed to give France a constitution and a reform administration. Mobs in Paris took up the new cause and storming the Bastille to obtain arms, originally just to protect themselves, they more or less inadvertently started the French Revolution - a revolution of the "common man" against the monarchy, the nobles and the clergy. From 1789 to 1791 the revolution held its own and France was a limited monarchy with the king kept virtually a prisoner in a diminished state in the Tuileries, while the National Assembly, now reorganized as to voting privileges, ruled the country with relative peace. The Assembly instituted reforms in the penal code, stopped heresy persecutions, opened the army ranks to all, while arranging a state administration for the church. The heads of the church were prohibited from being members of the Assembly, however, and this actually weakened the central government. One of the great, farsighted statesmen of that period was Mirabeau, but unfortunately he died in 1791 and extremists then began to take control.

In that same year of 1791 the royal family escaped and tried to join a loyal army on the east border, but they were identified and returned to Paris under guard. The extremist Jacobins - Robespierre, Danton and Marat - now began to dominate French affairs, with their advanced ideas. Robespierre was a disciple of Rousseau and himself a lawyer; Danton was a lawyer; and Marat was a scientist and medical man of sorts. The mobs of the streets absorbed their radical ideas. At the same time, France declared war on Austria for a strange mixture of reasons and then Prussia declared war on France "to restore the monarchy". The Jacobin "commune" imprisoned King Louis XVI and reconvened the Assembly to frame a constitution. With the Prussians advancing, however, the mobs took over, emptied the prisons and a general slaughter began. A French army stopped the Prussians at Valmy, but the bloody fighting on the streets of Paris continued. The National Convention proclaimed France a republic and in a few months Louis was beheaded. Wild with success the mobs formed armies dedicated to "republicanizing" all Europe and while singing the Marseillaise they spread out to Brussels, Holland, Savoy, Switzerland and south Germany and they declared war on England. Under their new general, Napoleon Bonaparte, a brilliant young artillery officer, the republican armies fought forces of Savoy and Austria in 1796 and won most of northern Italy. In addition, however, war continued at home between the republicans and the loyalists and the double war provided the fear and panic that made it easy for the Jacobins9 to institute the reign of terror. While the Constituent Assembly had been discussing the Declaration of the rights of man, food crises and food riots occupied most of the common people. While a construction laborer earned 18 sous a day, his wife had to pay 14 1/2 sous for a 4 pound loaf of bread. This has ever been perhaps both the cause and the result of revolution. (Ref. 76) Attempts of the monarchy to use government troops against civilian crowds created an awkward situation, as a volley of muskets at close range was murderous and there was yet no other method of crowd control. The French custom of having aristocratic officers, who traditionally kept considerable distance from their men made it easy for the non-coms and regular soldiers to rebel and support the new regime against the old. After Napoleon took control, enlistment in the army was an escape from the very high unemployment which was part of the over-population problem of the country. (Ref. 77)

All royalists were eventually slaughtered and Robespierre ruled with blood, consumed by a passion for a new order of life. He attempted to equalize property and abolish profit. Divorce was made easy and illegitimacy was approved. A new calendar was made. But somewhere in all this Robespierre became insane and was finally killed by his own group. The terror came to an end after 4,000 people had been executed. A new constitution of 1795 provided that France should be ruled by a two-house legislature and five executives known as Directors. A rapid recovery of market-regulated economic activity took place.

After his Italian victories, Bonaparte took an army to the Mediterranean, invaded and initially conquered a part of Egypt. He did this by making the Directory believe that he was indirectly attacking England by breaking their lifeline, but it is probable that the real reason for that peculiar move was locked into Napoleon's own dream of empire. He took scholars and scientists with him and these men did start the science of Egyptology, initiate the breaking of the old hieroglyphics' code and made some striking reforms in Egyptian public health. A combination of some reinforcement Turkish armies and a British fleet under Lord Nelson cut off Napoleon's ships and forces, however, and only he managed to escape to France at the end of 1799. In spite of leaving his men behind, he still managed to arrive as a hero, took over the Directory and conferred the administrative power to three consuls.

The French Revolution brought down the European Old Regime. Neither the previously existing radical ideas nor new technical processes could have transformed European society so rapidly and so fundamentally. In the last decades of the old regime, Russia and eastern Europe were drawing abreast of the political organization of other European states and were on the verge of tipping the scales eastward. The revolution changed this drift. Of course it was costly. Approximately 600,000 French soldiers died between 1792 and 1799, the survivors remaining outside France, living on plunder.

At the end of the century several great scientists emerged in spite of the turmoil. Laennec developed the stethoscope, Pierre Simon Laplace was a great astronomer and statesman and Lavoisier worked out a new theory of combustion and conservation of matter in chemical reactions while repeating many of Priestley's oxygen experiments with a better understanding of their meaning. Theophile de Bordeu held that the stomach, heart and brain each secreted a material to the blood stream necessary for health and thus became known as a pioneer in endocrinology. Dentistry became a separate, true profession with the work of Pierre Fauchard. His publication The Surgeon Dentist became a standard text for generations. (Ref. 79)

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

At the beginning of the century Holland built ships for all of Europe and we have seen how Peter the Great of Russia not only went there to personally learn shipbuilding but then transported a number of Hollanders to Russia to establish shipyards there. In 1717 with 600,000 people10, Amsterdam was the second largest city in Europe. (Ref. 80) It was a beautiful city but had one bad district, the Jordaan in the southwest, where foundations were poor and canals too narrow. Jewish immigrants (Marranos from Portugal and Spain) and French Huguenots all congregated there. (Ref. 81) The great Amsterdam Exchange Building was finished in the preceding century and now up to 4,500 people were said to "crush" inside about noon every day. It was the busiest exchange in Europe, while the city, itself, was the center of the Amsterdam-London-Paris-Geneva banking supremacy. (Ref. 82)

William of Orange, also king of England, died in 1702 without children and that ended the direct line of the House of Orange. The office of stadtholder and commander-in chief was allowed to pass into obeyance and Marlborough of England was appointed Deputy Captain-General of Holland. In 1704, with Holland's consent, that Duke of Marlborough penetrated Germany clear to the Danube just north of Munich, with British paid soldiers. At that point he joined forces with armies of Eugene of Savoy and Austria. The purpose was to strike at Bavaria, which was then an ally of France, and then take Vienna. In the great battle of Blenheim, the French lost 40,000 men and the terror of the French armies was broken. At home the Dutch Republic finally succumbed under the financial burden of protecting itself during the coalition wars against Louis XIV. Bearing the lion's share of the Anglo-Dutch army between 1689 and 1713, it had to abandon naval superiority to the English. After the Peace of Utrecht (1713) England reaped the profits of the opening up of Spanish America and the Dutch sank to the level of a second rate power. Again in 1743, however, the Hollanders had to join England and Austria against Russia and France, because of direct threats by France in the Austrian Netherlands. Holland's small population and scant natural resources were inadequate to support the status of a great power for long. By 1784 there was a three-way struggle going on in Holland for control. The middle class and the patrician families, who controlled the Estates General, were trying to eliminate a great part of the traditional powers of the stadtholder. In 1787 Prussian troops intervened and restored the stadtholder to even greater powers than before. (Ref. 84)

When the French revolutionists moved into Holland, however, Dutch independence was lost as the French took Amsterdam (1795) while the Dutch fleet was captured while it lay frozen in harbor ice.

The greatest intellectual achievement in Holland in this century was probably in medicine. The medical school at Leiden had two of the great teachers of the times in Hermann Boerhaave and the anatomist Bernhard Siegfried Albinus. Their students became the leaders in the profession all over Europe. (Ref. 85)

The Treaty of Utrecht, which ended the War of the Spanish Succession in 1713 also ended a long series of Spanish-French wars over Belgium and that country then went under Austrian Habsburg rule as part of the Holy Roman Empire. Economic recovery followed so that by 1787 the people felt strong enough to revolt against Emperor Joseph II and the Republic of the United Belgian Provinces was formed in 1790. In the same year, however, the emperor re-conquered the country. After the French Revolution, Belgium was incorporated into France (1799) in spite of resistance of Hanoverian, Prussian, Austrian, and Hessian forces.

BRITISH ISLES

ENGLAND AND WALES

The population of England and Wales grew to over 9 million by the end of this century. (Ref. 86) With the death of King William in 1702, Mary's sister Anne reigned until 1714 in a time known as the Augustan Age of England, because of the literature of Pope, Swift, Addison and others. This was also the time when the Duke of Marlborough defeated a French army in part of the War of the Spanish Succession, in which England gained Gibralter, Nova Scotia and Newfoundland. Parliament became the supreme power in the state and on Anne's death, decided to pick a less competent monarch, choosing the Elector of Hanover, George I, who could speak no English and would not learn to do so. He spent most of his time in Hanover and there was no love shared between him and the English people. The Great Northern War was in progress and George I decided that Sweden must make peace with Denmark and the German states so that then they could drive Russia from the Baltic. After English money and the Royal Navy had induced a Swedish-Danish peace treaty on July 3, 1720, a large armada was sent into the Baltic, but never did actually engage in battle. The British involvement faded when the South Sea Company and its stock collapsed, as will be described in a later paragraph. It was at that time that Sir Robert Walpole, the Whig leader and the first prime minister and master politician, used adroit maneuvers to solve the financial crisis. (Ref. 87) The monarchy and the House of Commons both lost power at that time as the House of Lords ruled England.

There was a period of increased overseas expansion in America (Canada) and India as the result of England's participation and France's losses in the Seven Years War. Winston Churchill (Ref. 88) insists on calling this the First World War because there were sea battles with France in all parts of the globe, as well as land battles in Germany and in America. Although George II had taken over the throne in 1727 and was more active in British affairs than his father had been, England's leader was William Pitt the Elder, Secretary of State, who ran the war from his office in London. Although having initial losses in America to the combined forces of the French and their Indian allies, by 1759 the British navy had captured Guadeloupe, the richest island in the west Indies, the army of Amherst had taken Ticonderoga and Fort Niagra and the combined services had obtained the key fortress of Quebec. In another year, the French were out of North America. King George II died in 1760 and George III preferred the minister Bute over Pitt. France, seeing that Pitt was losing influence, made a new alliance with Spain, hoping to again have a chance in America. Upon Pitt's resignation, England declared war on Spain and further victories resulted, including the taking of Manila. At the Peace of Paris in 1763, British acquisitions were considerable, although the naval power of France had been left untouched and she retained bases in the Gulf of St. Lawrence. (Ref. 89)

At home important changes took place in agriculture, farming and transportation. Rural life in England up to about 1715 was very much as it had been for a thousand years, each household being a self -contained economic unit. But things changed as a factory system made England the workshop of the world and machines began to take the place of workers. The steam engine, invented by James Watts of Glasgow in 1760, was of new design, having the piston driven by live steam. That, with the use of coke in the steel industry and the development of steamships and railways, all had a part in the Industrial Revolution. Wood had up to that time been the major fuel, but by the end of the century only four of the original 69 great forests of England remained and there was great need of a newer and cheaper fuel. Coal was the answer and new mining methods could be developed which in turn led to better production of steel. Iron smelting was changed by Abraham Darby, who mixed sulfur with Shropshire valley coal, making coke and it was this that let England become the world's leading iron manufacturer after 1760. (Ref. 90) These changes had not come overnight. For example, a blast furnace built in Dolgyne in Wales in 1717 was not fired until 5 years later when enough charcoal had been accumulated for 361/2 weeks work. Newcommen invented the atmospheric steam engine in 1711, but only one was in operation in England 30 years later. Thousands of factors hindered progress. What would happen to the labor force when machines took over? (Ref. 91) In 1728 the first steel rolling mill was set up and in 1740 Benjamin Huntsman invented the crucible process for making high-grade steel. This union of coal and iron made the great machines of the Industrial Revolution possible. (Ref. 92) Similarly in textile production, there was John Kay's "flying shuttle" (1733) and Lewis Paul's spinning machine (1738) which in this era revolutionized that field. The Industrial Revolution began in England and occurred only in England in this century. In the reign of George III the structure of British economy and society in general underwent profound change, manifested first by the tremendous output of coal, pig-iron, engineering products and textiles, as already noted. But the economic growth was furthered by the fortunate availability of cheap water transport in inland waterways11 for the newly manufactured heavy, bulky goods and a shipping fleet of 658,000 tons, which was to triple within the next 50 years. (Ref. 93) McNeill (Ref. 94) reminds us of a fact of ten overlooked in that the iron and steel production in Great Britain was basically stimulated by the governments' need for naval cannon and other military hardware. In the decade after 1794 the British government purchased about 1/5 of the ironmasters' products12. In essentially the same period, the Royal Navy made two important technical advancements - copper sheathing for ships' bottoms and the use of short-barreled, large caliber guns called "carronades", which were extremely effective at short ranges. Another plus for England was that except for two minor revolts (Jacobite), she fought her 18th century wars abroad and left the homeland free for industrial development. Her foreign trade trebled between 1702 and 1772. (Ref. 95)

Perhaps the most fundamental difference between social patterns of Britain and the continent was the greater prestige and autonomy which merchants and financiers enjoyed in the former. The interpenetration of the landed nobility and the merchant class in England resulted in availability of large amounts of capital and a remarkable economic growth. Toleration of religious nonconformity also helped. The liberties of Englishmen, expressed in chronic effervescence of parliamentary (and extraneous) debate, confirmed by economic and imperial success, contrasted the deferential obedience demanded by European monarchs. (Ref. 98)

One must not assume, however, that there were no troubles. England created two societies, remote from each other. The first was the society made up of modest country gentlemen and the other was the urban conglomerate, with plenty of animal spirits and not much civilization. (Ref. 99) With somewhere between 750,000 and 860,000 inhabitants London was the largest city in Europe13 but a considerable part of the population was packed into slums filthy with garbage and offal, breeding a hundred diseases. In some sections nearly 50% lived by charity, theft or prostitution. 64% of the children died before reaching 10 years of age. There was not a single bathing establishment in London, even in 1800. Education was very spotty and the great majority of Englishmen could not read or write. Drinking and gambling were rampant with the typical London man consuming a quart of beer or ale a day. 5 1/2 million gallons of gin were consumed in Britain in 1735. Soldiers were all given alcohol before battle and became habitual drinkers. An English military doctor of 1763 even felt that wine and alcohol helped to suppress certain diseases and were indispensable for the good health of the troops. In spite of that, improved farming machinery and methods such as fallowing led to improved diets and then to a population increase. (Ref. 100) In the 1770s some 8,000,000 pounds14 of tea were consumed in England and by the end of the century the English were consuming 2 pounds per person, per annum. Catsup (or ketchup) came to England via India from Chinese immigrants to Southeast Asia. The word comes from the Siamese Kachiap. (Ref. 101)

On the government level piracy was still tolerated and the slave trade by English ships still flourished. And even as now, the lawmakers of England had been so eager to protect the individual from the state that many worried that they were failing to protect society from the individual. The machinery of enforcement broke down before the spread and organization of crime. As in France, a stock exchange in London was established at the turn of the century and again, as in France, there was a market crash in 1720, as the South Sea Company went into bankruptcy.

In some degree history does repeat itself. Just as today labor fears the increase in automation, so in the 18th century the development of machines led to serious labor reactions. We have mentioned John Kay's invention of the "flying shuttle" which doubled the weaving output and increased quality, but now we must add that angry mobs broke up his house and he died in poverty, in France. Similarly, James Hargreaves of the spinning jenny fame, had his house sacked, his first machine burned and he also had to flee. (Ref. 104) Still another phenomenon appeared that remains with us today - bitter arguments over the mounting national debt. The entire economic system depended on the "credit-worthiness" of the state and it could continue to exist only if Parliament created new sources of revenue earmarked for regular payment of the interest on the debt. As a result certain people, land-owners particularly, had high taxes levied, while others, money lenders, renters, and business men, whose incomes were not taxed, gained whenever the state borrowed more money and the interest rate was raised. Braudel (Ref. 105) says that this latter group actually promoted the 1739 war with Spain.

As to philosophy and religion, Britain preceded continental Europe both in the collapse of the old feudal system and the near collapse of the Christian religion. The Established Church was rent by all varieties of dissenting sects and perhaps hit hardest of all by the campaign of the Deists to reduce Christianity to a belief in God and immortality only.

Thomas Woolston, Matthew Tendal, Conyers Middleton and others wrote, spoke and ridiculed. The upper classes were predominately counter-religious and the lower classes in great part had no religion at all, even though there were state penalties for being absent from church, a statute seldom enforced. Not more than 5 or 6 members of the House of Commons went to church. The Anglican clergy seldom mentioned heaven or hell and stressed social virtues rather than other-worldliness. In this setting flowered Methodism, founded by John and Charles Wesley, with a few friends, especially George Whitefield, as they organized a little group of 15 students and teachers at Oxford, resolved to practice Christianity with "Methodical" thoroughness. All were devout Anglicans and most became Anglican clergy. On a trip to Georgia as a missionary, John was impressed by the piety and creed of some Moravian Brothers and soon adopted some of their intensity and ideas. In the next few years, Whitefield's and John Wesley's emotional oratory and preaching and Charles' hymns took over lower class England for Methodism. They preached essentially the old Puritan Creed with the message of sin and repentance, a faith based on fear, not love, but they gave an ethical code that shared in the moral rehabilitation of England in the 2nd half of the century. By the time of John Wesley's death there were 79,000 followers in England and 40,000 in the United States. By 1957 there were 40,000,000 Methodists all over the world. Methodism placed all hopes on faith in the great conflict between reason and faith. (Ref. 106) By the end of the 18th century there were 20,000 Jews in London, hated and given little or no opportunities. (Ref. 107)

Literature and music continued to flourish. In addition to the early century writers mentioned at the beginning of this section, there were Henry Fielding, who wrote the well known Tom Jones in 1730, Thomas Gray, known particularly for his "Elegy in a Country Courtyard", the caustic Samuel Johnson, and the transplanted Scottish philosopher and historian, David Hume. We should not omit mention of Handel's music15.

The first medical school in London was founded by William Hunter, interested primarily in dentistry and obstetrics. His delivery of various members of the royal family helped to raise obstetrics from its medieval obscurity. William's brother, John Hunter, was even more famous as a surgeon and was a student of two other famous surgeons, William Cheselden and Percival Pott. John Hunter developed a method of closing off an aneurysm, thus preventing the necessity for amputation of limbs of thousands of soldiers and civilians. The surgeons finally achieved equality with their traditional rivals, the physicians. Most prominent among the latter was William Heberden, who described angina pectoris and nodules of osteoarthritis of the fingers, which still bear his name. The most important drug development was digitalis, used for "dropsy" by William Withering in 1785. James Lind, a British naval surgeon, proved the efficacy of fresh lemons and oranges in curing scurvy in 1753, but the Admiralty did not act until 1795 and even then used cheap, West Indies' limes (rather than the Mediterranean variety), and these lacked the necessary Vitamin C. Thus, scurvy outbreaks continued on British ships for another 100 years, although the mortality rate did decrease. (Ref. 108, 109)

In spite of the medical advances small-pox remained widespread and highly virulent, with mortality ranging from 15 to 30%. Throughout this century there were only 9 years in which small-pox deaths in London did not exceed 1,000 and in 1759 they reached 3,296. One-third of the inhabitants of England bore pit marks of that disease. The idea of inoculation by pus from a true small-pox lesion was brought from Turkey by Lady Mary Wortley Montagu and was used for a short time, but was then dropped as too dangerous. It was at the end of the century in 1798 that Edward Jenner published his famous paper on the use of cow-pox for vaccination. Typhus fever occurred sporadically in mild epidemics. Scarlet fever increased in incidence and by 1750 one out of every 30 cases died. A severe epidemic of that occurred in 1777-1778. In spite of all this, life expectancy of 35 years in England was much better than the overall world expectancy of 25 to 30 years. (Ref. 110, 111, 112, 113)

The War of American Independence was precipitated by the poor policies of ministers such as Grenville and Charles Townshend, but George III's responsibility for the final breach is not to be denied. (Ref. 114) Simple in tastes and unpretentious in manner, his mind was still Hanoverian, with an inveterate obstinacy and stubbornness. He could not understand those who feared the consequences of a policy of coercion. Edmund Burke, Secretary to the Marquis of Rockingham, brought the Whig party to stand for conciliation of the colonies as well as relaxation of restraints on the trade of his native Ireland, but the king was not convinced and after 13 months he got rid of Rockingham's government. William Pitt, now ill, went along with the king and Townshend returned to power, with the final result being war. As it progressed the British General Burgoyne's defeat in October of 1777 at Saratoga influenced France, supposedly neutral up until that time, to ally itself with the colonists. The French brought their intact navy up to the line and started a war of revenge against Britain to overcome the sting of the recent Seven Years War. (Ref. 115) The revolt of the colonies had shattered England's complacency and the word "reform" was in the air. William Pitt the Younger came to power at age 24 in 1783 and in the next 10 years he tried mightily to stay clear of Europe's upheavals, while he improved the financial, administrative and supply organization of the Royal Navy.

Scotland

The death of the widowed King William left the crowns of both England and Scotland to his sister-in-law Anne. Under some duress by restrictive trade decrees against Scotland, in 1707 a treaty was concluded producing a formal union of the two countries, with a common parliament. But the English continued to harass the Scots.

A Scots proposal to build roads into the Highlands to exploit their great timber resources was rejected by the English, as they continued to import wood from America. English coal could be exported duty free to Ireland, but not to Scotland. Poverty remained endemic but cultivation of the potato on the Stirling plain after 1739 and an increase in the breeding of black cattle began to offer hope for recovery. In the Highlands a warrior society still existed, tribal at the bottom, almost feudal at the top, all using their ancient Gaelic language and existing on the black cattle economy.

The Act of Union joining the two countries did not prevent an occasional resurgence of Scottish national pride and attempts at forcing a new Stuart king on to the throne of Britain. Bonnie Prince Charlie, Catholic son of James III, spent his life trying, with interval help from France and various Scot clans, and he even invaded England with an army of about 10,000 in 1745 - the Jacobite Rebellion. It all came to naught and after the Highlanders' defeat at Culloden, Gaelic Scotland was broken, as the clans were dissolved, the bagpipe banned in war and the kilt outlawed. At the end of that f inal battle, the English killed all the wounded on the field, shot and hung fugitives and burned houses. Many Celtic Scots emigrated to Nova Scotia (New Scotland). (Ref. 116) In spite of that bloodbath, it is amazing that trade, industry and arts made a rapid and substantial recovery. At the end of the century the economy was helped as iron foundries started up, with contracts from the British navy. (Ref. 117)

Every parish in Scotland tried to set up a school for its children and 4 universities offered the best education in the British Isles. Another student of Boerhaave of Leiden (see page 969), Alexander Monro, returned to his native Scotland to give new life to the ancient University of Edinburgh, which became the center of medical instruction for the English speaking world. (Ref. 118) This century has been called the era of "Scottish Enlightenment", with the philosophers David Hume and Thomas Reid, historian William Robertson, political economist Adam Smith, novelist Sir Walter Scott, who was born and educated in Edinburgh, and finally Robert Burns (1759-1796), who wrote some in English, but whose poems in Scottish have brought him everlasting fame. (Ref. 119)

IRELAND

Ireland had a far different situation from Scotland. As a result of repeated victories by English armies over native revolts, a code of laws had been set up that chained the Irish in body and soul. (Ref. 120) The landowners were almost all Protestants, most of them actually living in England and those who resided locally isolated themselves from the hostility of their surroundings with drink, quarreling, dueling and gambling. The Established (Anglican) Church in Ireland included only about 1/7 of the people, but was supported by tithes from the peasantry, almost all Catholics. The latter were excluded from public office, from all professions except medicine, could purchase no land or hold any valuable lease. Emigration continued with about 8,000 Irish going to America each year in the 8th decade. (Ref. 121)

At the end of the century in 1798 a revolt broke out again in the country, which was put down by Lord Cornwallis, in spite of French assistance to the Irish. (Ref. 122) The

British leaders then decided to make Ireland- a part of the United Kingdom. An Act of Union was passed in 1800, which made all of the British Isles a single entity of Great Britain. The social pattern in Ireland resembled that of eastern Europe and the southern American colonies, in having a privileged body of landowners, who shared European civilization and a culturally deprived, psychologically alienated mass of agricultural laborers. (Ref. 123) One helpful feature at the century end was a rise in grain prices in England, which made the Irish potato culture more profitable and necessary. (Ref. 124)

SCANDINAVIA

Coming from England, the potato reached Scandinavia in this century. (Ref. 125)

NORWAY

Still under Danish rule, Norway was rapidly developing a sea trade and shipping industry, with particularly close commercial ties with England. Norway's chief contribution to the literature of the period was Ludvig Holberg, who wrote a number of comedies to be played in the first theater in Denmark.

SWEDEN

Since Sweden was occupied almost entirely in the early century with war, we shall first continue our special section on that war.

After termination of the Great Northern War, political power in Sweden shifted to the lower nobility and the rich merchants, who were prospering in trade and industry, exploiting the mineral resources of the country. The parliament became the center of political life, but it soon took on dishonest ways and fell in prestige so that Gustavus III became an absolute ruler once more in a golden interlude of intellectualism and art (1771-1792). In the meantime the Hats, a political party under French influence, had provoked another war against Russia, but after two years Sweden was again the loser and had lost still more territory in Finland.

Great men of Sweden in this century were Karl von Linn (Linnaeus), who established the modern binomial system of naming plants and animals and Anders Celsius, astronomer at the University of Uppsala. He also devised the centigrade scale thermometer.

DENMARK

Some repetition of the material concerning the Great Northern War will be apparent, in this section. In 1699 Frederick IV, aged 28 years, had ascended to the throne of Denmark and with Peter the Great of Russia, aged 27 years and Augustus of Poland, 29, formed an alliance to obtain revenge for the actions of Sweden's 17 year old king, Karl XII. On the alliance's declaration of war, however, Karl immediately attacked Denmark, starting the Great Northern War. Sweden easily won those initial battles and continued conquering throughout eastern Europe for the next 10 years, as we have noted above.

After Karl was defeated at Poltava, however,-Frederick once more led Denmark and Norway into war on land and sea and the final peace did not come until 1721. The European powers at the peace table would not return both sides of the Sound to Denmark, because of the old grievance of the Sound Dues and they let Sweden keep Scania.

Frederick IV encouraged intellectual life, subsidizing the Norwegian poet and playwright, Ludvig Holberg. With budding intellectual life, industry also developed, including the still famous Royal Copenhagen Porcelain factory. After Frederick's death in 1728, a great fire swept Copenhagen in the reign of Christian VI. The latter was followed by Frederick V, who married the daughter of Britain's George II. Upon Frederick V's death in 1765 his mentally ill son became Christian VII, married to Caroline Matilda, sister of George III of England. Christian's physician, Struensee, became an all-powerful minister for a short period, but Andreas Peter Bernstorff replaced him as chief minister in 1773. After 1784 Christian's son and successor Frederick VI acted as regent and put through wide reforms, including the liberation of peasants from serfdom, clearing the way for the breaking up of large land-holdings and allowing improvements in farming methods. In 1792 Denmark became the first European country to prohibit the slave trade. Of interest is the fact that it was a Dane, Vitus Bering, who explored the northern seas and oceans for the Russian navy in the first half of the century. (Ref. 126, 127)

FINLAND

Sweden continued to rule Finland, but in 1713-1714, as a part of the Great Northern War, Russians conquered the entire south coast of Finland, using newly made galleys some 80 to 100 feet long with a single mast and sail and numerous benches for oarsmen. They moved in and out along the shore, out of reach of the Swedish men-of-war. Occasionally, when necessary, the galleys would grapple and use hand to hand battle on the decks of the great ships of the line. During this short period much of the Finnish population fled to the Aland Islands, lying between Finland and Sweden. Those islands, however, were soon also infiltrated by the Russian galleys. In the end, as noted above, Finland proper was returned to the control of Sweden. The Finns themselves were basically poor peasant farmers. Their houses and other farm buildings were wooden huts with little in the way of accessories. At the end of the century Russia's continued push against its frontiers resulted in a recurrent invasion into Finland (1790) at the expense of the Swedes. (Ref. 128, 129)

OVERSEAS SCANDINAVIAN CENTERS

In Norway's "colony" of Iceland, there was a severe cold period, with glaciers covering more of the land so that depopulation occurred. It was mentioned in the introductory material in Chapter 3 (FIFTH AND FOURTH MILLENIA B.C.) that Iceland sat on the mid-Atlantic ridge, which marks the junction of two crustal tectonic plates. Beginning in 1724 volcanic fissures opened and spewed the spectacular "Myvatn Fires" over a period of 5 years, pouring lava and destruction over a large area. (Ref. 130)

EASTERN EUROPE

The 18th century European surge in population did not put as much strain on the food supply system in eastern Europe as it did in the west, where easily used land had already been under cultivation for some time. In the east there was still much untilled expanse which could be converted to crops without costly capital improvements. As men became more abundant it was also easier for Poland and Russia16 to recruit more soldiers. Russia, as a state on the margin of Europe, like Great Britain, was able to increase control of resources more rapidly than was possible in the more crowded center of Europe. (Ref. 131)

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

It will be recalled that the close of the last century saw almost the entire southern shore of the Baltic in Swedish hands, with a debilitated Swedish army in Livonia, after defeating the Russians at Narva and Poland as an independent kingdom, ruled by the Saxon Elector, Augustus. Having put what remained of his army in Livonia in winter quarters, Karl XII of Sweden obtained 10,000 fresh recruits from the mother country in the spring of 1701 and then marched with a total of 24,000 men south across the West Divina River, near Riga, to defeat a Saxon army of 9,000 plus an additional cadre of 4,000 Russians. Because Karl could not move his cavalry across the river, which was some 650 yards wide, the Saxons, although badly beaten and battered, retreated and got away. Karl then decided on total defeat of Augustus, before invading Russia. Up to that time Augustus had fought only as a Saxon and not as King- of Poland. Karl wanted the Polish Diet to depose Augustus II and elect a new king, so he waited patiently for that action. But it did not come and by that time it was too late in the year for war in that cold climate, so he wintered his troops in Courland. In January the Swedish army shif ted south into Lithuania and in the spring of 1702 started the fight against Poland and Augustus II, which was to last for 6 years. Behind the Swedes, Russian soldiers with Calmuck and Cossack horsemen eventually completely overran and devastated Livonia and the peasants were being bought and sold as serf s. Among the prisoners taken was Martha Skavronskaya, a 17 year old, illiterate girl who would join the house of Prince Menshikov, become Peter I's mistress, then wife and finally the ruler of Russia as Catherine I.

By the end of 1704, after taking the Swedish held fort at the junction of Lake Lagoda with the Neva, the Russians had taken both Narva in Estonia and Dorpat in Livonia, giving Russia an entrance to the Baltic. (Ref. 132) Meanwhile Karl XII had finally convinced the Polish to dethrone the Saxon, Augustus, and under Swedish guns Stanislaus Leszczynski was crowned King of Poland at Warsaw (not at Cracow, as tradionally). The Swedish army then turned toward Russia (1705) while Augustus, disguised, went by a circuitous route through Hungary to join Czar Peter and the Russian forces. In the first battle at Grodno Karl forced the Russians to retreat in disarray, but he could not follow because of a spring thaw and its mud. The eventual defeat of the Swedish forces at Poltava, however, has been described above in the special section on THE GREAT NORTHERN WAR.

We have also previously reported that Karl Xll obtained a new army of 18,000 men in 1712, landing in Swedish Pomerania with the intent to again attack Russia. A Danish fleet caught a convoy of supply ships, sending 30 of them to the bottom of the Baltic.

The Swedish General Stenbock wheeled and attacked the Danes on the west, winning the battle but losing 6,000 fighting men. He then marched on west toward Hamburg. At Altona he demanded 100,000 thalers for expenses and when the town could raise only 42,000, his men burned the community to the ground.

At what might be called the half-way point of the Great Northern War, after the Swedish defeat at Poltava in Russia, Poland became in effect a possession of Russia and Augustus II was put back on the throne. Peter I also arranged a marriage between Duke Frederick William, of Courland (a nephew of Frederick of Prussia) to his niece Anna (daughter of his half-brother Ivan). She soon became Duchess of Courland, as her young husband died. We shall note later that she was also called back to Russia in 1730 to be Empress Anna Ivanovna. Also, in this interim, Peter's son Alexis married the daughter of the Duke of Wolfenbuettel at the castle of the Queen of Poland in 1711. (Ref. 133)

In about 1733 Russian and Saxon troops put young Augustus III on the Polish throne. He had Austrian backing, but France, Spain and Sardinia took up arms in the so-called War of the Polish Succession, in favor of the deposed Stanislas Lesczynski. By 1738 Stanislas announced a renunciation of the throne and Poland had reached a point of real political decay. (Ref. 134) Rich nobles still wielded much power, however, and Prince Radziwill single-handedly raised his own army, equipped with artillery, in 1750. (Ref. 135) The body politic pulled itself together enough by 1764 upon the death of Augustus III, to elect Stanislas II Poniatowski as king, but Catherine II of Russia used religious divisions as a lever to foment more civil strife. In the resulting war of 1768-1774, the Turks decided to help Poland, but Russia still dominated and sliced off a portion of Poland (part of the first Polish partition) and destroyed the Turkish Mediterranean fleet at Chesme. In the midst of this was a Jewish persecution with thousands having to flee, some to England. (Ref. 136) To complete that first partition Prussia took an area of Poland between Danzig and Thorn, while Austria helped herself to a large area just south of Cracow. A second partition of Poland took place in 1787-92 and finally in 1795 all of Poland was gobbled up, with Austria taking Cracow, Prussia getting Warsaw and Russia occupying Vilna. On that occasion Catherine II of Russia was invited in by the greater nobles of Poland. Life in that country was bad and superstition great. The starving citizens of Kolberg would not touch a wagon load of potatoes sent to them by Frederick the Great in 1774. (Ref. 137) The peasants were subjected to the worst kind of serfdom. In Lower Silesia in 1.798 compulsory labor by peasants was unlimited - that is, they could be forced to work 7 days a week for an unlimited number of hours. Later in the century there was a tremendous "floating" population of runaway serfs, impoverished noblemen, indigent Jews and urban paupers, forming a sort of "anti-society". (Ref. 138)

The unfortunate history of Poland through the ages seems due to multiple factors, not the least of which was the constant antagonism between the nobility and the crown, often subjected to various foreign pressures. The Polish territory overlapped an area containing Russians in the east and an area containing Germans in the west. The country was still abundant in Jews but the majority of the people were Catholic. There were no great cities and little trade and actually very little central authority. An arm of Poland reached out to the sea at Danzig and this separated Prussia into two halves, annoying Frederick II. Internal weakness was caused by obsolete institutions and religious antagonism brought about by central intolerance to both Protestantism on the western borders and orthodoxy in the great Ukraine.

Map from Reference 97

The other Baltic states suffered about the same ultimate f ate as Poland. Latvia and Lithuania were divided along with Poland in the various partitions between 1772 and 1795. Estonia, devastated by Peter's armies was then ruled by Russia for the next 200 years, although the culture of the country remained Germanic. (Ref. 139, 140)

RUSSIA (Please see map in RUSSIA section, next chapter)

After his defeat by Swedish forces at Narva, Peter I immediately started to rebuild his army and equipment. When he had been in England, he had bought about 40,000 modern flintlocks with bayonets and he used those remaining after the Narva battle as models, constructing 6,000 in 1701 and turning out 40,000 a year by 1711. One-fourth of all the church bells in Russia were melted down to make new cannons, with 20 new ones available by May, 1701. In the next three years seven new iron works were developed beyond the Urals, using good ore, perhaps even better than Sweden's17. Peter received no help from Holland or the Habsburgs in this period, because they were involved with most of the rest of Europe in the War of the Spanish Succession. He did get some reassurance from his old ally, Augustus II of Poland. However, when the allies defeated Sweden, Russia got only Ingria and had to supply 15,000 to 20,000 infantrymen for the Saxons, besides paying Augustus a war subsidy of 100,000 rubles a year for 3 years.

During the 6 years that Karl XII of Sweden was fighting in Poland, Peter had some small military successes, including the standing off of a Swedish naval expedition at Archangel and some victories against the 7,800 Swedes left to hold Livonia, taking some Swedish prisoners back to Moscow and eventually completely destroying the rest of that Swedish army, using savage Kalmuch and Cossack horsemen. In 1702, with a fleet of small gun- boats built on the south shore of Lake Lagoda, the czar attacked a Swedish squadron of three brigantines and three galleys, forcing the Swedes to withdraw down the Neva River, leaving the great lake to the Russians. After similar attacks the Swedes also had to with- draw from Lake Peipus, only to return in 1703 and again be run out by the Russians.

Peter had gained his opening to the Baltic by taking Fort Noeteborg (renamed Schluesselburg) and he soon controlled the ancient area of Ingria, along with the area where he was soon to build a city, St. Petersburg, at the mouth of the Neva. That city is at the same latitude as Hudson's Bay and when built, New York was already 77 years old and Boston 73. The first digging for the new city was in May, 1702 on Hare Island. Although still occasionally under attack by Swedes, the new city received its f irst merchant ships for trade in 1703. The hardships of building a fortress and a city on the swamps were stupendous, requiring thousands of laborers, who were drafted from all parts of the empire

Cossacks, Siberians, Tatars, Finns and Russians. Scurvy, dysentery, malaria, etc. cut them down by the hundreds, perhaps overall some 30,000 dying. All the stone and most of the timber and all food was imported from inland. People, from nobles and merchants down to peasants, were forced there to live. Fires were common and the czar himself of ten led the firefighters. Floods were also frequent and devastating, with the entire town sometimes under water. In the area around St. Petersburg, most of the original Finns had been eliminated by war and plague18 and Peter gave their land to noblemen and officers who often then brought whole villages of peasants to live there.

The czar had to control Livonia and Estonia to safeguard his new city and to accomplish this while still administering the entire country meant that he had to travel constantly.

Except in winter, travel was extremely difficult and hazardous,- with rutted or muddy roads, worn out bridges, crude ferries and fords and few fresh horses. His whole concern was war and taxes to support war. The money came from an increasing number of state monopolies, with the state taking control of production and sale of innumerable commodities from alcohol to chessmen, salt and furs19. Many people revolted, some escaping to the north and east to join the "old Believers", others even organized true revolts, including a rebellion at Astrakhan and the uprising of the Bashkir (semi-orientals between the Volga and the Urals), as well as the Don Cossack revolt under Kondraty Bulavin. All were put down in one way or another, the latter one with the help of other loyal Cossacks under Hetman Maximov. For that, Maximov was later executed by Bulavin.

In the interval af ter Peter defeated the Swedish king at Narva and after the cessation of the War of the Spanish Succession, Peter tried to make deals with any and every European power for help against further Swedish advances, but he had no luck. And then Karl XII struck again with 26,000 of his own men and almost 42,000 men from Saxony, leaving the latter country in August of 1707, going through Protestant Silesia. Ahead of that army, however, in western Poland, Cossacks and Kalmuks had ridden, laying waste the countryside and poisoning the wells with dead, uncooperative Poles. All Russian soldiers were withdrawn from western Poland to a line near Minsk. Then, while waiting for Karl's forces, Peter married his Lithuanian, low-born mistress of many years, Martha Skavronskaya, who had taken the name Ekaterina (Catherine). Karl came relentlessly on through the winter over the frozen Vistula and soon captured Grodno, leaving Poland and entering Lithuania. Then the tides of war wavered toward one side and then the other, but gradually the battle lines shifted more southward towards the Ukraine and away from Moscow.

This brought up again the thorny question of the shif ting allegiances of the various Cossack and Ukranian peoples. The Hetman of one large group of Cossacks was Ivan Stepanovich Mazeppa, born in the then Polish sector of the Ukraine, well educated in Jesuit academies but orthodox in religion and at one time a page at the court of King Jan Casimir of Poland. Mazeppa had mixed loyalties, part to the new czar and part to his people, who had wanted full Ukrainian independence in order to avoid Russian taxes, conscription and requisitions. Finally the Hetman did betray Peter and went over to the side of the invading Swedes, whom he thought would win. But while Mazeppa was gone, Peter's forces slipped into the former's home city of Baturin and completely destroyed it, slaughtering 7,000 inhabitants, soldiers and civilians alike. Most of the Ukrainians then stood by the czar and the worst winter of history, which followed, dealt a devastating blow to the invading Swedes, with sentries freezing to death at their posts and overall, some 3,000 Swedes freezing to death, with many more seriously incapacitated by frost-bite. Still Karl XII would not give up, hoping to receive reinforcements and supplies from Poland and the Turks and/or the Crimean Tatars. None of this materialized although he did gain support through the dealings of Mazeppa, of the wild Zaporozhsky Cossacks, who lived on 13 fortified islands below the rapids of the vast Dnieper River, under their Hetman Gordeenko. These Cossacks had sufficient boats to transport 3,000 men across the great river in a single trip, but once again Peter got there first and destroyed all the boats and razed their island base.

As noted in previous sections, the decisive battle of the Great Northern War was fought in the summer of 1709 at Poltava in the Ukraine, in which an original army of 19,000 Swedes left 6,900 dead and wounded and had 2,760 taken prisoner, including some 560 officers in both groups. Russian losses were light. In that single battle, the Swedish invasion of Russia was terminated and the political axis of Europe was shifted, with a new balance of power, which carried over for the next three centuries. The last of the Swedish army was caught and surrendered some days later as it attempted a southern escape and Czar Peter then had 17,000 Scandinavian prisoners. They were treated well, with the officers given the same rank in the Russian army, where some served Russia on other fronts. Of the regular soldier prisoners, in time some 1,000 became painters, goldsmiths, tailors, shoemakers, woodsmen and teachers. When the final peace came in 1721, only 5,000 Swedes could be found who wanted to return to Sweden. In the meantime, King Karl XII escaped to Turkey.

St Petersburg continued to flourish, with Italian, French and German architects all leaving their marks, but it never escaped entirely from the sea, from which it was snatched, suffering complete flooding in 1715 and again in 1775. The common people in and about St. Petersburg were chief ly Finnish and while the women were chambermaids or cooks, the men were sledge drivers or snow and ice shovelers and ice-breakers on the Neva. Ice blocks supplied ice-houses on the ground floor of every large home. Even the lowest servant spoke Russian, German and Finnish, while the educated often spoke 8 or 9 languages. There were endless supply problems. While fish could be obtained from lakes Ladoga and Onega, sheep and cattle had to be brought from the Ukraine, the Don and the Volga regions or even from Turkey. (Ref. 142)

Peter, like other sovereigns of his day, had his many eccentricities, including the collection of giants and dwarfs. The Russian people of that time were crude, with continual drinking and fighting being their greatest entertainments, all under most unsanitary conditions. When they did bathe, they then ran out into the snow, like many Finns do yet today. Under Peter, Russia's past traditions disappeared; there were no more beards, caftans or female seclusions at the court; the Julian calendar was adopted and the alphabet simplified. Like Ivan the Terrible before him and Stalin afterwards, Peter's individual will effectually transformed Russian society and institutions within one quarter of a century. He transposed the serf system to new industries, with everyone working directly or indirectly for the state. (Ref. 143) Besides the westernization and naval development, men were elevated by merit and although old noble titles were not abolished, they no longer carried special privileges. He promoted mining and industry and an Academy of Science. One of his greatest accomplishments was a continuous waterway from the Caspian Sea via the Volga, Volga tributary, a small canal at Vyshny-Volochok20 to Lake Ladoga, the Neva River and then the Baltic. But Lake Ladoga weather and waves were of ten too much for flat-bottomed river barges, so later Peter started another canal at the south end in the marches of Ladoga, which was to be 70' wide, 16' deep and 66 miles long. It was not completed in Peter's life time.

Even after the Great Northern War was settled Peter's drive for conquest was not stilled and he started for the Caspian Sea, Persia and India as well as north and east to the Pacific. In 1724 the Danish born sea captain Vitus Bering, in Russian employ, led an expedition to what was subsequently called the Bering Strait, then 53 miles wide and only 144' deep. East of the Caspian, Peter did not have much luck, as he was soon met by the army of the Khan of Khiva. The Russians won the initial engagement and were invited into the city where they were divided up for billeting and then were systematically slaughtered, group by group. West of the Caspian in the area of Christian Georgia, Peter had better fortune, eventually winning the city of Derbent from then decadent Persia, along with three seaboard provinces of the eastern Caucasus Persia continued to fight, however, and later in 1732 Empress Anna, losing 15,000 Russian soldiers a year to disease, gave those Caucasian provinces back to Persia, where they remained until the time of Czar Alexander I, in the next century. (Ref. 145, 146, 147)

On the bad side of Peter's ledger was the creation of a bureau of official informers called "fiscals" and as today, when Russians sold goods to foreigners, they could receive only foreign money. He also started an internal passport system, still in use today, which binds a Russian to a f arm or a factory. Of Peter's 12 children by Catherine, only Anna and Elizabeth lived beyond the age of seven. Catherine was made officially Empress of all Russia in 1722 and when Peter died in January, 1725 she continued to rule. Peter's death had to do with a chronic urinary tract problem (he had passed numerous stones) and apparently he developed an obstruction in his bladder from stone or cancer of the prostate, along with infection. At autopsy he had gangrene of the bladder and adjacent tissues. There was no evidence of syphilis, as has been intimated by a few authors in the past. (Ref. 148) The real ruler during Catherine I's short reign was Peter's old, close friend Menshikov, also of very humble origins. Catherine died in 1727, succeeded by Peter II (Peter's son by Eudoxia, his first wife) and Menshikov was exiled. But Peter II died of small-pox in 1730 and Anna, daughter of Ivan V, and the widowed Duchess of Courland, became Empress for the next 10 years. On her death the infant Ivan VI, grandson of her elder sister, Catherine of Mecklenburg, inherited the throne, only to be shortly imprisoned for 22 years, while Elizabeth, Peter's daughter, helped by the guards regiment became Empress from 1741 to 1762. Although never married officially she may have secretly married her lover, Alexis Razhumovsky, whom she raised from commoner to count. Following Elizabeth came a short reign of Peter III (another of Peter the Great's grandsons) and then his grandson's German wife, Catherine II the Great21. (Ref. 149) This Catherine had assumed power when she schemed with her lover, the guard, the army and the navy to force her weak husband to resign as czar. Shortly thereafter the poor husband was either murdered or just died. (Ref. 150) Superficially she was a sophisticated ruler, carrying on correspondence with Voltaire and other European intellectuals, but at home she let social reforms die and was actually concerned only with increasing her territories. She preserved her power by cultivating the Imperial Guard and satisfying the noble class. The urban population rose to about 2,000,000, while the serfs' lives became more degraded. In 1773 Emelian Pugachev, a Don Cossack, led an uprising of peasants, Cossacks of southeastern Russia and minority groups of Kalmuks and Bushkirsalls along the Ural and Volga rivers. The stage had been set by the long history of serfdom and the attachment of peasants to factories, intolerance and discrimination toward the various tribes in the Volga region, administration corruption, abuse of power by the gentry, crushing tax burdens and intolerable conditions in the army. Religion also became a factor when most of the Cossacks, who were "old Believers", were forced to shave upon conscription. At the time of that rebellion Russia was at war with Turkey and busy with the partitions of Poland but when that was settled government troops put down the rebellion (1775) and then executed Pugachev. But the primary causes of the movement remained. (Ref. 151, 152)

We have mentioned Catherine's participation in the partitions of Poland in section III, E, I, above. At the end of the century Catherine II had finally defeated the Tatar Khanate of the Crimea, getting control of the north shore of the Black Sea. That portion of the steppe, which included the Ukraine and the grasslands to the east, was far more valuable than the territories which ended up under the control of Austria and Turkey. (Ref. 154) It was Dutch money, loaned to Catherine 11 by Henry Hope and Company in the amount of 57,000,000 francs that made that conquering expedition to the Black Sea possible. (Ref. 155) Iron and copper ores, along with plenty of charcoal, all from the Urals, allowed great expansion of armament industries and general industrialization. (Ref. 156) In 1771 plague killed 56,672 people in Moscow alone, but an enlarged food supply through the use of the plow overcame those losses so that the population actually increased from about 12,500,000 in 1724 to 21,000,000 by 1796. Catherine introduced smallpox inoculation through an English physician in 1768. (Ref. 157)

A little more about the Russian science at this period is of interest. M.V. Lomonosov was the father of Russian science, doing fine work in molecular physics, chemistry, optics, electricity and in the development of a law of the conservation of matter. He founded the Russian Academy of Science. It was I.I. Shuvalov who founded the University of Moscow in 1755. Leonard Euler, born in Switzerland, did most of his work at the Academy in St. Petersburg. He was the greatest mathematician of the century, developing calculus and some aspects of astronomy. He was the first to develop algorithmic devices and use the concepts of "e", "Pi", and "i" for various constants and an imaginary number, respectively. (Ref.158)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

5 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

10 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

11 [86] HANSEN, James, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

12 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

13 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

14 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

17 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

18 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

19 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

20 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

21 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

22 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

23 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

24 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

25 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

26 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

27 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

28 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

29 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

30 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

31 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

32 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

33 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

34 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

35 [47] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

36 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

37 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

38 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

39 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

40 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

41 [181] RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

42 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

43 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

44 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

45 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

48 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

49 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

50 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

51 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

52 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

53 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

54 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

55 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

56 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

57 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

58 [272] Tong, ENZHENG; Leng, Jian and WANGDUI, SUOLANG, "Unraveling Tibetan Prehistory at Karuo", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 62, Sept./Oct. 1982.

59 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE de, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

60 [147] MITFORD, Nancy, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

61 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

62 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

63 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

64 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

65 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

66 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

67 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

68 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

69 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

70 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

71 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

72 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

73 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

74 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

75 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

76 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

77 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

78 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

79 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

80 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

81 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

82 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

83 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

84 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

85 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

86 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

87 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

88 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

89 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

90 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

91 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

92 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

93 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

94 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

95 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

96 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

97 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

98 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

99 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

100 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

101 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

102 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

103 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

104 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

105 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

106 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

107 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

108 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

109 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

110 [214] THOMSON, DANIEL, "The Ebb & Flow of Infection", Journal of the American Medical Assoc. 235: Vol. 3, page 269, Jan 19, 1976).

111 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

112 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

113 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

114 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

115 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

116 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

117 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

118 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

119 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

120 [54] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

121 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

122 [110] JUDGE, JOSEPH, The Travail of Ireland", National Geographic 1159: 432-441, Apr. 1981.

123 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

124 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

125 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

126 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

127 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

128 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

129 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

130 [105] HYMAN, RANDALL, - "Fiery Images of Continental Drift", Smithsonian 12: 52-63, Jan. 1982.

131 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

132 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

133 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

134 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

135 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

136 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

137 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

138 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

139 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

140 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

141 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

142 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

143 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

144 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

145 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

146 [53] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

147 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

148 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

149 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

150 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE g., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

151 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE g., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

152 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

153 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

154 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

155 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

156 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

157 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

158 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE g., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

1.  Up until this date Venice had preserved its own constitution and closed citizenship throughout the centuries. (Ref. 17)

2.  One must distinguish between the Fredericks I, II, and III of Germany in the 12th to the 15th centuries and these Fredericks, who were electors and kings of Prussia

3.  Frederick Wilhelm I married his Hanoverian first cousin, Sophia Dorothea, daughter of the future king George I of England

4.  The Silesian wars between 1740 and 1745 were actually part of what is often called the War of the Austrian Succession, as a coalition of European powers tried to block the accession of Maria Theresa

5.   Actually, as Maria Theresa officially came to power at the Treaty of Aix-la-chapelle of 1748, ending the War of the Austrian Succession, Silesia was temporarily given to Prussia. (Ref. 43)

6.  The husband of Maria Theresa, duke of Lorraine and grand duke of Tuscany, was given the title of Emperor Francis I, although he had very limited authority

7.  Negotiated by John Methuen actually to better encircle Spain, which was loyal to the Duke of Anjou, Philip V and the French. (Ref. 58)

8.  Quotation from Braudel (Ref. 70), page 85

9.  The Jacobins were a political club named after their meeting place, a Dominican monastery. Jacobin was the Parisian name for Dominican. (Ref. 78)

10.  Braudel (Ref. 83) says that Amsterdam had only 200,000 at the end of this century. This only demonstrates the uncertainty of population estimates

11.  There were 4,250 miles of inland waterways, all developed privately or by stock companies. (Ref. 96)

12.  50% of E1ritish iron was used for horseshoes. (Ref. 97)

13.  England's total population was at about 8,000,000. (Ref. 102)

14.   One pound of tea makes almost 300 cups. (Ref. 103)

15.  George Frederic Handel was born in Halle, Germany, but moved to England in 1712 at age 27

16.  This was also true of Prussia and Austria

17.  By 1715 these iron works had produced some 13,000 cannons and by 1720 there was an annual output of 20,000 muskets.

18.  Moscow also suffered severely from the plague later in 1770 and 1790. (Ref. 141)

19.  Thus, the later communism was not exactly new to the Russian people

20.  This canal took 20,000 men four years to build. (Ref. 144)

21.  Born Sophia-Augusta of Anhalt Zerbst. (Ref. 153)